<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Emotional Intelligence on Figuring it Out</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/tags/emotional-intelligence/</link><description>Recent content in Emotional Intelligence on Figuring it Out</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ashleyedds.dev/tags/emotional-intelligence/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>When Your Nervous System Says "Run": The Courage to Give People Who Scare You a Chance</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/growth-through-uncomfortable-encounters/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/growth-through-uncomfortable-encounters/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/growth-through-uncomfortable-encounters/cover.png" alt="Featured image of post When Your Nervous System Says "Run": The Courage to Give People Who Scare You a Chance" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;My nervous system went into overdrive the moment I met her. Everything about this person screamed &amp;ldquo;threat&amp;rdquo; to my conflict-averse brain—the confident way she spoke about her accomplishments, the casual mention of impressive experiences, the ease with which she navigated conversations I found intimidating. Coming from what I perceived as a humble background, I felt instantly small and easily dismissed. &lt;em&gt;Who am I to this person with all these accolades?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every instinct told me to politely excuse myself and avoid future interactions. Instead, I made one of the most transformative decisions of my professional life: I chose to stay and engage with the discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="when-fear-masks-opportunity"&gt;When Fear Masks Opportunity
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;As leaders, we&amp;rsquo;re constantly pushing ourselves out of our comfort zones—whether it&amp;rsquo;s having difficult conversations, asking challenging questions, or simply letting people know when we&amp;rsquo;re upset rather than sugarcoating our feelings. Yet when that alarm bell triggers during first encounters, it feels easiest to retreat and minimize future contact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned from intentionally engaging with people who initially scared me: that nervous system response isn&amp;rsquo;t always signaling danger. Sometimes, it&amp;rsquo;s responding to something unfamiliar—and unfamiliar is often where our greatest growth lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I&amp;rsquo;ve consciously chosen discomfort over avoidance, several encounters stand out as particularly meaningful. Some of those people are now among my closest friends and most trusted advisors. The person I mentioned earlier? She&amp;rsquo;s someone I confide in regularly, someone who serves as both mirror and lighthouse when I need honest feedback. It turns out her apparent bragging was armor against her own self-consciousness—the same way my withdrawal was mine. We shared similar values but applied them differently, which is exactly why she could offer perspectives I couldn&amp;rsquo;t reach alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-learning-lives-in-both-outcomes"&gt;The Learning Lives in Both Outcomes
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are other meaningful encounters,however, that didn&amp;rsquo;t blossom into lasting friendships, but they taught me invaluable lessons about myself and others. In both cases, my initial discomfort was partially warranted—there were genuine misalignments in values or communication styles that made deep connection difficult. But engaging authentically allowed me to understand &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; I felt triggered, what those reactions revealed about my own growth edges, and how to trust my judgment more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beauty lies in this: whether the relationship flourishes or fades, you&amp;rsquo;ve gained crucial data about yourself. You&amp;rsquo;ve practiced assuming positive intent, stretched your emotional intelligence, and hopefully offered something meaningful to the other person in return. Most importantly, you&amp;rsquo;ve learned to distinguish between your nervous system responding to genuine incompatibility versus simply responding to difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="practical-steps-for-engaging-with-discomfort"&gt;Practical Steps for Engaging with Discomfort
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start with perspective-shifting.&lt;/strong&gt; Before your next networking event or team meeting, remind yourself that your initial discomfort might be pointing toward growth, not danger. When you meet someone who triggers that alarm, pause and ask: &amp;ldquo;What if I don&amp;rsquo;t know them well enough to judge? What might their perspective be?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assume positive intent deliberately.&lt;/strong&gt; This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean ignoring red flags—it means giving people the benefit of the doubt when your nervous system reacts to unfamiliarity rather than actual threat. Ask yourself: &amp;ldquo;What if their confidence comes from a place of sharing rather than showing off? What if their directness is clarity, not aggression?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engage with curiosity.&lt;/strong&gt; Instead of defensive questioning, try genuine inquiry. &amp;ldquo;Tell me more about that project&amp;rdquo; instead of internal skepticism. &amp;ldquo;How did you develop that approach?&amp;rdquo; rather than immediate judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust the learning process.&lt;/strong&gt; Whether the relationship deepens or remains surface-level, you&amp;rsquo;re building emotional agility and expanding your leadership capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-courage-to-stay-present"&gt;The Courage to Stay Present
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In our hyperconnected yet increasingly polarized world, the ability to sit with discomfort and engage authentically across differences isn&amp;rsquo;t just a nice-to-have—it&amp;rsquo;s essential leadership currency. The people who challenge us, who make us squirm a little in their presence, often hold the keys to our next level of growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of my most valuable professional relationships started with that stomach-dropping feeling of &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t belong here&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;This person is too much for me.&amp;rdquo; Learning to distinguish between productive discomfort and genuine warning signals has become one of my most valuable leadership skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your nervous system will always have opinions. But you get to choose whether to let those opinions make your decisions—or use them as data points in a much richer conversation about growth, connection, and possibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about you?&lt;/strong&gt; Have you ever been surprised by a relationship that started with discomfort? I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear your stories in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*The image for this post was generated by AI&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Leadership Paradox: Why Showing Your Unhappiness Makes You a Better Leader</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/leadership-paradox/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/leadership-paradox/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/leadership-paradox/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The Leadership Paradox: Why Showing Your Unhappiness Makes You a Better Leader" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;As leaders, we&amp;rsquo;re often taught that emotional control is paramount. We learn to stay calm under pressure, think before we speak, and approach every situation with level-headed rationality. But what if this approach—while valuable—is missing a crucial component of effective leadership?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-feedback-that-changed-everything"&gt;The Feedback That Changed Everything
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;During my participation in a leadership accelerator program at Relias, I received feedback that fundamentally challenged how I viewed effective leadership. The comprehensive assessment revealed something I hadn&amp;rsquo;t considered: my pride in remaining emotionally detached might actually be limiting my effectiveness as a leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conversation involved a leader I deeply respect—someone whose approach differs completely from mine yet achieves remarkable results. Through our discussion with a facilitator from our parent company, an uncomfortable truth emerged about my leadership style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-default-leadership-response"&gt;My Default Leadership Response
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;For years, I&amp;rsquo;ve operated under a specific framework when facing challenging situations or feeling upset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove myself from the immediate situation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process emotions privately until I feel calm and level-headed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Return to address the issue without emotional involvement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on constructive, forward-moving solutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach felt rational, professional, and respectful. It aligned with my personal values and seemed to avoid the pitfalls of reactive, emotion-driven communication that I&amp;rsquo;d witnessed create problems in other contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-surprising-truth-about-leadership-communication"&gt;The Surprising Truth About Leadership Communication
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The feedback I received was both simple and profound: &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s important as a leader that you sometimes let people know that you are unhappy with them.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This statement struck me like lightning because it ran completely counter to my self-image as a leader. I had spent considerable effort developing systems to avoid communicating emotionally, believing this made me more effective and professional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-emotional-detachment-can-backfire"&gt;Why Emotional Detachment Can Backfire
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I learned through this experience is that my well-intentioned approach was creating an unintended consequence. By removing all emotion from my communication, I was inadvertently:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Downplaying the severity of situations&lt;/strong&gt; that warranted concern&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Depriving team members of important contextual information&lt;/strong&gt; about the impact of their actions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Missing opportunities for immediate course correction&lt;/strong&gt; through emotional feedback&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reducing the motivational impact&lt;/strong&gt; of my leadership communication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-strategic-value-of-showing-unhappiness"&gt;The Strategic Value of Showing Unhappiness
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The revelation helped me understand that a leader&amp;rsquo;s unhappiness with a situation serves multiple strategic purposes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="immediate-signal-strength"&gt;Immediate Signal Strength
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;When team members see that their leader is genuinely upset about an outcome, it immediately communicates the gravity of the situation in ways that calm, rational feedback cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="creating-coachable-moments"&gt;Creating Coachable Moments
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;That moment when someone thinks, &amp;ldquo;Oh no, my boss is upset with me because of this&amp;rdquo; becomes a powerful catalyst for self-reflection and behavioral change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="authentic-relationship-building"&gt;Authentic Relationship Building
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Showing genuine emotion (when appropriate) demonstrates that you&amp;rsquo;re invested in outcomes and care deeply about the team&amp;rsquo;s success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="clear-expectation-setting"&gt;Clear Expectation Setting
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your emotional response helps team members calibrate their understanding of what matters most and what standards they&amp;rsquo;re expected to meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-two-phase-leadership-approach"&gt;The Two-Phase Leadership Approach
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The key insight wasn&amp;rsquo;t to abandon my thoughtful, rational approach entirely, but rather to implement a two-phase strategy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="phase-1-immediate-emotional-feedback"&gt;Phase 1: Immediate Emotional Feedback
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Allow team members to witness and understand your genuine reaction to situations when they occur. This provides immediate context and impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="phase-2-reflective-problem-solving"&gt;Phase 2: Reflective Problem-Solving
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Later, when emotions have settled, engage in the deeper, analytical conversation about what happened and how to improve moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="balancing-emotional-intelligence-with-authentic-leadership"&gt;Balancing Emotional Intelligence with Authentic Leadership
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This experience taught me that effective leadership isn&amp;rsquo;t about eliminating emotion—it&amp;rsquo;s about using emotion strategically. The goal isn&amp;rsquo;t to become reactive or lose professional composure, but rather to ensure that the full picture of your leadership perspective is communicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your frustration, disappointment, or concern about a situation is itself valuable information for your team. It helps them understand not just what went wrong, but how significantly it impacted the broader goals and relationships they care about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="implementing-constructive-emotional-leadership"&gt;Implementing Constructive Emotional Leadership
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re like me and tend toward emotional restraint in leadership situations, consider these strategies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow Initial Reactions:&lt;/strong&gt; Give yourself permission to show genuine concern or disappointment when it first occurs, rather than immediately suppressing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use Emotion as Data:&lt;/strong&gt; Treat your emotional responses as valuable information to share with your team about priorities and expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow Up Thoughtfully:&lt;/strong&gt; Maintain your commitment to reflective, solution-oriented conversations, but don&amp;rsquo;t let them replace the immediate emotional feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Model Emotional Intelligence:&lt;/strong&gt; Show your team that emotions can be acknowledged and expressed professionally without derailing productive communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-leadership-growth-mindset"&gt;The Leadership Growth Mindset
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most valuable aspect of this feedback was how it challenged my assumptions about what makes a &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; leader. Growth in leadership often requires us to examine our comfortable patterns and consider whether they&amp;rsquo;re serving our teams as effectively as we believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leader who gave me this feedback approaches leadership completely differently than I do, yet achieves incredible results. This experience reminded me that there&amp;rsquo;s no single template for effective leadership—but there are always opportunities to expand our toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="moving-forward-emotion-as-leadership-tool"&gt;Moving Forward: Emotion as Leadership Tool
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, I&amp;rsquo;m still the same person who values thoughtful, rational problem-solving. But I&amp;rsquo;ve added a new dimension to my leadership approach: the strategic use of authentic emotional communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When something goes wrong now, I don&amp;rsquo;t hide my disappointment. I let my team see that I&amp;rsquo;m genuinely upset about the outcome, because that unhappiness is part of the feedback they need to fully understand the situation and grow from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal isn&amp;rsquo;t to become more emotional as a leader—it&amp;rsquo;s to become more complete in how we communicate the full spectrum of our leadership perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What surprising feedback have you received that changed your approach to leadership? How do you balance emotional authenticity with professional communication in your role?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>