<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Communication on Figuring it Out</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/tags/communication/</link><description>Recent content in Communication on Figuring it Out</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ashleyedds.dev/tags/communication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Leadership Paradox: Why Showing Your Unhappiness Makes You a Better Leader</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/leadership-paradox/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/leadership-paradox/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/leadership-paradox/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The Leadership Paradox: Why Showing Your Unhappiness Makes You a Better Leader" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;As leaders, we&amp;rsquo;re often taught that emotional control is paramount. We learn to stay calm under pressure, think before we speak, and approach every situation with level-headed rationality. But what if this approach—while valuable—is missing a crucial component of effective leadership?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-feedback-that-changed-everything"&gt;The Feedback That Changed Everything
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;During my participation in a leadership accelerator program at Relias, I received feedback that fundamentally challenged how I viewed effective leadership. The comprehensive assessment revealed something I hadn&amp;rsquo;t considered: my pride in remaining emotionally detached might actually be limiting my effectiveness as a leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conversation involved a leader I deeply respect—someone whose approach differs completely from mine yet achieves remarkable results. Through our discussion with a facilitator from our parent company, an uncomfortable truth emerged about my leadership style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-default-leadership-response"&gt;My Default Leadership Response
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;For years, I&amp;rsquo;ve operated under a specific framework when facing challenging situations or feeling upset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove myself from the immediate situation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process emotions privately until I feel calm and level-headed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Return to address the issue without emotional involvement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on constructive, forward-moving solutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach felt rational, professional, and respectful. It aligned with my personal values and seemed to avoid the pitfalls of reactive, emotion-driven communication that I&amp;rsquo;d witnessed create problems in other contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-surprising-truth-about-leadership-communication"&gt;The Surprising Truth About Leadership Communication
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The feedback I received was both simple and profound: &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s important as a leader that you sometimes let people know that you are unhappy with them.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This statement struck me like lightning because it ran completely counter to my self-image as a leader. I had spent considerable effort developing systems to avoid communicating emotionally, believing this made me more effective and professional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-emotional-detachment-can-backfire"&gt;Why Emotional Detachment Can Backfire
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I learned through this experience is that my well-intentioned approach was creating an unintended consequence. By removing all emotion from my communication, I was inadvertently:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Downplaying the severity of situations&lt;/strong&gt; that warranted concern&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Depriving team members of important contextual information&lt;/strong&gt; about the impact of their actions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Missing opportunities for immediate course correction&lt;/strong&gt; through emotional feedback&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reducing the motivational impact&lt;/strong&gt; of my leadership communication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-strategic-value-of-showing-unhappiness"&gt;The Strategic Value of Showing Unhappiness
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The revelation helped me understand that a leader&amp;rsquo;s unhappiness with a situation serves multiple strategic purposes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="immediate-signal-strength"&gt;Immediate Signal Strength
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;When team members see that their leader is genuinely upset about an outcome, it immediately communicates the gravity of the situation in ways that calm, rational feedback cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="creating-coachable-moments"&gt;Creating Coachable Moments
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;That moment when someone thinks, &amp;ldquo;Oh no, my boss is upset with me because of this&amp;rdquo; becomes a powerful catalyst for self-reflection and behavioral change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="authentic-relationship-building"&gt;Authentic Relationship Building
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Showing genuine emotion (when appropriate) demonstrates that you&amp;rsquo;re invested in outcomes and care deeply about the team&amp;rsquo;s success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="clear-expectation-setting"&gt;Clear Expectation Setting
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your emotional response helps team members calibrate their understanding of what matters most and what standards they&amp;rsquo;re expected to meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-two-phase-leadership-approach"&gt;The Two-Phase Leadership Approach
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The key insight wasn&amp;rsquo;t to abandon my thoughtful, rational approach entirely, but rather to implement a two-phase strategy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="phase-1-immediate-emotional-feedback"&gt;Phase 1: Immediate Emotional Feedback
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Allow team members to witness and understand your genuine reaction to situations when they occur. This provides immediate context and impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="phase-2-reflective-problem-solving"&gt;Phase 2: Reflective Problem-Solving
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Later, when emotions have settled, engage in the deeper, analytical conversation about what happened and how to improve moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="balancing-emotional-intelligence-with-authentic-leadership"&gt;Balancing Emotional Intelligence with Authentic Leadership
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This experience taught me that effective leadership isn&amp;rsquo;t about eliminating emotion—it&amp;rsquo;s about using emotion strategically. The goal isn&amp;rsquo;t to become reactive or lose professional composure, but rather to ensure that the full picture of your leadership perspective is communicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your frustration, disappointment, or concern about a situation is itself valuable information for your team. It helps them understand not just what went wrong, but how significantly it impacted the broader goals and relationships they care about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="implementing-constructive-emotional-leadership"&gt;Implementing Constructive Emotional Leadership
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re like me and tend toward emotional restraint in leadership situations, consider these strategies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow Initial Reactions:&lt;/strong&gt; Give yourself permission to show genuine concern or disappointment when it first occurs, rather than immediately suppressing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use Emotion as Data:&lt;/strong&gt; Treat your emotional responses as valuable information to share with your team about priorities and expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow Up Thoughtfully:&lt;/strong&gt; Maintain your commitment to reflective, solution-oriented conversations, but don&amp;rsquo;t let them replace the immediate emotional feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Model Emotional Intelligence:&lt;/strong&gt; Show your team that emotions can be acknowledged and expressed professionally without derailing productive communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-leadership-growth-mindset"&gt;The Leadership Growth Mindset
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most valuable aspect of this feedback was how it challenged my assumptions about what makes a &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; leader. Growth in leadership often requires us to examine our comfortable patterns and consider whether they&amp;rsquo;re serving our teams as effectively as we believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leader who gave me this feedback approaches leadership completely differently than I do, yet achieves incredible results. This experience reminded me that there&amp;rsquo;s no single template for effective leadership—but there are always opportunities to expand our toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="moving-forward-emotion-as-leadership-tool"&gt;Moving Forward: Emotion as Leadership Tool
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, I&amp;rsquo;m still the same person who values thoughtful, rational problem-solving. But I&amp;rsquo;ve added a new dimension to my leadership approach: the strategic use of authentic emotional communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When something goes wrong now, I don&amp;rsquo;t hide my disappointment. I let my team see that I&amp;rsquo;m genuinely upset about the outcome, because that unhappiness is part of the feedback they need to fully understand the situation and grow from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal isn&amp;rsquo;t to become more emotional as a leader—it&amp;rsquo;s to become more complete in how we communicate the full spectrum of our leadership perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What surprising feedback have you received that changed your approach to leadership? How do you balance emotional authenticity with professional communication in your role?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mindful Curiosity</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/mindful-curiosity/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/mindful-curiosity/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/mindful-curiosity/cover.jpeg" alt="Featured image of post Mindful Curiosity" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my most recent coaching session, I sought guidance on an upcoming meeting with my management colleagues, directors, and SVP. I was nervous because I had received information about a change I didn’t agree with—one that I believed would significantly impact my team. &lt;em&gt;(It turned out my concerns were based on a misunderstanding, and my anxiety was unnecessary.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I explained my concerns, the questions I had, and my apprehension about how &amp;ldquo;pushing back&amp;rdquo; might be perceived, my coach interrupted with a thought-provoking question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do you think you&amp;rsquo;re pushing back? What I hear is your curiosity about the change and a desire to understand where it’s coming from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That question completely reframed my perspective. Why did I instinctively view my desire to understand leadership decisions as resistance? Shouldn’t gathering context and reasoning be part of my role as an effective change agent for my team? Isn’t deeper understanding essential for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensuring I have the right information before expressing concerns?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Framing concerns in a productive and constructive way?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This internalized fear of questioning leadership likely stems from deep-seated patterns in my psychology—an exploration for another time. But recognizing this mindset allows me to be more mindful in leadership interactions. Moving forward, when I feel anxiety creeping in, I’ll pause and ask myself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am I feeling anxious because I’m mislabeling my curiosity as pushback?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="strengthening-my-curiosity-muscle"&gt;Strengthening My Curiosity Muscle
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since this realization, I’ve also noticed other ways my curiosity (or lack thereof) manifests. Sometimes, I accept information or suggestions at face value without deeper exploration. If I want to continue growing as a technical leader, I need to challenge myself to dig deeper and ensure I have a well-rounded understanding before making decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-commitment-to-mindful-curiosity"&gt;My Commitment to Mindful Curiosity
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;To foster this growth, I’m setting the following personal challenges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reframing curiosity&lt;/strong&gt; – Asking leadership questions to understand a decision isn’t an act of defiance; it’s a tool for learning, effective communication, and advocacy for my team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seeking deeper understanding&lt;/strong&gt; – Instead of passively accepting information, I’ll actively engage, research, and explore different perspectives to develop a more informed viewpoint.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curiosity isn’t resistance—it’s a leadership strength. If I can embrace this mindset, I’ll not only become a stronger advocate for my team but also continue evolving as a leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about you?&lt;/strong&gt; Have you ever mistaken curiosity for pushback? How do you challenge yourself to ask better questions and seek deeper understanding? Let’s discuss in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>