<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Personal Growth on Figuring it Out</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/categories/personal-growth/</link><description>Recent content in Personal Growth on Figuring it Out</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ashleyedds.dev/categories/personal-growth/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Incoming: Personal Rebrand</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/incoming-personal-rebrand/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/incoming-personal-rebrand/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/incoming-personal-rebrand/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Incoming: Personal Rebrand" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fair warning: this post is about to get introspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I participated in a Quantum Bloom Women&amp;rsquo;s Leadership Session provided by Relias, and let&amp;rsquo;s just say it&amp;rsquo;s one of those experiences that leaves you questioning some fundamental things about yourself. The good kind of questioning, though—the kind that makes you realize you&amp;rsquo;ve been carrying around beliefs that stopped serving you a long time ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session focused on examining the stories we tell ourselves—the beliefs and values that shape our professional identities but don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily help us grow. While the conversation touched on gender dynamics in the workplace, what I&amp;rsquo;m taking away goes deeper. It&amp;rsquo;s about the narratives we create, the shields we carry, and what happens when you finally decide to put them down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="when-your-heroes-have-the-same-doubts-you-do"&gt;When Your Heroes Have the Same Doubts You Do
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was in a breakout session with two colleagues I genuinely admire. These are women I consider experts in their fields—talented, productive, excellent communicators who build strong communities and possess deep knowledge in their areas of ownership. They&amp;rsquo;re the kind of professionals I look up to and think, &amp;ldquo;Yeah, that&amp;rsquo;s who I want to be like.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So imagine my surprise when both of them started talking about their insecurities. About not feeling good enough for their roles. About questioning whether they belong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These incredible, accomplished women were expressing the exact same doubts I carry around every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve been reading my posts for any length of time, you know my particular flavor of self-doubt. I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;m technical enough. I moved into management as a mid-level engineer without a computer science degree, having come to tech through a bootcamp as a second career. This insecurity was cemented early on when a leader told me that if I went into management before becoming a senior engineer, I&amp;rsquo;d never earn the respect of strong technical talent. They said senior developers wouldn&amp;rsquo;t respect me as a leader because of my lack of technical depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That comment? It stuck. Hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-shield-i-didnt-know-i-was-carrying"&gt;The Shield I Didn&amp;rsquo;t Know I Was Carrying
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the complicated part: this belief has actually served me in some ways. I&amp;rsquo;ve used this narrative to brand myself as a different kind of engineering leader—one who brings skills beyond the purely technical, who can fill gaps in a strongly technical leadership team. And honestly? That story has worked. It&amp;rsquo;s proven valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;rsquo;s also been a cage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve avoided situations where I&amp;rsquo;d be technically challenged. I&amp;rsquo;ve controlled the narrative by preemptively telling people—especially those I perceive as highly technical—that I&amp;rsquo;m &amp;ldquo;not a technical leader.&amp;rdquo; By saying it first, I manage their expectations and protect myself from judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that while there&amp;rsquo;s power in controlling how others see you, this approach has been unnecessarily reducing my value. It undermines how good I actually am at my job. And I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; good at my job. I&amp;rsquo;m very good at what I do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I shared this belief in our breakout session, the women I admire pushed back immediately. They told me I am technical. That they&amp;rsquo;ve always seen me as technical. That this story I tell myself doesn&amp;rsquo;t match the reality they see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we went around sharing our limiting beliefs, we were all genuinely shocked to discover we felt similarly diminished in different ways. Watching these talented women undersell their own skill sets was both disheartening and revealing—revealing of how we&amp;rsquo;ve internalized expectations and lost trust in ourselves over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-moment-everything-shifted"&gt;The Moment Everything Shifted
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the end of the exercise, we were asked to rewrite our limiting beliefs. My first attempt was predictably safe: &amp;ldquo;My lack of technical skills does not diminish my value in my role.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the women in my group stopped me cold. &amp;ldquo;You need to stop saying you&amp;rsquo;re not technical. Period. That&amp;rsquo;s not serving you and it never will.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I tried again. This time, I wrote something simple and terrifying: &lt;strong&gt;I am a technical leader.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There it is. That&amp;rsquo;s the rebrand. No more hedging, no more caveating, no more controlling the narrative by diminishing myself first. This blog will no longer be a space for ruminating on why I&amp;rsquo;m not enough. I&amp;rsquo;m going to own what I bring, challenge myself, and actually grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-perfection-problem"&gt;The Perfection Problem
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another theme that emerged in our session was the pressure to be perfect. Many of us talked about growing up with expectations to excel at everything—to be the A+ student, the top of the class, the one who never makes mistakes. While this isn&amp;rsquo;t exclusively a gendered experience, I do think we internalize these expectations in different ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That people-pleasing, teacher&amp;rsquo;s-pet programming from our youth? Sure, it&amp;rsquo;s part of why we&amp;rsquo;re successful. But at what cost? How much are we missing out on because we won&amp;rsquo;t put ourselves in situations where we might not be the best in the room?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has to be a way to keep our drive while establishing healthier boundaries. It requires checking in with ourselves when we&amp;rsquo;re obsessing over the perfect wording of an email or avoiding an opportunity because we&amp;rsquo;re not guaranteed to excel. We need to allow ourselves to be in uncomfortable spaces, to potentially fail, and to see what happens when we stop limiting ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-communication-style-trap"&gt;The Communication Style Trap
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The third insight that really landed for me was about how we compare ourselves to colleagues who use more direct, assertive, sometimes aggressive communication styles. Many of us bring more empathetic, open-minded approaches to getting things done, yet we watch the more abrupt style get rewarded more often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes sense when you consider that corporate America was designed by and for a specific demographic. The system cyclically supports certain communication styles and ways of working. (If you haven&amp;rsquo;t read the Harvard Business Review article &lt;a class="link" href="https://hbr.org/2021/02/stop-telling-women-they-have-imposter-syndrome" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;&amp;ldquo;Stop Telling Women They Have Imposter Syndrome,&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; I highly recommend it—it articulates this dynamic perfectly.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s what I realized: someone who can learn from direct, assertive approaches &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; embrace empathetic, holistic communication? That person has access to a genuine superpower. Knowing when to be direct and when to be empathetic, understanding when to focus on goals and when to engage with someone as a whole person—this isn&amp;rsquo;t a weakness. It&amp;rsquo;s flexibility and range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The corporate value system is shifting, slowly but surely. I hope my generation of leaders—those of us who tend to be more thoughtful about the whole person and the whole situation—can help accelerate that change. We don&amp;rsquo;t need to place arbitrary value on one approach over another just because of historical precedent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-comes-next"&gt;What Comes Next
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This conversation was a turning point. I&amp;rsquo;m walking away with a reworked belief system, one that actually supports who I am and where I want to go instead of holding me back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to be clear: while these conversations often center on gender, this isn&amp;rsquo;t about attacking anyone. It&amp;rsquo;s about acknowledging that certain dynamics exist in workplace cultures—dynamics that don&amp;rsquo;t always support different approaches or perspectives equally. For those navigating multiple intersections of identity, these dynamics can be even more complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to seeing how things evolve. I&amp;rsquo;m excited to keep having these conversations with colleagues. And honestly? I&amp;rsquo;m excited to see where this rebrand takes me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here we go. New narrative, same person—just finally willing to own all of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And hey, to the women who were in my breakout session—if you&amp;rsquo;re reading this, thank you. You&amp;rsquo;re both incredible, you absolutely have this, and I&amp;rsquo;m lucky to work alongside you. I can&amp;rsquo;t wait to see your own rebrands in action.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Seven Years at Relias: Three Lessons That Transformed My Career Journey</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/seven-years-relias-career-lessons-learned/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/seven-years-relias-career-lessons-learned/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/seven-years-relias-career-lessons-learned/cover.png" alt="Featured image of post Seven Years at Relias: Three Lessons That Transformed My Career Journey" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today marks my seventh anniversary at Relias, a milestone that feels both surreal and significant. This is officially the longest I&amp;rsquo;ve stayed with any employer, and the longest I&amp;rsquo;ve committed to any single career path. Before joining Relias, I spent six years as a speech-language pathologist before taking the leap into software engineering through a coding bootcamp. Looking back at the person I was seven years ago, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure she would recognize the professional she&amp;rsquo;s become—though perhaps some core elements would feel familiar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-journey-of-growth-and-gratitude"&gt;The Journey of Growth and Gratitude
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;These seven years have been filled with tremendous growth, and distilling that evolution into just three key takeaways proved challenging. My learning has been rapid, consistent, and wonderfully varied. I&amp;rsquo;ve been fortunate to have incredible mentors throughout this journey—from the developers on my first team who taught me what it truly means to be a software engineer and how to navigate our codebase, to the leadership mentors who helped me identify my strengths and step confidently into my role as a leader, to my colleagues who taught me the nuances of engineering management, how to develop team members effectively, and the principles of servant leadership. Thank you to each and every person who has invested in my growth and shaped the professional I am today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="lesson-one-embracing-your-technical-identity"&gt;Lesson One: Embracing Your Technical Identity
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I AM a technical person.&lt;/strong&gt; For those who&amp;rsquo;ve followed my writing, you might be tired of hearing about my confidence struggles. But this realization is foundational, and it&amp;rsquo;s something I still navigate daily. The questions persist: Am I strong enough as a player-coach? Am I &amp;ldquo;technical enough&amp;rdquo; to continue advancing in this field?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer, definitively, is yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seven years ago, I joined Relias with just enough React and SQL knowledge to be dangerous. Today, I&amp;rsquo;m partnering with my team to modernize our integrations solution. I&amp;rsquo;m coaching team members on leveraging GitHub Copilot to troubleshoot configuration issues and get new services running. I&amp;rsquo;m mentoring emerging leaders across the company about what engineering means at Relias and how our technical systems work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evidence is clear. It&amp;rsquo;s time to own this identity and stop questioning it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="lesson-two-the-power-of-doing-hard-things"&gt;Lesson Two: The Power of Doing Hard Things
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I can do hard things.&lt;/strong&gt; (Thank you, Ms. Rachel, for this mantra!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many millennials, I grew up being labeled &amp;ldquo;gifted&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;smart.&amp;rdquo; The unintended consequence? Whenever I encountered something challenging—something that threatened that identity—I ran. If I failed, did that mean I wasn&amp;rsquo;t gifted anymore? I avoided the discomfort of not immediately excelling or achieving perfection, whether it was learning to rock climb or tackling complex projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I entered software engineering, where everything was hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coding doesn&amp;rsquo;t come naturally to me the way it might for others. I&amp;rsquo;ve had to work exceptionally hard to achieve even middle-of-the-road results. Initially, this reinforced my feelings of being &amp;ldquo;not technical enough&amp;rdquo; and prevented me from pursuing opportunities that could have accelerated my growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned: &lt;strong&gt;the space of discomfort is where growth happens&lt;/strong&gt;. I will see the other side. It might not be perfect. I might not get it right the first time. And that&amp;rsquo;s completely okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="lesson-three-know-thyself-trust-thyself"&gt;Lesson Three: Know Thyself, Trust Thyself
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Know thyself.&lt;/strong&gt; I understand my value now. I recognize my strengths. I&amp;rsquo;ve learned not to let doubts—whether internal or external—prevent me from pursuing what I know I can excel at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The times I&amp;rsquo;ve questioned my value or doubted my capabilities have stalled my growth and potentially led to missed opportunities. Staying grounded in self-knowledge keeps me on the path I&amp;rsquo;m meant to follow. This self-awareness isn&amp;rsquo;t about arrogance; it&amp;rsquo;s about having the confidence to advocate for yourself and make career decisions aligned with your authentic strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="moving-forward-with-confidence"&gt;Moving Forward with Confidence
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;These seven years at Relias have taught me that career growth isn&amp;rsquo;t linear, and transformation often happens in the spaces that feel most uncomfortable. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re considering a career transition, struggling with imposter syndrome, or questioning your technical capabilities, remember: you are more capable than you think, hard things become possible with persistence, and knowing yourself is your greatest professional asset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s your career transformation story? Have you experienced similar challenges with technical confidence or imposter syndrome? I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear about your journey in the comments below. Let&amp;rsquo;s continue learning and growing together.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Are you navigating a career transition in tech or struggling with similar confidence challenges? Connect with me on LinkedIn to continue the conversation and share insights from your own professional journey.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Efficiency Trap</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/efficiency-trap/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/efficiency-trap/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/efficiency-trap/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The Efficiency Trap" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Remember in &lt;em&gt;The Parent Trap&lt;/em&gt; when Lindsay Lohan&amp;rsquo;s characters spend the entire movie scheming to get their parents back together through increasingly elaborate plans? They could have just&amp;hellip; talked to them. But no, they needed to control every detail, orchestrate every moment, and make sure everything happened exactly their way. Spoiler alert: it got messy before it got better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s me in most work situations. I&amp;rsquo;m both Lindsay Lohans—the one with the perfectly planned strategy AND the one panicking when things don&amp;rsquo;t go according to plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-anxiety-spiral"&gt;The Anxiety Spiral
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I start to feel the anxiety of not making a decision and moving into action, it begins with a familiar tightness in my chest that expands into low-level panic. I get clammy, my mind goes blank on everything except finding a path to resolution, and I become increasingly difficult to work with as my frustration builds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has led to more than one mistake and left more than one situation with others feeling just as frustrated as I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a developer, I was used to sitting in refinement meetings where conversations would churn around technical implementation. I always felt like there was more to learn, and I never wanted us to make an incorrect choice. But now, in leadership, when I&amp;rsquo;m in meetings where my developers seem to talk in circles without making tangible progress on refinements, I start to lose it. We get caught in a swirl of what-ifs and future-proofing, completely throwing the agile process out the window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="when-just-let-me-handle-it-backfires"&gt;When &amp;ldquo;Just Let Me Handle It&amp;rdquo; Backfires
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently, I made a classic efficiency-over-effectiveness mistake. I agreed to let two of my senior developers work on a new feature set that involved separating two different user experiences with largely the same functionality and a new identity provider. In my mind, I was being efficient—trusting my team, moving quickly, not micromanaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reality? There was no insight into progress, missed requirements piled up, and what should have been a straightforward feature became a months-long saga. My desire to move fast and avoid process actually created more work, more confusion, and more stress for everyone involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had fallen into what I now call the efficiency trap—prioritizing speed and my preferred way of doing things over actually getting the right outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-coach-question-that-broke-my-brain"&gt;The Coach Question That Broke My Brain
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When my Torch coach asked me which I valued more—efficiency or effectiveness—my brain just went &amp;ldquo;buzzzzzzzz.&amp;rdquo; It didn&amp;rsquo;t compute. What do you mean there&amp;rsquo;s a difference? Getting things done correctly and quickly is what matters, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the more I sat with it, the more I realized I was creating unnecessary anxiety for myself and my team. There&amp;rsquo;s real power in letting go of needing to do something a certain way within a certain timeframe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This question hit particularly hard because my team is currently navigating two critical challenges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We need to improve our predictability quarter over quarter to help with deliverable timelines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We need to maximize the work we can produce with our current team size&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized I needed to find a reasonable middle ground. Sometimes moving quickly and being efficient is the right approach. Other times, being effective—getting the right outcome—is all that matters at the end of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="putting-it-into-practice"&gt;Putting It Into Practice
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the &amp;ldquo;just cut me a ticket and let me hack at it&amp;rdquo; disaster, I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to be more mindful about when I apply the brakes to enforce process and when I need to make a quick call and move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our upcoming quarterly planning, we&amp;rsquo;re taking time to go through epics with a fine-tooth comb, making sure requirements are defined and we&amp;rsquo;re considering all aspects of technical implementation. Maybe the pendulum has swung too far in the other direction, but I think it&amp;rsquo;s good practice for the team. Once the actual development work begins, there should be less churn because we&amp;rsquo;ll know everything from day one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Stay tuned for a future update on how this approach affects our effectiveness and predictability.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-root-of-the-problem"&gt;The Root of the Problem
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This need for control and hyper-efficiency comes from being a Type A, people-pleasing, teacher&amp;rsquo;s pet. I&amp;rsquo;ve been this way my whole life, and I think it stems from wanting to be good at what I do—starting with being successful in school and following through to today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s this underlying script that I&amp;rsquo;ve been successful because I get things done my way, quickly. Not because I was just getting the right things done, period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-this-is-changing-how-i-lead"&gt;How This Is Changing How I Lead
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This framework is still new for me in my leadership journey, but I&amp;rsquo;ve already noticed some shifts in how I approach my role:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I delegate more thoughtfully.&lt;/strong&gt; Instead of either micromanaging or completely hands-off approaches, I&amp;rsquo;m delegating to people I trust to be effective, with clear guidelines for check-ins, observable progress markers, and well-defined scope and requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I ask better questions.&lt;/strong&gt; Rather than jumping straight to &amp;ldquo;how do we do this faster,&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;m starting with &amp;ldquo;what outcome are we actually trying to achieve here?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m more comfortable with different approaches.&lt;/strong&gt; If someone on my team has a different way of reaching the same effective outcome, I&amp;rsquo;m learning to let them run with it instead of redirecting them to my preferred method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth is, some of my best work has happened when I focused on being effective first, then found efficient ways to execute. The efficiency trap had me believing that speed and control were always the answer, but sometimes the fastest path to the right outcome is the one that feels slower in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just like those scheming twins in &lt;em&gt;The Parent Trap&lt;/em&gt;, sometimes the most elaborate plan isn&amp;rsquo;t the one that gets you where you want to go—it&amp;rsquo;s the one that&amp;rsquo;s willing to adapt when life throws you a curveball.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What about you? Have you ever found yourself caught in the efficiency trap? I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear how you&amp;rsquo;ve learned to balance getting things done with getting the right things done.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>My Self-Rebrand: Owning the Room in My Own Way</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/self-rebrand/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/self-rebrand/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/self-rebrand/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post My Self-Rebrand: Owning the Room in My Own Way" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have you ever had to go through a personal rebrand?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our entire lives, we tell ourselves stories about ourselves. Others tell us stories about ourselves. And around and around it goes. Before long, all the neural pathways in our brains are deeply rooted in specific ideas, and it can be incredibly difficult to get them to move, bend, and change to fit new perspectives about our self-images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My entire life, I&amp;rsquo;ve been told I&amp;rsquo;m quiet and shy. Soft-spoken. And I am — most days it can be difficult to get my voice to carry across a dinner table, much less command a presentation space. So by extension, I never thought of myself as much of a public speaker. I assumed I was too shy, too soft-spoken, not bold or confident enough to deliver a presentation that left people walking away thinking, &lt;em&gt;“Wow, that was a great session.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, though, my role has required me to step up — presenting to large internal audiences, engaging leadership in smaller strategy sessions, and showing up with clarity and purpose. And while I’ve always felt confident in my knowledge of my team and product, I hadn’t internalized the idea that &lt;em&gt;I’m good at public speaking&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the larger forums I regularly speak at is a quarterly stakeholder review, where I summarize key accomplishments and upcoming goals. The audience spans hundreds of people, so I’ve developed a rhythm: keep it casual, keep it high-level, throw in a little humor. I know it’s not a space for deep technical dives — it’s about connection and clarity. This is where I’ve found my stride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feedback from my most recent presentation floored me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The new VP of Product said it reflected deep product knowledge and praised the strength of my partnership with my Director of Product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A fellow engineering manager joked that I must secretly be in Sales or Marketing — and meant it as a compliment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An engineer who’s usually disengaged during company-wide meetings said mine actually woke him up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And most meaningfully, an engineer I’ve admired since I was an Associate — someone I’ve always been intimidated by — reached out privately with kind words I’ll treasure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the thing: this isn’t the first time I’ve received positive feedback on my presentations. But for some reason, this time it clicked. &lt;em&gt;Maybe I am good at this.&lt;/em&gt; Maybe public speaking isn’t something I have to muscle through — maybe it’s something I’ve grown into.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can still be soft-spoken, quiet, and reserved. But that doesn’t mean I can’t also own a room when the time calls for it. It’s not either/or.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This experience taught me something valuable: we don’t have to stay locked into the stories we were told — or the ones we told ourselves. We can allow room for expansion. Growth. New neural pathways. Rebranding doesn’t mean we lose ourselves — it means we make room for who we’re becoming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever felt boxed in by an identity that no longer fits, ask yourself: &lt;em&gt;What if I’m more than that?&lt;/em&gt; Give yourself permission to evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="ready-to-rebrand-yourself"&gt;Ready to rebrand yourself?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;If this post resonated with you, I’d love to hear your story. Have you ever surprised yourself with growth in an area you thought was closed off? Drop a comment, send a message, or share this with someone who might need the nudge today.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>No Silver Linings, Just Clouds</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/just-clouds/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/just-clouds/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/just-clouds/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post No Silver Linings, Just Clouds" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;The past few weeks have been difficult. Not that everything is going terribly wrong, but things certainly aren&amp;rsquo;t going right either. And it’s not just work. Life, in general, has felt heavier than usual.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When things get tough, I try to take a step back—reflect on what’s happening, explore why I feel the way I do, and consider what I might do to shift things in a better direction. One technique that has helped in the past is &lt;a class="link" href="https://medium.com/@soulinsticts/the-self-awareness-onion-8cdba8880ad7" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;The Self-Awareness Onion&lt;/a&gt;—a method of repeatedly asking yourself why until you uncover the root cause of your emotions. (Spoiler: It’s usually not what you first think it is.) But this time, after all that introspection, I don’t have any big revelations or groundbreaking takeaways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that’s okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We tend to look for meaning in our struggles. It feels like every hard moment should come with a lesson, a path forward, or at least a silver lining. But sometimes, life is just hard, and there’s no immediate wisdom to extract from it. There’s no grand realization waiting at the end of a rough day, week, or month—just the experience of enduring it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, work piles up. Personal challenges weigh on you. Plans stall because of things outside your control. Your body and mind don’t feel like they’re cooperating. Like they say, when it rains, it pours. And in those moments, searching for a silver lining can feel exhausting—like another task you need to accomplish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if we let go of that expectation? What if we allowed ourselves to sit with the discomfort without rushing to fix it, justify it, or turn it into something profound?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s value in simply acknowledging when things are tough. Talking about the struggles, even when we don’t have a solution, helps remove the pressure to always be okay. It gives us permission to be human—to experience the full range of emotions without needing to tie them up neatly with a bow of wisdom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We share our wins, our lessons, and our transformations. But we should also share the messy in-between—the moments when things just &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt;. When we’re waiting for clarity that hasn’t come yet. When we’re not ready to look back on a hard time with a sense of resolution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if you’re in a season where things feel heavy, know that you don’t have to turn it into a learning moment right away, or at all. You don’t have to find the silver lining today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some clouds just need to pass on their own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="keep-the-conversation-going"&gt;Keep the Conversation Going
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have you ever gone through a rough patch where there wasn’t an easy takeaway? How do you sit with those moments? If this post resonates with you, I’d love to hear your thoughts in the comments. Or, if you just need a space to say, &lt;em&gt;“Yeah, it’s been tough”&lt;/em&gt;—that’s welcome too.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>