<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Leadership on Figuring it Out</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/categories/leadership/</link><description>Recent content in Leadership on Figuring it Out</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ashleyedds.dev/categories/leadership/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Incoming: Personal Rebrand</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/incoming-personal-rebrand/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/incoming-personal-rebrand/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/incoming-personal-rebrand/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Incoming: Personal Rebrand" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fair warning: this post is about to get introspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I participated in a Quantum Bloom Women&amp;rsquo;s Leadership Session provided by Relias, and let&amp;rsquo;s just say it&amp;rsquo;s one of those experiences that leaves you questioning some fundamental things about yourself. The good kind of questioning, though—the kind that makes you realize you&amp;rsquo;ve been carrying around beliefs that stopped serving you a long time ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session focused on examining the stories we tell ourselves—the beliefs and values that shape our professional identities but don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily help us grow. While the conversation touched on gender dynamics in the workplace, what I&amp;rsquo;m taking away goes deeper. It&amp;rsquo;s about the narratives we create, the shields we carry, and what happens when you finally decide to put them down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="when-your-heroes-have-the-same-doubts-you-do"&gt;When Your Heroes Have the Same Doubts You Do
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was in a breakout session with two colleagues I genuinely admire. These are women I consider experts in their fields—talented, productive, excellent communicators who build strong communities and possess deep knowledge in their areas of ownership. They&amp;rsquo;re the kind of professionals I look up to and think, &amp;ldquo;Yeah, that&amp;rsquo;s who I want to be like.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So imagine my surprise when both of them started talking about their insecurities. About not feeling good enough for their roles. About questioning whether they belong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These incredible, accomplished women were expressing the exact same doubts I carry around every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve been reading my posts for any length of time, you know my particular flavor of self-doubt. I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;m technical enough. I moved into management as a mid-level engineer without a computer science degree, having come to tech through a bootcamp as a second career. This insecurity was cemented early on when a leader told me that if I went into management before becoming a senior engineer, I&amp;rsquo;d never earn the respect of strong technical talent. They said senior developers wouldn&amp;rsquo;t respect me as a leader because of my lack of technical depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That comment? It stuck. Hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-shield-i-didnt-know-i-was-carrying"&gt;The Shield I Didn&amp;rsquo;t Know I Was Carrying
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the complicated part: this belief has actually served me in some ways. I&amp;rsquo;ve used this narrative to brand myself as a different kind of engineering leader—one who brings skills beyond the purely technical, who can fill gaps in a strongly technical leadership team. And honestly? That story has worked. It&amp;rsquo;s proven valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;rsquo;s also been a cage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve avoided situations where I&amp;rsquo;d be technically challenged. I&amp;rsquo;ve controlled the narrative by preemptively telling people—especially those I perceive as highly technical—that I&amp;rsquo;m &amp;ldquo;not a technical leader.&amp;rdquo; By saying it first, I manage their expectations and protect myself from judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that while there&amp;rsquo;s power in controlling how others see you, this approach has been unnecessarily reducing my value. It undermines how good I actually am at my job. And I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; good at my job. I&amp;rsquo;m very good at what I do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I shared this belief in our breakout session, the women I admire pushed back immediately. They told me I am technical. That they&amp;rsquo;ve always seen me as technical. That this story I tell myself doesn&amp;rsquo;t match the reality they see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we went around sharing our limiting beliefs, we were all genuinely shocked to discover we felt similarly diminished in different ways. Watching these talented women undersell their own skill sets was both disheartening and revealing—revealing of how we&amp;rsquo;ve internalized expectations and lost trust in ourselves over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-moment-everything-shifted"&gt;The Moment Everything Shifted
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the end of the exercise, we were asked to rewrite our limiting beliefs. My first attempt was predictably safe: &amp;ldquo;My lack of technical skills does not diminish my value in my role.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the women in my group stopped me cold. &amp;ldquo;You need to stop saying you&amp;rsquo;re not technical. Period. That&amp;rsquo;s not serving you and it never will.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I tried again. This time, I wrote something simple and terrifying: &lt;strong&gt;I am a technical leader.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There it is. That&amp;rsquo;s the rebrand. No more hedging, no more caveating, no more controlling the narrative by diminishing myself first. This blog will no longer be a space for ruminating on why I&amp;rsquo;m not enough. I&amp;rsquo;m going to own what I bring, challenge myself, and actually grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-perfection-problem"&gt;The Perfection Problem
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another theme that emerged in our session was the pressure to be perfect. Many of us talked about growing up with expectations to excel at everything—to be the A+ student, the top of the class, the one who never makes mistakes. While this isn&amp;rsquo;t exclusively a gendered experience, I do think we internalize these expectations in different ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That people-pleasing, teacher&amp;rsquo;s-pet programming from our youth? Sure, it&amp;rsquo;s part of why we&amp;rsquo;re successful. But at what cost? How much are we missing out on because we won&amp;rsquo;t put ourselves in situations where we might not be the best in the room?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has to be a way to keep our drive while establishing healthier boundaries. It requires checking in with ourselves when we&amp;rsquo;re obsessing over the perfect wording of an email or avoiding an opportunity because we&amp;rsquo;re not guaranteed to excel. We need to allow ourselves to be in uncomfortable spaces, to potentially fail, and to see what happens when we stop limiting ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-communication-style-trap"&gt;The Communication Style Trap
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The third insight that really landed for me was about how we compare ourselves to colleagues who use more direct, assertive, sometimes aggressive communication styles. Many of us bring more empathetic, open-minded approaches to getting things done, yet we watch the more abrupt style get rewarded more often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes sense when you consider that corporate America was designed by and for a specific demographic. The system cyclically supports certain communication styles and ways of working. (If you haven&amp;rsquo;t read the Harvard Business Review article &lt;a class="link" href="https://hbr.org/2021/02/stop-telling-women-they-have-imposter-syndrome" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;&amp;ldquo;Stop Telling Women They Have Imposter Syndrome,&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; I highly recommend it—it articulates this dynamic perfectly.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s what I realized: someone who can learn from direct, assertive approaches &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; embrace empathetic, holistic communication? That person has access to a genuine superpower. Knowing when to be direct and when to be empathetic, understanding when to focus on goals and when to engage with someone as a whole person—this isn&amp;rsquo;t a weakness. It&amp;rsquo;s flexibility and range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The corporate value system is shifting, slowly but surely. I hope my generation of leaders—those of us who tend to be more thoughtful about the whole person and the whole situation—can help accelerate that change. We don&amp;rsquo;t need to place arbitrary value on one approach over another just because of historical precedent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-comes-next"&gt;What Comes Next
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This conversation was a turning point. I&amp;rsquo;m walking away with a reworked belief system, one that actually supports who I am and where I want to go instead of holding me back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to be clear: while these conversations often center on gender, this isn&amp;rsquo;t about attacking anyone. It&amp;rsquo;s about acknowledging that certain dynamics exist in workplace cultures—dynamics that don&amp;rsquo;t always support different approaches or perspectives equally. For those navigating multiple intersections of identity, these dynamics can be even more complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to seeing how things evolve. I&amp;rsquo;m excited to keep having these conversations with colleagues. And honestly? I&amp;rsquo;m excited to see where this rebrand takes me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here we go. New narrative, same person—just finally willing to own all of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And hey, to the women who were in my breakout session—if you&amp;rsquo;re reading this, thank you. You&amp;rsquo;re both incredible, you absolutely have this, and I&amp;rsquo;m lucky to work alongside you. I can&amp;rsquo;t wait to see your own rebrands in action.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>When Your Nervous System Says "Run": The Courage to Give People Who Scare You a Chance</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/growth-through-uncomfortable-encounters/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/growth-through-uncomfortable-encounters/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/growth-through-uncomfortable-encounters/cover.png" alt="Featured image of post When Your Nervous System Says "Run": The Courage to Give People Who Scare You a Chance" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;My nervous system went into overdrive the moment I met her. Everything about this person screamed &amp;ldquo;threat&amp;rdquo; to my conflict-averse brain—the confident way she spoke about her accomplishments, the casual mention of impressive experiences, the ease with which she navigated conversations I found intimidating. Coming from what I perceived as a humble background, I felt instantly small and easily dismissed. &lt;em&gt;Who am I to this person with all these accolades?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every instinct told me to politely excuse myself and avoid future interactions. Instead, I made one of the most transformative decisions of my professional life: I chose to stay and engage with the discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="when-fear-masks-opportunity"&gt;When Fear Masks Opportunity
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;As leaders, we&amp;rsquo;re constantly pushing ourselves out of our comfort zones—whether it&amp;rsquo;s having difficult conversations, asking challenging questions, or simply letting people know when we&amp;rsquo;re upset rather than sugarcoating our feelings. Yet when that alarm bell triggers during first encounters, it feels easiest to retreat and minimize future contact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned from intentionally engaging with people who initially scared me: that nervous system response isn&amp;rsquo;t always signaling danger. Sometimes, it&amp;rsquo;s responding to something unfamiliar—and unfamiliar is often where our greatest growth lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I&amp;rsquo;ve consciously chosen discomfort over avoidance, several encounters stand out as particularly meaningful. Some of those people are now among my closest friends and most trusted advisors. The person I mentioned earlier? She&amp;rsquo;s someone I confide in regularly, someone who serves as both mirror and lighthouse when I need honest feedback. It turns out her apparent bragging was armor against her own self-consciousness—the same way my withdrawal was mine. We shared similar values but applied them differently, which is exactly why she could offer perspectives I couldn&amp;rsquo;t reach alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-learning-lives-in-both-outcomes"&gt;The Learning Lives in Both Outcomes
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are other meaningful encounters,however, that didn&amp;rsquo;t blossom into lasting friendships, but they taught me invaluable lessons about myself and others. In both cases, my initial discomfort was partially warranted—there were genuine misalignments in values or communication styles that made deep connection difficult. But engaging authentically allowed me to understand &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; I felt triggered, what those reactions revealed about my own growth edges, and how to trust my judgment more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beauty lies in this: whether the relationship flourishes or fades, you&amp;rsquo;ve gained crucial data about yourself. You&amp;rsquo;ve practiced assuming positive intent, stretched your emotional intelligence, and hopefully offered something meaningful to the other person in return. Most importantly, you&amp;rsquo;ve learned to distinguish between your nervous system responding to genuine incompatibility versus simply responding to difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="practical-steps-for-engaging-with-discomfort"&gt;Practical Steps for Engaging with Discomfort
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start with perspective-shifting.&lt;/strong&gt; Before your next networking event or team meeting, remind yourself that your initial discomfort might be pointing toward growth, not danger. When you meet someone who triggers that alarm, pause and ask: &amp;ldquo;What if I don&amp;rsquo;t know them well enough to judge? What might their perspective be?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assume positive intent deliberately.&lt;/strong&gt; This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean ignoring red flags—it means giving people the benefit of the doubt when your nervous system reacts to unfamiliarity rather than actual threat. Ask yourself: &amp;ldquo;What if their confidence comes from a place of sharing rather than showing off? What if their directness is clarity, not aggression?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engage with curiosity.&lt;/strong&gt; Instead of defensive questioning, try genuine inquiry. &amp;ldquo;Tell me more about that project&amp;rdquo; instead of internal skepticism. &amp;ldquo;How did you develop that approach?&amp;rdquo; rather than immediate judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust the learning process.&lt;/strong&gt; Whether the relationship deepens or remains surface-level, you&amp;rsquo;re building emotional agility and expanding your leadership capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-courage-to-stay-present"&gt;The Courage to Stay Present
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In our hyperconnected yet increasingly polarized world, the ability to sit with discomfort and engage authentically across differences isn&amp;rsquo;t just a nice-to-have—it&amp;rsquo;s essential leadership currency. The people who challenge us, who make us squirm a little in their presence, often hold the keys to our next level of growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of my most valuable professional relationships started with that stomach-dropping feeling of &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t belong here&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;This person is too much for me.&amp;rdquo; Learning to distinguish between productive discomfort and genuine warning signals has become one of my most valuable leadership skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your nervous system will always have opinions. But you get to choose whether to let those opinions make your decisions—or use them as data points in a much richer conversation about growth, connection, and possibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about you?&lt;/strong&gt; Have you ever been surprised by a relationship that started with discomfort? I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear your stories in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*The image for this post was generated by AI&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Five Managerial Archetypes That Shaped My Leadership Style (And What I Learned From Each)</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/five-managerial-archetypes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/five-managerial-archetypes/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/five-managerial-archetypes/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Five Managerial Archetypes That Shaped My Leadership Style (And What I Learned From Each)" /&gt;&lt;h2 id="five-managerial-archetypes-that-shaped-my-leadership-style-and-what-i-learned-from-each"&gt;Five Managerial Archetypes That Shaped My Leadership Style (And What I Learned From Each)
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: If you recognize yourself in any of these vignettes, know that these are distilled stories meant to illustrate broader patterns. I&amp;rsquo;ve learned tremendously from each leader I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with, and I&amp;rsquo;m genuinely grateful for everything they&amp;rsquo;ve taught me that has shaped who I am today.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-charismatic-delegator-aka-the-ferris-bueller"&gt;The Charismatic Delegator (aka &amp;ldquo;The Ferris Bueller&amp;rdquo;)
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;You know this manager. They glide through the office with an almost supernatural ability to avoid looking busy while somehow keeping everything running. They&amp;rsquo;re rarely in meetings, masterfully delegate most tasks to their reports, and yet&amp;hellip; people genuinely like them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leader had an uncanny knack for interpersonal relationships and could read the political undercurrents of any situation. They&amp;rsquo;d show up fashionably late to meetings (always), drop a perfectly timed joke or wildly insightful observation, then disappear again. People either adored them for their hands-off approach or liked them while quietly wondering what exactly they did all day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt; This manager was the first person to tell me something revolutionary as a new leader: &amp;ldquo;You have agency to do what you need to do with your team to make things happen.&amp;rdquo; That permission to trust my instincts was invaluable. They taught me that sometimes the best leadership is knowing when to get out of people&amp;rsquo;s way or when to pull rank and do what needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was missing:&lt;/strong&gt; While the autonomy was empowering, I craved more concrete mentoring. Their laissez-faire approach meant I had to figure out a lot of leadership challenges on my own when some direct guidance would have accelerated my growth significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-aloof-guru"&gt;The Aloof Guru
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Picture this: You spend hours preparing for your 1:1, armed with thoughtful questions, industry insights, team updates, and burning issues that need guidance. You&amp;rsquo;re ready for a rich 45-minute conversation. Instead, you get a distracted leader who seems to be mentally somewhere else entirely, wrapping up after 15-20 minutes with vague, inspirational platitudes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leader had a frustrating pattern of responding to concrete problems with abstract wisdom. When I needed specific coaching on handling a difficult team dynamic, I&amp;rsquo;d get something like &amp;ldquo;trust the process&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;lean into the discomfort.&amp;rdquo; Meanwhile, initiatives they&amp;rsquo;d championed were quietly falling apart, and the team was left to navigate the chaos without clear direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes inspiration is exactly what people need, but sometimes they need you to roll up your sleeves and get tactical. The best leaders know when to be the visionary guru and when to be the hands-on problem-solver. Being only one or the other leaves gaps that your team will feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-fierce-advocate-aka-the-anti-change-agent"&gt;The Fierce Advocate (aka &amp;ldquo;The Anti-Change Agent&amp;rdquo;)
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This leader taught me everything about servant leadership and empathetic management. When I reported to them, I felt genuinely heard and supported. They&amp;rsquo;d fight tooth and nail for their team members, running concerns up the flagpole and using every ounce of their influence to make our work lives better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when I became their colleague, I saw the other side of this coin. Their reflexive pushback against any change from senior leadership—even necessary business changes—started to feel counterproductive. While advocating for your team is crucial, sometimes changes need to happen for the organization to survive and thrive, even if they&amp;rsquo;re initially unpopular or challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt; There&amp;rsquo;s an art to strategic pushback. I now try to save my &amp;ldquo;squeaky wheel quota&amp;rdquo; for things I feel passionately about rather than reflexively opposing every change. The key is helping your team understand why changes are happening while still being their advocate within reasonable bounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-emotional-volcano"&gt;The Emotional Volcano
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This manager wore every feeling on their sleeve—the good, the bad, and everything in between. We always knew exactly how they felt about any situation, person, or decision. While transparency can be valuable, this leader let emotions build and build until they&amp;rsquo;d explode in disruptive ways that affected the entire team&amp;rsquo;s dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their emotional volatility meant we often knew more than we should have about office politics, interpersonal conflicts, and leadership decisions that were still in flux. What started as refreshing honesty became exhausting unpredictability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt; Emotional transparency has its place in leadership, but it needs boundaries. Yes, your team should sometimes see when you&amp;rsquo;re upset about something important—it shows you care and have their backs. But sharing every emotional reaction creates unnecessary stress and can undermine your credibility as a steady presence your team can rely on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-puppet-master"&gt;The Puppet Master
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This leader turned management into a psychological chess game. They&amp;rsquo;d weaponize silence in meetings, waiting until the discomfort forced you to say something you might not have otherwise shared. Trust was a foreign concept—they were never warm, never vulnerable, never genuine in their interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They played favorites openly, and for a while, I was on the good side of that equation. Conference attendance, paid training, regular 1:1 attention—I got it all. But when their focus shifted to someone else, I received the lowest performance review of my career during what I considered my hardest-working year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most insidiously, they&amp;rsquo;d bring up gossip in individual conversations, designed to make people suspicious of their colleagues. And despite being in a player-coach role, whenever they needed to contribute as a &amp;ldquo;player,&amp;rdquo; their work barely met minimum standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt; Trust is the foundation of effective leadership, and manipulation erodes it faster than almost anything else. Favorites might feel good in the moment, but they create toxic team dynamics. Consistency in how you treat people and genuine investment in everyone&amp;rsquo;s success builds the kind of culture where people actually want to do their best work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-leadership-cocktail"&gt;The Leadership Cocktail
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what&amp;rsquo;s fascinating about these experiences: each archetype had elements worth emulating and others worth avoiding. The Charismatic Delegator&amp;rsquo;s trust in people&amp;rsquo;s agency, the Aloof Guru&amp;rsquo;s occasional inspirational moments, the Fierce Advocate&amp;rsquo;s genuine care, the Emotional Volcano&amp;rsquo;s transparency (in smaller doses), and even the Puppet Master&amp;rsquo;s strategic thinking (applied ethically)—there&amp;rsquo;s something to learn from every approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leaders who&amp;rsquo;ve had the most positive impact on my growth have been able to flex between these styles as situations demanded. They knew when to delegate and when to dive deep, when to inspire and when to get tactical, when to advocate and when to embrace change, when to be transparent and when to maintain professional boundaries, when to be strategic and when to be genuine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What managerial archetypes have shaped your leadership journey? Which ones do you find yourself gravitating toward, and which ones do you actively try to avoid?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Want more thoughts on leadership and management? Follow along for more real talk about the messy, complicated, and occasionally brilliant world of leading people.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Leadership Paradox: Why Showing Your Unhappiness Makes You a Better Leader</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/leadership-paradox/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/leadership-paradox/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/leadership-paradox/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The Leadership Paradox: Why Showing Your Unhappiness Makes You a Better Leader" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;As leaders, we&amp;rsquo;re often taught that emotional control is paramount. We learn to stay calm under pressure, think before we speak, and approach every situation with level-headed rationality. But what if this approach—while valuable—is missing a crucial component of effective leadership?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-feedback-that-changed-everything"&gt;The Feedback That Changed Everything
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;During my participation in a leadership accelerator program at Relias, I received feedback that fundamentally challenged how I viewed effective leadership. The comprehensive assessment revealed something I hadn&amp;rsquo;t considered: my pride in remaining emotionally detached might actually be limiting my effectiveness as a leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conversation involved a leader I deeply respect—someone whose approach differs completely from mine yet achieves remarkable results. Through our discussion with a facilitator from our parent company, an uncomfortable truth emerged about my leadership style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-default-leadership-response"&gt;My Default Leadership Response
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;For years, I&amp;rsquo;ve operated under a specific framework when facing challenging situations or feeling upset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove myself from the immediate situation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process emotions privately until I feel calm and level-headed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Return to address the issue without emotional involvement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on constructive, forward-moving solutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach felt rational, professional, and respectful. It aligned with my personal values and seemed to avoid the pitfalls of reactive, emotion-driven communication that I&amp;rsquo;d witnessed create problems in other contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-surprising-truth-about-leadership-communication"&gt;The Surprising Truth About Leadership Communication
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The feedback I received was both simple and profound: &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s important as a leader that you sometimes let people know that you are unhappy with them.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This statement struck me like lightning because it ran completely counter to my self-image as a leader. I had spent considerable effort developing systems to avoid communicating emotionally, believing this made me more effective and professional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-emotional-detachment-can-backfire"&gt;Why Emotional Detachment Can Backfire
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I learned through this experience is that my well-intentioned approach was creating an unintended consequence. By removing all emotion from my communication, I was inadvertently:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Downplaying the severity of situations&lt;/strong&gt; that warranted concern&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Depriving team members of important contextual information&lt;/strong&gt; about the impact of their actions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Missing opportunities for immediate course correction&lt;/strong&gt; through emotional feedback&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reducing the motivational impact&lt;/strong&gt; of my leadership communication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-strategic-value-of-showing-unhappiness"&gt;The Strategic Value of Showing Unhappiness
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The revelation helped me understand that a leader&amp;rsquo;s unhappiness with a situation serves multiple strategic purposes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="immediate-signal-strength"&gt;Immediate Signal Strength
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;When team members see that their leader is genuinely upset about an outcome, it immediately communicates the gravity of the situation in ways that calm, rational feedback cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="creating-coachable-moments"&gt;Creating Coachable Moments
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;That moment when someone thinks, &amp;ldquo;Oh no, my boss is upset with me because of this&amp;rdquo; becomes a powerful catalyst for self-reflection and behavioral change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="authentic-relationship-building"&gt;Authentic Relationship Building
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Showing genuine emotion (when appropriate) demonstrates that you&amp;rsquo;re invested in outcomes and care deeply about the team&amp;rsquo;s success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="clear-expectation-setting"&gt;Clear Expectation Setting
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your emotional response helps team members calibrate their understanding of what matters most and what standards they&amp;rsquo;re expected to meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-two-phase-leadership-approach"&gt;The Two-Phase Leadership Approach
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The key insight wasn&amp;rsquo;t to abandon my thoughtful, rational approach entirely, but rather to implement a two-phase strategy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="phase-1-immediate-emotional-feedback"&gt;Phase 1: Immediate Emotional Feedback
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Allow team members to witness and understand your genuine reaction to situations when they occur. This provides immediate context and impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="phase-2-reflective-problem-solving"&gt;Phase 2: Reflective Problem-Solving
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Later, when emotions have settled, engage in the deeper, analytical conversation about what happened and how to improve moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="balancing-emotional-intelligence-with-authentic-leadership"&gt;Balancing Emotional Intelligence with Authentic Leadership
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This experience taught me that effective leadership isn&amp;rsquo;t about eliminating emotion—it&amp;rsquo;s about using emotion strategically. The goal isn&amp;rsquo;t to become reactive or lose professional composure, but rather to ensure that the full picture of your leadership perspective is communicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your frustration, disappointment, or concern about a situation is itself valuable information for your team. It helps them understand not just what went wrong, but how significantly it impacted the broader goals and relationships they care about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="implementing-constructive-emotional-leadership"&gt;Implementing Constructive Emotional Leadership
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re like me and tend toward emotional restraint in leadership situations, consider these strategies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow Initial Reactions:&lt;/strong&gt; Give yourself permission to show genuine concern or disappointment when it first occurs, rather than immediately suppressing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use Emotion as Data:&lt;/strong&gt; Treat your emotional responses as valuable information to share with your team about priorities and expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow Up Thoughtfully:&lt;/strong&gt; Maintain your commitment to reflective, solution-oriented conversations, but don&amp;rsquo;t let them replace the immediate emotional feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Model Emotional Intelligence:&lt;/strong&gt; Show your team that emotions can be acknowledged and expressed professionally without derailing productive communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-leadership-growth-mindset"&gt;The Leadership Growth Mindset
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most valuable aspect of this feedback was how it challenged my assumptions about what makes a &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; leader. Growth in leadership often requires us to examine our comfortable patterns and consider whether they&amp;rsquo;re serving our teams as effectively as we believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leader who gave me this feedback approaches leadership completely differently than I do, yet achieves incredible results. This experience reminded me that there&amp;rsquo;s no single template for effective leadership—but there are always opportunities to expand our toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="moving-forward-emotion-as-leadership-tool"&gt;Moving Forward: Emotion as Leadership Tool
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, I&amp;rsquo;m still the same person who values thoughtful, rational problem-solving. But I&amp;rsquo;ve added a new dimension to my leadership approach: the strategic use of authentic emotional communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When something goes wrong now, I don&amp;rsquo;t hide my disappointment. I let my team see that I&amp;rsquo;m genuinely upset about the outcome, because that unhappiness is part of the feedback they need to fully understand the situation and grow from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal isn&amp;rsquo;t to become more emotional as a leader—it&amp;rsquo;s to become more complete in how we communicate the full spectrum of our leadership perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What surprising feedback have you received that changed your approach to leadership? How do you balance emotional authenticity with professional communication in your role?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>When Your Former Manager Apologizes: Lessons from My Early Management Transition</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/apology/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/apology/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/apology/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post When Your Former Manager Apologizes: Lessons from My Early Management Transition" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the most powerful career moments happen years after the fact. Recently, I received an unexpected LinkedIn message that made me reflect on one of the most pivotal conversations of my early career—and the lessons it taught me about trusting your instincts when transitioning into management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-backstory-when-coding-wasnt-my-calling"&gt;The Backstory: When Coding Wasn&amp;rsquo;t My Calling
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back in my developer days, I had a realization that many engineers face but don&amp;rsquo;t always voice: coding wasn&amp;rsquo;t my passion. Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong—I liked it well enough, but I was honestly struggling to produce what I considered quality work. There&amp;rsquo;s a certain mental block that kicks in when you&amp;rsquo;re working outside your zone of genius, and for me, that happened once problems reached a certain complexity level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was working in a tech stack I hadn&amp;rsquo;t trained for in bootcamp. While I&amp;rsquo;d become competent in Angular, I had zero interest in learning C# to support our backend and truly fulfill my &amp;ldquo;fullstack&amp;rdquo; job title. My heart just wasn&amp;rsquo;t in the technical depth required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s what I &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; passionate about: I&amp;rsquo;d worked incredibly hard on a project converting our legacy, manual deployment process into Azure DevOps pipelines. I was making connections outside the direct software engineering groups, thinking deeply about DevOps culture, operational considerations, and overall process improvement. I wanted to focus on how we got the job done, not just what we built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming from my background as a Speech-Language Pathologist, I knew I was good with people. I missed having that human element as a focus of my day—working with varied professionals toward common goals, identifying objectives, and strategizing paths to reach them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I was ready for management. I craved it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-conversation-that-stuck"&gt;The Conversation That Stuck
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d just received a promotion to mid-level and was getting direct coaching around transitioning into leadership. In my mind, I didn&amp;rsquo;t need to become a senior developer before becoming a manager (a topic that probably deserves its own blog series).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a 1:1, my manager and I were building an upskilling plan. He was focused on getting me to a senior role, which meant extensive C# training—work I genuinely didn&amp;rsquo;t want to do. When I made my case for a different path, in a moment of frustration, he told me I was being &lt;strong&gt;impatient&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That word hit me hard for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I felt like I was finally doing what everyone said I should do&lt;/strong&gt;: advocating for myself. As someone who&amp;rsquo;s naturally conflict-avoidant, this was growth for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never seen this manager frustrated with me before&lt;/strong&gt;. It felt like I&amp;rsquo;d hit a nerve, and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t understand why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating shared understanding of goals and paths forward was supposed to be my strength&lt;/strong&gt;. But now that I was on the receiving end of career guidance, was I missing something?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not long after, this manager left for another opportunity. Within a few years, I successfully transitioned into management without becoming a senior developer first. But that moment—that word &amp;ldquo;impatient&amp;rdquo;—lingered like a gray cloud over my career journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-apology-that-changed-everything"&gt;The Apology That Changed Everything
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently, that same manager reached out on LinkedIn with an unexpected message: an apology. He acknowledged that our interaction had made an impact on him too. He said he was proud of me and felt he&amp;rsquo;d made a mistake not recognizing I was ready for management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re reading this, Manager-of-Before, thank you. I can&amp;rsquo;t express how much it means to know you&amp;rsquo;re proud of me and see in me what I was striving for back then.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This apology came at a time when I&amp;rsquo;d been questioning whether I truly made the right choice moving into management as early as I did. The answer, honestly, depends on the day. But knowing that he—on the other side of our previous interaction—sees me thriving in this role means everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="three-lessons-im-taking-forward"&gt;Three Lessons I&amp;rsquo;m Taking Forward
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on this experience, here are the insights swirling in my head:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="1-trust-your-gut-when-you-know-youre-ready"&gt;1. Trust Your Gut When You Know You&amp;rsquo;re Ready
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you feel ready for something in your bones, don&amp;rsquo;t automatically let others convince you otherwise. There&amp;rsquo;s wisdom in your intuition about your own readiness, especially when it comes to leveraging existing strengths in new ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="2-your-leaders-know-youlisten-thoughtfully-to-pushback"&gt;2. Your Leaders Know You—Listen Thoughtfully to Pushback
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;When managers push back on your career aspirations, try not to take it personally immediately. Consider their perspective thoughtfully. They may see development areas you haven&amp;rsquo;t acknowledged, or they may be operating from their own constraints and experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="3-intense-responses-often-have-context-you-cant-see"&gt;3. Intense Responses Often Have Context You Can&amp;rsquo;t See
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;If your manager has a strong reaction to something, it&amp;rsquo;s not necessarily about what&amp;rsquo;s happening in that moment. Other pressures, constraints, or experiences may be narrowing their perspective and making it harder for them to show up as their best selves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-bigger-picture-on-early-management-transitions"&gt;The Bigger Picture on Early Management Transitions
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This experience reinforced something I&amp;rsquo;m passionate about: the path into management doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be linear. While technical expertise matters, management is fundamentally about people, process, and vision. Sometimes the skills that make you ready for leadership—emotional intelligence, systems thinking, collaborative problem-solving—don&amp;rsquo;t perfectly align with traditional technical progression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key is honest self-assessment: Are you avoiding management because you&amp;rsquo;re not ready, or are you avoiding technical depth because management is where your strengths and interests truly lie?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="your-turn-trusting-your-career-instincts"&gt;Your Turn: Trusting Your Career Instincts
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have you ever had a career conversation that stuck with you? A moment when you advocated for yourself and faced unexpected resistance? I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear about your experiences with non-traditional career transitions and how you navigated the tension between others&amp;rsquo; expectations and your own intuition.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Efficiency Trap</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/efficiency-trap/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/efficiency-trap/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/efficiency-trap/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The Efficiency Trap" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Remember in &lt;em&gt;The Parent Trap&lt;/em&gt; when Lindsay Lohan&amp;rsquo;s characters spend the entire movie scheming to get their parents back together through increasingly elaborate plans? They could have just&amp;hellip; talked to them. But no, they needed to control every detail, orchestrate every moment, and make sure everything happened exactly their way. Spoiler alert: it got messy before it got better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s me in most work situations. I&amp;rsquo;m both Lindsay Lohans—the one with the perfectly planned strategy AND the one panicking when things don&amp;rsquo;t go according to plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-anxiety-spiral"&gt;The Anxiety Spiral
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I start to feel the anxiety of not making a decision and moving into action, it begins with a familiar tightness in my chest that expands into low-level panic. I get clammy, my mind goes blank on everything except finding a path to resolution, and I become increasingly difficult to work with as my frustration builds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has led to more than one mistake and left more than one situation with others feeling just as frustrated as I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a developer, I was used to sitting in refinement meetings where conversations would churn around technical implementation. I always felt like there was more to learn, and I never wanted us to make an incorrect choice. But now, in leadership, when I&amp;rsquo;m in meetings where my developers seem to talk in circles without making tangible progress on refinements, I start to lose it. We get caught in a swirl of what-ifs and future-proofing, completely throwing the agile process out the window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="when-just-let-me-handle-it-backfires"&gt;When &amp;ldquo;Just Let Me Handle It&amp;rdquo; Backfires
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently, I made a classic efficiency-over-effectiveness mistake. I agreed to let two of my senior developers work on a new feature set that involved separating two different user experiences with largely the same functionality and a new identity provider. In my mind, I was being efficient—trusting my team, moving quickly, not micromanaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reality? There was no insight into progress, missed requirements piled up, and what should have been a straightforward feature became a months-long saga. My desire to move fast and avoid process actually created more work, more confusion, and more stress for everyone involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had fallen into what I now call the efficiency trap—prioritizing speed and my preferred way of doing things over actually getting the right outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-coach-question-that-broke-my-brain"&gt;The Coach Question That Broke My Brain
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When my Torch coach asked me which I valued more—efficiency or effectiveness—my brain just went &amp;ldquo;buzzzzzzzz.&amp;rdquo; It didn&amp;rsquo;t compute. What do you mean there&amp;rsquo;s a difference? Getting things done correctly and quickly is what matters, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the more I sat with it, the more I realized I was creating unnecessary anxiety for myself and my team. There&amp;rsquo;s real power in letting go of needing to do something a certain way within a certain timeframe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This question hit particularly hard because my team is currently navigating two critical challenges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We need to improve our predictability quarter over quarter to help with deliverable timelines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We need to maximize the work we can produce with our current team size&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized I needed to find a reasonable middle ground. Sometimes moving quickly and being efficient is the right approach. Other times, being effective—getting the right outcome—is all that matters at the end of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="putting-it-into-practice"&gt;Putting It Into Practice
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the &amp;ldquo;just cut me a ticket and let me hack at it&amp;rdquo; disaster, I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to be more mindful about when I apply the brakes to enforce process and when I need to make a quick call and move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our upcoming quarterly planning, we&amp;rsquo;re taking time to go through epics with a fine-tooth comb, making sure requirements are defined and we&amp;rsquo;re considering all aspects of technical implementation. Maybe the pendulum has swung too far in the other direction, but I think it&amp;rsquo;s good practice for the team. Once the actual development work begins, there should be less churn because we&amp;rsquo;ll know everything from day one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Stay tuned for a future update on how this approach affects our effectiveness and predictability.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-root-of-the-problem"&gt;The Root of the Problem
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This need for control and hyper-efficiency comes from being a Type A, people-pleasing, teacher&amp;rsquo;s pet. I&amp;rsquo;ve been this way my whole life, and I think it stems from wanting to be good at what I do—starting with being successful in school and following through to today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s this underlying script that I&amp;rsquo;ve been successful because I get things done my way, quickly. Not because I was just getting the right things done, period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-this-is-changing-how-i-lead"&gt;How This Is Changing How I Lead
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This framework is still new for me in my leadership journey, but I&amp;rsquo;ve already noticed some shifts in how I approach my role:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I delegate more thoughtfully.&lt;/strong&gt; Instead of either micromanaging or completely hands-off approaches, I&amp;rsquo;m delegating to people I trust to be effective, with clear guidelines for check-ins, observable progress markers, and well-defined scope and requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I ask better questions.&lt;/strong&gt; Rather than jumping straight to &amp;ldquo;how do we do this faster,&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;m starting with &amp;ldquo;what outcome are we actually trying to achieve here?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m more comfortable with different approaches.&lt;/strong&gt; If someone on my team has a different way of reaching the same effective outcome, I&amp;rsquo;m learning to let them run with it instead of redirecting them to my preferred method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth is, some of my best work has happened when I focused on being effective first, then found efficient ways to execute. The efficiency trap had me believing that speed and control were always the answer, but sometimes the fastest path to the right outcome is the one that feels slower in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just like those scheming twins in &lt;em&gt;The Parent Trap&lt;/em&gt;, sometimes the most elaborate plan isn&amp;rsquo;t the one that gets you where you want to go—it&amp;rsquo;s the one that&amp;rsquo;s willing to adapt when life throws you a curveball.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What about you? Have you ever found yourself caught in the efficiency trap? I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear how you&amp;rsquo;ve learned to balance getting things done with getting the right things done.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>My Self-Rebrand: Owning the Room in My Own Way</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/self-rebrand/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/self-rebrand/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/self-rebrand/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post My Self-Rebrand: Owning the Room in My Own Way" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have you ever had to go through a personal rebrand?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our entire lives, we tell ourselves stories about ourselves. Others tell us stories about ourselves. And around and around it goes. Before long, all the neural pathways in our brains are deeply rooted in specific ideas, and it can be incredibly difficult to get them to move, bend, and change to fit new perspectives about our self-images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My entire life, I&amp;rsquo;ve been told I&amp;rsquo;m quiet and shy. Soft-spoken. And I am — most days it can be difficult to get my voice to carry across a dinner table, much less command a presentation space. So by extension, I never thought of myself as much of a public speaker. I assumed I was too shy, too soft-spoken, not bold or confident enough to deliver a presentation that left people walking away thinking, &lt;em&gt;“Wow, that was a great session.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, though, my role has required me to step up — presenting to large internal audiences, engaging leadership in smaller strategy sessions, and showing up with clarity and purpose. And while I’ve always felt confident in my knowledge of my team and product, I hadn’t internalized the idea that &lt;em&gt;I’m good at public speaking&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the larger forums I regularly speak at is a quarterly stakeholder review, where I summarize key accomplishments and upcoming goals. The audience spans hundreds of people, so I’ve developed a rhythm: keep it casual, keep it high-level, throw in a little humor. I know it’s not a space for deep technical dives — it’s about connection and clarity. This is where I’ve found my stride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feedback from my most recent presentation floored me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The new VP of Product said it reflected deep product knowledge and praised the strength of my partnership with my Director of Product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A fellow engineering manager joked that I must secretly be in Sales or Marketing — and meant it as a compliment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An engineer who’s usually disengaged during company-wide meetings said mine actually woke him up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And most meaningfully, an engineer I’ve admired since I was an Associate — someone I’ve always been intimidated by — reached out privately with kind words I’ll treasure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the thing: this isn’t the first time I’ve received positive feedback on my presentations. But for some reason, this time it clicked. &lt;em&gt;Maybe I am good at this.&lt;/em&gt; Maybe public speaking isn’t something I have to muscle through — maybe it’s something I’ve grown into.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can still be soft-spoken, quiet, and reserved. But that doesn’t mean I can’t also own a room when the time calls for it. It’s not either/or.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This experience taught me something valuable: we don’t have to stay locked into the stories we were told — or the ones we told ourselves. We can allow room for expansion. Growth. New neural pathways. Rebranding doesn’t mean we lose ourselves — it means we make room for who we’re becoming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever felt boxed in by an identity that no longer fits, ask yourself: &lt;em&gt;What if I’m more than that?&lt;/em&gt; Give yourself permission to evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="ready-to-rebrand-yourself"&gt;Ready to rebrand yourself?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;If this post resonated with you, I’d love to hear your story. Have you ever surprised yourself with growth in an area you thought was closed off? Drop a comment, send a message, or share this with someone who might need the nudge today.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A 12-Year Lookback: From Speech-Language Pathologist to Engineering Leader</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/12-year-lookback/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/12-year-lookback/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/12-year-lookback/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post A 12-Year Lookback: From Speech-Language Pathologist to Engineering Leader" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Twelve years ago, I graduated with my Master’s Degree from East Carolina University. And it wasn’t in Computer Science or anything remotely related to technology. I’m the proud owner of a Master of Science in Communication Sciences and Disorders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who don’t know, I spent the first six years of my grown-up-career life as a Speech-Language Pathologist, working with adult patients in acute care settings. I loved the patient care, even though it could be emotionally difficult. I had the privilege of working with some of the most resilient people I’ve ever met—witnessing their strength as they overcame incredible obstacles. I had the opportunity to apply clinical problem-solving to create diagnoses, prognoses, and treatment plans, always keeping my patients’ individual goals and quality of life at the center of everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I didn’t love working &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; the healthcare system. After several years, I realized I couldn’t make a sustainable long-term career out of it. Still, my passion for healthcare—and a desire to make it better—led me to a coding bootcamp. Six and a half years later, I’m still lucky enough to be at Relias, where I help connect healthcare professionals with top-tier educational resources and tools that make a real difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things that almost held me back from making the leap to tech was my Master’s degree. I had invested years of time and a lot of money into earning it. I worried it would be a sunk cost—a credential that was now irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or… was it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, the intricacies of laryngeal nerves and tracheostomy care don’t show up in my day-to-day work anymore. But a graduate degree is about much more than memorizing clinical protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here’s what else that degree gave me:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research literacy:&lt;/strong&gt; I learned how to evaluate sources, synthesize information, and apply evidence-based methods—skills I now use in technical investigations and strategic planning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Critical thinking under pressure:&lt;/strong&gt; Whether it was managing a stroke patient’s cognitive recovery or debugging a legacy integration system, the ability to assess, analyze, and act is foundational.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Communication with empathy:&lt;/strong&gt; Working with patients taught me to deliver difficult news with compassion, adjust my style based on the audience, and truly listen—something I rely on heavily in management today.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goal-oriented planning:&lt;/strong&gt; Building measurable therapy goals for patients is surprisingly similar to setting OKRs or team goals in engineering. You need to start with the end in mind and work backward to create a practical path forward.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience working in healthcare also directly informs what I love most about being a manager. I thrive on building relationships rooted in trust and empathy. I’m deeply motivated by aligning people’s individual aspirations with broader team and business goals. I understand the emotional component of work and how much it matters to feel heard, supported, and challenged at the right times. Just like in clinical settings, I strive to create environments where people feel safe to grow—but I also know when to step in, ask the hard questions, and help someone level up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twelve years ago, Ashley had no clue she’d end up here. And that’s kind of incredible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here’s a reminder—don’t box yourself in because of the sunk cost fallacy. Your past experience isn’t wasted. It’s raw material. You can shape it into something new. Even if the path forward isn’t crystal clear yet, every step builds on the last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You just have to start walking.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Power of Immediate Action: How I Tamed My Endless To-Do List</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/immediate-action/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/immediate-action/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/immediate-action/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The Power of Immediate Action: How I Tamed My Endless To-Do List" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have a secret. Don’t worry, it’s a good one—and I’m happy to share it with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first became an Engineering Manager, I felt like I was drowning. My “To Do” column in Trello, my notebook, and my brain kept expanding like a balloon, no matter how many tasks I knocked out. And those are the tasks that I didn&amp;rsquo;t forget to keep record of&amp;hellip;there were many that just fell through the cracks. I was attending back-to-back meetings, responding to Slack messages, trying to think strategically, and still expected to deliver tangible results. Everything felt equally urgent, and the pressure to perform without dropping the ball was intense. I considered working late every night just to keep up, but let’s be real—that’s a shortcut to burnout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what changed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One small shift made a big difference: &lt;strong&gt;Immediate action&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not a magic bullet for every task, but it’s been incredibly effective for the small, high-context action items that are easy to forget. You know the ones—send a follow-up message, file a ticket for access, start a shared doc, ask someone for a clarification. Things that don’t require deep focus but can easily slip through the cracks if left for later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, when I’m in a meeting and someone mentions needing IT access, I file the ticket right then. If we need input from someone who isn’t present, I send them a quick Slack or email immediately. If we need a document to capture notes or decisions, I open it and share it before the meeting ends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach has two major benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Momentum&lt;/strong&gt;: Even if the task isn’t fully complete, it’s already moving. There’s energy and attention on it. In many cases, that’s enough to keep it progressing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust&lt;/strong&gt;: My team and cross-functional partners now know that when they ask for something, it won’t vanish into the void. I’ve built a reputation for being responsive, and that builds confidence and credibility over time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me be clear—this doesn’t mean I multitask my way through every meeting. I prioritize quick, low-effort actions that I can complete in 30-90 seconds. For deeper asks, I jot them down and return to them later with full focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of caveats, though. Acting immediately can sometimes mean I’m not 100% focused on the current conversation. I’ve missed a few small details here and there—but in my experience, the trade-off is worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, this strategy works for me because I don’t struggle with attention redirection. I understand this isn’t the case for everyone. If you have attention-related challenges, this method might feel overwhelming or counterproductive. That’s okay—there are other ways to harness the same principle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some alternatives to try:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leave 5–10 minutes at the end of each meeting&lt;/strong&gt; to knock out those quick tasks before jumping to the next one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a running “Immediate Action” list&lt;/strong&gt; during meetings and batch-process them during your next break.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use keyboard shortcuts, templates, and automation tools&lt;/strong&gt; to reduce friction for repeatable tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heart of the idea is this: the faster you give a task momentum, the more likely it is to get done—and the more others will see you as reliable, effective, and “on it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="what-works-for-you"&gt;What Works for You?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;If immediate action isn’t your style, what &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;? How do you stay on top of your fast-moving task list without burning out? I’d love to hear your strategies and hacks. Let’s share notes—after all, we’re all just figuring it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to leave a comment or reach out directly. I’m always looking to expand my toolkit—and yours too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let’s connect.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
If this resonated with you, consider subscribing to the blog or sharing it with someone who might benefit. We&amp;rsquo;re all learning how to lead and live better, one tiny change at a time.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Learning GA4 and Rediscovering the Joy of Growth</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/ga4-new-learning/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/ga4-new-learning/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/ga4-new-learning/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Learning GA4 and Rediscovering the Joy of Growth" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week, I earned my first new certification in years: &lt;a class="link" href="https://skillshop.exceedlms.com/student/catalog/list?category_ids=53-google-analytics" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Google Analytics&lt;/a&gt;, offered through Google Skillshop. And let me tell you—it felt &lt;strong&gt;SO GOOD&lt;/strong&gt;. From watching the videos and taking notes, to studying for the final exam, to finally passing and posting that shiny little badge on LinkedIn, I felt a sense of pride that I hadn’t experienced in a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally got to be the one to say: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m happy to share that I&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But beyond the badge, I’m proud of something deeper: the small, intentional choices I made that allowed me to chip away at the coursework despite a jam-packed schedule. Choosing to log in instead of doomscroll. Prioritizing my own growth alongside my responsibilities as a manager. Investing in myself again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not that I haven’t been learning—stepping into management, navigating a new tech stack, and entering the world of e-commerce was like jumping off a cliff into deep water. But this was different. This was structured, focused learning that I chose. And it reminded me how much I &lt;em&gt;missed&lt;/em&gt; that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding Google Analytics 4 was a key step for me as a leader. I’d never worked with SEO before—didn’t even realize how closely it ties into software development and data collection. I used to sit silently in meetings while our product managers and engineers discussed upcoming tagging work or issues with a poorly performing page. I’d listen, absorb, and nod&amp;hellip; but rarely contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now? After just one certification, I’ve already seen the impact. We just wrapped up our Q2 Big Room Planning, and for the first time, I was able to ask intelligent questions about data collection strategies for a new set of pages we’re rolling out. I even caught a user flow issue that hadn’t been considered yet—&lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; suggested a tagging approach to help track it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It felt empowering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combination of new knowledge and immediate application was an absolute rush. I remembered how curiosity, when nurtured, turns into confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now I’m hooked. I’m ready to keep going. But what next?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should I dive into &lt;strong&gt;Google Cloud Platform&lt;/strong&gt; (GCP) training to get more comfortable with the infrastructure side of things? Are there deeper SEO-related topics—like structured data, schema markup, or Lighthouse audits—that I should explore? What would help me show up even stronger for my team and our cross-functional partners?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve recently learned something new that shifted how you work, I’d love to hear about it. Let’s trade notes. Or if you’ve taken GCP or SEO courses you really liked, send them my way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s to the next learning curve. I’m ready.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;✨ Got suggestions for what I should learn next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Drop them in the comments, message me on LinkedIn, or send a carrier pigeon. I’m serious—I want to hear what’s helped you grow. Let’s build a little learning community together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you’ve been putting off that course, certification, or passion project? This is your nudge. Start today. A little at a time adds up, I promise.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mindful Curiosity</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/mindful-curiosity/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/mindful-curiosity/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/mindful-curiosity/cover.jpeg" alt="Featured image of post Mindful Curiosity" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my most recent coaching session, I sought guidance on an upcoming meeting with my management colleagues, directors, and SVP. I was nervous because I had received information about a change I didn’t agree with—one that I believed would significantly impact my team. &lt;em&gt;(It turned out my concerns were based on a misunderstanding, and my anxiety was unnecessary.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I explained my concerns, the questions I had, and my apprehension about how &amp;ldquo;pushing back&amp;rdquo; might be perceived, my coach interrupted with a thought-provoking question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do you think you&amp;rsquo;re pushing back? What I hear is your curiosity about the change and a desire to understand where it’s coming from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That question completely reframed my perspective. Why did I instinctively view my desire to understand leadership decisions as resistance? Shouldn’t gathering context and reasoning be part of my role as an effective change agent for my team? Isn’t deeper understanding essential for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensuring I have the right information before expressing concerns?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Framing concerns in a productive and constructive way?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This internalized fear of questioning leadership likely stems from deep-seated patterns in my psychology—an exploration for another time. But recognizing this mindset allows me to be more mindful in leadership interactions. Moving forward, when I feel anxiety creeping in, I’ll pause and ask myself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am I feeling anxious because I’m mislabeling my curiosity as pushback?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="strengthening-my-curiosity-muscle"&gt;Strengthening My Curiosity Muscle
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since this realization, I’ve also noticed other ways my curiosity (or lack thereof) manifests. Sometimes, I accept information or suggestions at face value without deeper exploration. If I want to continue growing as a technical leader, I need to challenge myself to dig deeper and ensure I have a well-rounded understanding before making decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-commitment-to-mindful-curiosity"&gt;My Commitment to Mindful Curiosity
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;To foster this growth, I’m setting the following personal challenges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reframing curiosity&lt;/strong&gt; – Asking leadership questions to understand a decision isn’t an act of defiance; it’s a tool for learning, effective communication, and advocacy for my team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seeking deeper understanding&lt;/strong&gt; – Instead of passively accepting information, I’ll actively engage, research, and explore different perspectives to develop a more informed viewpoint.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curiosity isn’t resistance—it’s a leadership strength. If I can embrace this mindset, I’ll not only become a stronger advocate for my team but also continue evolving as a leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about you?&lt;/strong&gt; Have you ever mistaken curiosity for pushback? How do you challenge yourself to ask better questions and seek deeper understanding? Let’s discuss in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Can Leadership Ever Truly Log Off?</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/can-leadership-truly-logoff/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/can-leadership-truly-logoff/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/can-leadership-truly-logoff/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Can Leadership Ever Truly Log Off?" /&gt;&lt;h2 id="can-leadership-ever-truly-log-off"&gt;Can Leadership Ever Truly Log Off?
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Balancing Work Responsibilities with the Need for True Time Off&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week was a tough one. In the early hours of Monday morning, my daughter woke up with a &lt;strong&gt;103-degree fever&lt;/strong&gt;, and I knew the flu had finally hit our household. Six hours later, I started feeling off myself, and thus began a week of so-called “rest” and recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I officially took Monday and Tuesday off to care for my daughter and attempt to recover. I’m incredibly fortunate that my husband’s job is flexible—he was able to be home for support. Later in the week, when we felt less contagious, my mom even came up to help. Despite all that support, I probably could have used the full five days to rest. But work had other plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-reality-of-leadership-work-never-pauses"&gt;The Reality of Leadership: Work Never Pauses
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even though I was out sick, pressing issues kept piling up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;site was experiencing issues.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;Principal Engineer was also out&lt;/strong&gt; sick all week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unexpected compensation and promotion discussions&lt;/strong&gt; were happening at the manager level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I needed to &lt;strong&gt;meet with HR&lt;/strong&gt; to plan a hiring strategy for a new team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annual reviews were due.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The usual &lt;strong&gt;weekly administrative to-dos&lt;/strong&gt; still needed to be completed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had this been planned PTO, I would have worked ahead to finish tasks, delegated responsibilities, and set expectations for my time away. But when unexpected time off happens, there’s no time to prepare—you just do your best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-frustration-of-being-pulled-back-in"&gt;The Frustration of Being Pulled Back In
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I found myself feeling &lt;strong&gt;frustrated&lt;/strong&gt;. I needed to step away and completely log off to care for my daughter and recover, but I didn’t feel like I truly could. There was &lt;strong&gt;too much happening&lt;/strong&gt;, too many unknowns, and I felt a responsibility to show up for my team—especially in the &lt;strong&gt;compensation and promotion discussions&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(That said, my &lt;strong&gt;peer in my department had my back&lt;/strong&gt; in my absence—thank you so much!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it made me question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can I expect my team to feel confident that they can fully log off when I don’t set the same example?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it even possible for leadership to fully step away?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="if-leaders-cant-log-off-can-anyone"&gt;If Leaders Can’t Log Off, Can Anyone?
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;My boss, an &lt;strong&gt;SVP&lt;/strong&gt;, has been on extended PTO. Before he left, I promised him I wouldn’t bother him while he was away visiting family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet… I &lt;strong&gt;reached out at least five times&lt;/strong&gt; (probably more). Sometimes I messaged him directly. Other times, I tagged him in notes or documents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry, Boss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="no-easy-answersjust-questions"&gt;No Easy Answers—Just Questions
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don’t have a perfect solution here. I’m simply &lt;strong&gt;asking the question&lt;/strong&gt; and wondering what others experience or expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As leaders, &lt;strong&gt;can we ever truly go offline&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While planning ahead helps, &lt;strong&gt;what about unexpected time away&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we ensure our teams know that they &lt;strong&gt;can and should&lt;/strong&gt; fully disengage during PTO—if we don’t set that example ourselves?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d love to hear from others: &lt;strong&gt;Have you successfully &amp;ldquo;fully logged off&amp;rdquo; as a leader? If so, how?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Your Cheese Just Missing? Learning to Embrace Change in Process Overhaul</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/missing-cheese/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/missing-cheese/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/missing-cheese/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Is Your Cheese Just Missing? Learning to Embrace Change in Process Overhaul" /&gt;&lt;h2 id="update-2325"&gt;Update 2/3/25
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since publishing this article, it has been brought to my attention that the &amp;ldquo;missing cheese&amp;rdquo; metaphor my colleague used, and I assumed an off-the-cuff-original, is actually likely referencing &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/0091876044?ref=cm_sw_r_ffobk_cso_cp_apin_dp_X47H5QMN1BPD16XBKCC9&amp;amp;ref_=cm_sw_r_ffobk_cso_cp_apin_dp_X47H5QMN1BPD16XBKCC9&amp;amp;social_share=cm_sw_r_ffobk_cso_cp_apin_dp_X47H5QMN1BPD16XBKCC9&amp;amp;starsLeft=1&amp;amp;skipTwisterOG=1&amp;amp;bestFormat=true&amp;amp;titleSource=avft-a&amp;amp;newOGT=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;&lt;em&gt;Who Moved My Cheese&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Dr. Spencer Johnston. I shall be adding this to my TBR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I received an incredible compliment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m really looking for your steady presence in this to really drive &amp;lsquo;Is this actually broken? Or is your cheese just missing?&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This simple remark made my day and sparked some deep reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, we overhauled our Jira project management workflows, starting fresh with a simpler, more streamlined strategy. The goal? Cut down on complexity to make our sprints more effective and reduce administrative overhead. We removed redundant workflow statuses—like tracking deployment and verification—and simplified the movement of tasks on the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite detailed pre-communication, training, and preparation, the change wasn’t universally welcomed. Which is fine. Pleasing everyone is impossible and change is tough. Within a week, the change management Teams channel lit up with frustrations, particularly around the removal of the &amp;ldquo;Ready for Testing&amp;rdquo; status—a step where tickets lingered until a test engineer was available to pick them up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some, the absence of this status felt like a loss of control. To them, their &amp;ldquo;cheese was missing,&amp;rdquo; but it felt like something was actually broken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When discussions in the channel veered toward resistance rather than solutions, I sent a message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m hearing &amp;rsquo;this thing doesn&amp;rsquo;t work like it did before&amp;rsquo;—and that&amp;rsquo;s kind of the point. The first couple of sprints may have growing pains, but we owe it to the people who spent time designing this to see if it works as intended. We want to hear feedback, but let’s give it a little time before making big changes.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, I felt anxious after hitting send. Pushing back publicly wasn’t in my comfort zone. But the response—a trio of heart emojis from process designers and positive feedback from project leads in a private DM—was reaffirming. They appreciated that I stood firm, giving the new workflow the time and space to succeed before yielding to reactionary changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I later offered office hours to help teams adapt to the new process. While there weren’t many takers, it signaled to me that teams were finding ways to work through the adjustment. Now, as we enter Sprint 2, I’m eager to evaluate pain points after completing Sprint 3 and ensure the process is genuinely serving its purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What stood out most to me was how this moment taught me something about myself. By holding boundaries and embracing discomfort, I discovered a steadying presence I hadn’t fully recognized until I received that comment in passing today. It’s a trait I’ll nurture, as it not only supports me but also adds value to my teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day change can feel unsettling—but sometimes missing cheese just means it’s time to find a new snack. 😉&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have you ever experienced “missing cheese” in your workflows or team processes? Share your thoughts in the comments! How do you balance patience with addressing feedback during times of change?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Bringing Developers into the Bigger Picture</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/bigger-context/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/bigger-context/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/bigger-context/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Bringing Developers into the Bigger Picture" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to company All Hands meetings—especially those focused on larger business goals or strategies—developers often react with indifference. Comments like, “Just give me tickets and let me code,” or “It’s just exec speak; I’m not interested,” are all too common.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a new developer, I remember feeling the same way. The business side of things felt distant and disconnected from my day-to-day tasks. It was hard to see how these grand initiatives translated to my keyboard or my assigned Jira tasks. But looking back, I wonder—what do we lose when we dismiss that broader context? And are business leaders missing an opportunity to engage their entire workforce by failing to connect these ideas to everyone?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, my company held its 2025 Kickoff event. For the second year, the event was open to the entire organization, not just senior leadership, client-facing teams, or Product. Last year, I missed it because I was seven months pregnant and reluctant to be in a crowded space. This year, I finally got to sit in the audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll admit—I really liked what I heard. The speakers shared important context, background, and insights. Having previously worked in healthcare, staying connected to the impact our products have on providers and patients is deeply meaningful to me. The executive and Product teams’ discussions helped me stay grounded in our mission to make a positive impact in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also gained a clearer understanding of how my team’s work aligns with the company’s larger vision. Seeing that connection reinvigorated my sense of purpose. As an engineering manager, I hope my team took away similar insights, and I plan to follow up in one-on-one meetings to reinforce our mission, vision, and goals. We’ll also revisit these ideas at our next department All Hands meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.svpg.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;The Silicon Valley Product Group&lt;/a&gt; introduced me to the concept of &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.svpg.com/missionaries-vs-mercenaries/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;“Missionaries, not Mercenaries”&lt;/a&gt;, and it comes to mind thinking about the importance of that broader business context. The essence of this idea is captured perfectly in the article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Teams of missionaries are engaged, motivated, have a deep understanding of the business context, and tangible empathy for the customer. Teams of mercenaries feel no real sense of empowerment or accountability, no passion for the problem to be solved, and little real connection with the actual users and customers.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When senior leadership clearly defines the organization’s mission, and employees are open to listening, the result is a highly engaged, motivated team ready to deliver exceptional value to users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m fortunate to lead a team that genuinely understands our mission and user base. Sure, there are sprints when we just need to power through the backlog. That’s part of the job. But the moments that leave me energized are when my team asks questions like, “What about our users who don’t have internet access at work?” or, “How can we make this process simpler for a particular group of users?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developers are natural problem solvers. Leaders, let’s not underestimate the value of involving them in the bigger conversations. When they understand the broader business context, their creativity can lead to extraordinary ideas. And developers, let’s take the time to listen to our leaders—it might just open doors to new ways of thinking and problem-solving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s your experience with connecting your work to the broader company mission? Whether you’re a leader or an individual contributor, share your thoughts or strategies in the comments—I’d love to hear them!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>