<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Team Management on Figuring it Out</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/tags/team-management/</link><description>Recent content in Team Management on Figuring it Out</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ashleyedds.dev/tags/team-management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Five Managerial Archetypes That Shaped My Leadership Style (And What I Learned From Each)</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/five-managerial-archetypes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/five-managerial-archetypes/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/five-managerial-archetypes/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Five Managerial Archetypes That Shaped My Leadership Style (And What I Learned From Each)" /&gt;&lt;h2 id="five-managerial-archetypes-that-shaped-my-leadership-style-and-what-i-learned-from-each"&gt;Five Managerial Archetypes That Shaped My Leadership Style (And What I Learned From Each)
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: If you recognize yourself in any of these vignettes, know that these are distilled stories meant to illustrate broader patterns. I&amp;rsquo;ve learned tremendously from each leader I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with, and I&amp;rsquo;m genuinely grateful for everything they&amp;rsquo;ve taught me that has shaped who I am today.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-charismatic-delegator-aka-the-ferris-bueller"&gt;The Charismatic Delegator (aka &amp;ldquo;The Ferris Bueller&amp;rdquo;)
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;You know this manager. They glide through the office with an almost supernatural ability to avoid looking busy while somehow keeping everything running. They&amp;rsquo;re rarely in meetings, masterfully delegate most tasks to their reports, and yet&amp;hellip; people genuinely like them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leader had an uncanny knack for interpersonal relationships and could read the political undercurrents of any situation. They&amp;rsquo;d show up fashionably late to meetings (always), drop a perfectly timed joke or wildly insightful observation, then disappear again. People either adored them for their hands-off approach or liked them while quietly wondering what exactly they did all day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt; This manager was the first person to tell me something revolutionary as a new leader: &amp;ldquo;You have agency to do what you need to do with your team to make things happen.&amp;rdquo; That permission to trust my instincts was invaluable. They taught me that sometimes the best leadership is knowing when to get out of people&amp;rsquo;s way or when to pull rank and do what needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was missing:&lt;/strong&gt; While the autonomy was empowering, I craved more concrete mentoring. Their laissez-faire approach meant I had to figure out a lot of leadership challenges on my own when some direct guidance would have accelerated my growth significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-aloof-guru"&gt;The Aloof Guru
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Picture this: You spend hours preparing for your 1:1, armed with thoughtful questions, industry insights, team updates, and burning issues that need guidance. You&amp;rsquo;re ready for a rich 45-minute conversation. Instead, you get a distracted leader who seems to be mentally somewhere else entirely, wrapping up after 15-20 minutes with vague, inspirational platitudes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leader had a frustrating pattern of responding to concrete problems with abstract wisdom. When I needed specific coaching on handling a difficult team dynamic, I&amp;rsquo;d get something like &amp;ldquo;trust the process&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;lean into the discomfort.&amp;rdquo; Meanwhile, initiatives they&amp;rsquo;d championed were quietly falling apart, and the team was left to navigate the chaos without clear direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes inspiration is exactly what people need, but sometimes they need you to roll up your sleeves and get tactical. The best leaders know when to be the visionary guru and when to be the hands-on problem-solver. Being only one or the other leaves gaps that your team will feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-fierce-advocate-aka-the-anti-change-agent"&gt;The Fierce Advocate (aka &amp;ldquo;The Anti-Change Agent&amp;rdquo;)
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This leader taught me everything about servant leadership and empathetic management. When I reported to them, I felt genuinely heard and supported. They&amp;rsquo;d fight tooth and nail for their team members, running concerns up the flagpole and using every ounce of their influence to make our work lives better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when I became their colleague, I saw the other side of this coin. Their reflexive pushback against any change from senior leadership—even necessary business changes—started to feel counterproductive. While advocating for your team is crucial, sometimes changes need to happen for the organization to survive and thrive, even if they&amp;rsquo;re initially unpopular or challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt; There&amp;rsquo;s an art to strategic pushback. I now try to save my &amp;ldquo;squeaky wheel quota&amp;rdquo; for things I feel passionately about rather than reflexively opposing every change. The key is helping your team understand why changes are happening while still being their advocate within reasonable bounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-emotional-volcano"&gt;The Emotional Volcano
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This manager wore every feeling on their sleeve—the good, the bad, and everything in between. We always knew exactly how they felt about any situation, person, or decision. While transparency can be valuable, this leader let emotions build and build until they&amp;rsquo;d explode in disruptive ways that affected the entire team&amp;rsquo;s dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their emotional volatility meant we often knew more than we should have about office politics, interpersonal conflicts, and leadership decisions that were still in flux. What started as refreshing honesty became exhausting unpredictability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt; Emotional transparency has its place in leadership, but it needs boundaries. Yes, your team should sometimes see when you&amp;rsquo;re upset about something important—it shows you care and have their backs. But sharing every emotional reaction creates unnecessary stress and can undermine your credibility as a steady presence your team can rely on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-puppet-master"&gt;The Puppet Master
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This leader turned management into a psychological chess game. They&amp;rsquo;d weaponize silence in meetings, waiting until the discomfort forced you to say something you might not have otherwise shared. Trust was a foreign concept—they were never warm, never vulnerable, never genuine in their interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They played favorites openly, and for a while, I was on the good side of that equation. Conference attendance, paid training, regular 1:1 attention—I got it all. But when their focus shifted to someone else, I received the lowest performance review of my career during what I considered my hardest-working year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most insidiously, they&amp;rsquo;d bring up gossip in individual conversations, designed to make people suspicious of their colleagues. And despite being in a player-coach role, whenever they needed to contribute as a &amp;ldquo;player,&amp;rdquo; their work barely met minimum standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt; Trust is the foundation of effective leadership, and manipulation erodes it faster than almost anything else. Favorites might feel good in the moment, but they create toxic team dynamics. Consistency in how you treat people and genuine investment in everyone&amp;rsquo;s success builds the kind of culture where people actually want to do their best work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-leadership-cocktail"&gt;The Leadership Cocktail
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what&amp;rsquo;s fascinating about these experiences: each archetype had elements worth emulating and others worth avoiding. The Charismatic Delegator&amp;rsquo;s trust in people&amp;rsquo;s agency, the Aloof Guru&amp;rsquo;s occasional inspirational moments, the Fierce Advocate&amp;rsquo;s genuine care, the Emotional Volcano&amp;rsquo;s transparency (in smaller doses), and even the Puppet Master&amp;rsquo;s strategic thinking (applied ethically)—there&amp;rsquo;s something to learn from every approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leaders who&amp;rsquo;ve had the most positive impact on my growth have been able to flex between these styles as situations demanded. They knew when to delegate and when to dive deep, when to inspire and when to get tactical, when to advocate and when to embrace change, when to be transparent and when to maintain professional boundaries, when to be strategic and when to be genuine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What managerial archetypes have shaped your leadership journey? Which ones do you find yourself gravitating toward, and which ones do you actively try to avoid?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Want more thoughts on leadership and management? Follow along for more real talk about the messy, complicated, and occasionally brilliant world of leading people.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Efficiency Trap</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/efficiency-trap/</link><pubDate>Mon, 16 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/efficiency-trap/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/efficiency-trap/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The Efficiency Trap" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Remember in &lt;em&gt;The Parent Trap&lt;/em&gt; when Lindsay Lohan&amp;rsquo;s characters spend the entire movie scheming to get their parents back together through increasingly elaborate plans? They could have just&amp;hellip; talked to them. But no, they needed to control every detail, orchestrate every moment, and make sure everything happened exactly their way. Spoiler alert: it got messy before it got better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s me in most work situations. I&amp;rsquo;m both Lindsay Lohans—the one with the perfectly planned strategy AND the one panicking when things don&amp;rsquo;t go according to plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-anxiety-spiral"&gt;The Anxiety Spiral
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When I start to feel the anxiety of not making a decision and moving into action, it begins with a familiar tightness in my chest that expands into low-level panic. I get clammy, my mind goes blank on everything except finding a path to resolution, and I become increasingly difficult to work with as my frustration builds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has led to more than one mistake and left more than one situation with others feeling just as frustrated as I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was a developer, I was used to sitting in refinement meetings where conversations would churn around technical implementation. I always felt like there was more to learn, and I never wanted us to make an incorrect choice. But now, in leadership, when I&amp;rsquo;m in meetings where my developers seem to talk in circles without making tangible progress on refinements, I start to lose it. We get caught in a swirl of what-ifs and future-proofing, completely throwing the agile process out the window.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="when-just-let-me-handle-it-backfires"&gt;When &amp;ldquo;Just Let Me Handle It&amp;rdquo; Backfires
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently, I made a classic efficiency-over-effectiveness mistake. I agreed to let two of my senior developers work on a new feature set that involved separating two different user experiences with largely the same functionality and a new identity provider. In my mind, I was being efficient—trusting my team, moving quickly, not micromanaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reality? There was no insight into progress, missed requirements piled up, and what should have been a straightforward feature became a months-long saga. My desire to move fast and avoid process actually created more work, more confusion, and more stress for everyone involved.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had fallen into what I now call the efficiency trap—prioritizing speed and my preferred way of doing things over actually getting the right outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-coach-question-that-broke-my-brain"&gt;The Coach Question That Broke My Brain
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;When my Torch coach asked me which I valued more—efficiency or effectiveness—my brain just went &amp;ldquo;buzzzzzzzz.&amp;rdquo; It didn&amp;rsquo;t compute. What do you mean there&amp;rsquo;s a difference? Getting things done correctly and quickly is what matters, right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the more I sat with it, the more I realized I was creating unnecessary anxiety for myself and my team. There&amp;rsquo;s real power in letting go of needing to do something a certain way within a certain timeframe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This question hit particularly hard because my team is currently navigating two critical challenges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We need to improve our predictability quarter over quarter to help with deliverable timelines&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We need to maximize the work we can produce with our current team size&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realized I needed to find a reasonable middle ground. Sometimes moving quickly and being efficient is the right approach. Other times, being effective—getting the right outcome—is all that matters at the end of the day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="putting-it-into-practice"&gt;Putting It Into Practice
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since the &amp;ldquo;just cut me a ticket and let me hack at it&amp;rdquo; disaster, I&amp;rsquo;ve tried to be more mindful about when I apply the brakes to enforce process and when I need to make a quick call and move on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our upcoming quarterly planning, we&amp;rsquo;re taking time to go through epics with a fine-tooth comb, making sure requirements are defined and we&amp;rsquo;re considering all aspects of technical implementation. Maybe the pendulum has swung too far in the other direction, but I think it&amp;rsquo;s good practice for the team. Once the actual development work begins, there should be less churn because we&amp;rsquo;ll know everything from day one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Stay tuned for a future update on how this approach affects our effectiveness and predictability.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-root-of-the-problem"&gt;The Root of the Problem
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This need for control and hyper-efficiency comes from being a Type A, people-pleasing, teacher&amp;rsquo;s pet. I&amp;rsquo;ve been this way my whole life, and I think it stems from wanting to be good at what I do—starting with being successful in school and following through to today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s this underlying script that I&amp;rsquo;ve been successful because I get things done my way, quickly. Not because I was just getting the right things done, period.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="how-this-is-changing-how-i-lead"&gt;How This Is Changing How I Lead
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This framework is still new for me in my leadership journey, but I&amp;rsquo;ve already noticed some shifts in how I approach my role:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I delegate more thoughtfully.&lt;/strong&gt; Instead of either micromanaging or completely hands-off approaches, I&amp;rsquo;m delegating to people I trust to be effective, with clear guidelines for check-ins, observable progress markers, and well-defined scope and requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I ask better questions.&lt;/strong&gt; Rather than jumping straight to &amp;ldquo;how do we do this faster,&amp;rdquo; I&amp;rsquo;m starting with &amp;ldquo;what outcome are we actually trying to achieve here?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m more comfortable with different approaches.&lt;/strong&gt; If someone on my team has a different way of reaching the same effective outcome, I&amp;rsquo;m learning to let them run with it instead of redirecting them to my preferred method.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The truth is, some of my best work has happened when I focused on being effective first, then found efficient ways to execute. The efficiency trap had me believing that speed and control were always the answer, but sometimes the fastest path to the right outcome is the one that feels slower in the moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And just like those scheming twins in &lt;em&gt;The Parent Trap&lt;/em&gt;, sometimes the most elaborate plan isn&amp;rsquo;t the one that gets you where you want to go—it&amp;rsquo;s the one that&amp;rsquo;s willing to adapt when life throws you a curveball.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What about you? Have you ever found yourself caught in the efficiency trap? I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear how you&amp;rsquo;ve learned to balance getting things done with getting the right things done.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>