<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Engineering Management on Figuring it Out</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/tags/engineering-management/</link><description>Recent content in Engineering Management on Figuring it Out</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ashleyedds.dev/tags/engineering-management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Incoming: Personal Rebrand</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/incoming-personal-rebrand/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/incoming-personal-rebrand/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/incoming-personal-rebrand/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Incoming: Personal Rebrand" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fair warning: this post is about to get introspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I participated in a Quantum Bloom Women&amp;rsquo;s Leadership Session provided by Relias, and let&amp;rsquo;s just say it&amp;rsquo;s one of those experiences that leaves you questioning some fundamental things about yourself. The good kind of questioning, though—the kind that makes you realize you&amp;rsquo;ve been carrying around beliefs that stopped serving you a long time ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session focused on examining the stories we tell ourselves—the beliefs and values that shape our professional identities but don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily help us grow. While the conversation touched on gender dynamics in the workplace, what I&amp;rsquo;m taking away goes deeper. It&amp;rsquo;s about the narratives we create, the shields we carry, and what happens when you finally decide to put them down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="when-your-heroes-have-the-same-doubts-you-do"&gt;When Your Heroes Have the Same Doubts You Do
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was in a breakout session with two colleagues I genuinely admire. These are women I consider experts in their fields—talented, productive, excellent communicators who build strong communities and possess deep knowledge in their areas of ownership. They&amp;rsquo;re the kind of professionals I look up to and think, &amp;ldquo;Yeah, that&amp;rsquo;s who I want to be like.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So imagine my surprise when both of them started talking about their insecurities. About not feeling good enough for their roles. About questioning whether they belong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These incredible, accomplished women were expressing the exact same doubts I carry around every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve been reading my posts for any length of time, you know my particular flavor of self-doubt. I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;m technical enough. I moved into management as a mid-level engineer without a computer science degree, having come to tech through a bootcamp as a second career. This insecurity was cemented early on when a leader told me that if I went into management before becoming a senior engineer, I&amp;rsquo;d never earn the respect of strong technical talent. They said senior developers wouldn&amp;rsquo;t respect me as a leader because of my lack of technical depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That comment? It stuck. Hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-shield-i-didnt-know-i-was-carrying"&gt;The Shield I Didn&amp;rsquo;t Know I Was Carrying
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the complicated part: this belief has actually served me in some ways. I&amp;rsquo;ve used this narrative to brand myself as a different kind of engineering leader—one who brings skills beyond the purely technical, who can fill gaps in a strongly technical leadership team. And honestly? That story has worked. It&amp;rsquo;s proven valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;rsquo;s also been a cage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve avoided situations where I&amp;rsquo;d be technically challenged. I&amp;rsquo;ve controlled the narrative by preemptively telling people—especially those I perceive as highly technical—that I&amp;rsquo;m &amp;ldquo;not a technical leader.&amp;rdquo; By saying it first, I manage their expectations and protect myself from judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that while there&amp;rsquo;s power in controlling how others see you, this approach has been unnecessarily reducing my value. It undermines how good I actually am at my job. And I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; good at my job. I&amp;rsquo;m very good at what I do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I shared this belief in our breakout session, the women I admire pushed back immediately. They told me I am technical. That they&amp;rsquo;ve always seen me as technical. That this story I tell myself doesn&amp;rsquo;t match the reality they see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we went around sharing our limiting beliefs, we were all genuinely shocked to discover we felt similarly diminished in different ways. Watching these talented women undersell their own skill sets was both disheartening and revealing—revealing of how we&amp;rsquo;ve internalized expectations and lost trust in ourselves over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-moment-everything-shifted"&gt;The Moment Everything Shifted
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the end of the exercise, we were asked to rewrite our limiting beliefs. My first attempt was predictably safe: &amp;ldquo;My lack of technical skills does not diminish my value in my role.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the women in my group stopped me cold. &amp;ldquo;You need to stop saying you&amp;rsquo;re not technical. Period. That&amp;rsquo;s not serving you and it never will.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I tried again. This time, I wrote something simple and terrifying: &lt;strong&gt;I am a technical leader.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There it is. That&amp;rsquo;s the rebrand. No more hedging, no more caveating, no more controlling the narrative by diminishing myself first. This blog will no longer be a space for ruminating on why I&amp;rsquo;m not enough. I&amp;rsquo;m going to own what I bring, challenge myself, and actually grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-perfection-problem"&gt;The Perfection Problem
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another theme that emerged in our session was the pressure to be perfect. Many of us talked about growing up with expectations to excel at everything—to be the A+ student, the top of the class, the one who never makes mistakes. While this isn&amp;rsquo;t exclusively a gendered experience, I do think we internalize these expectations in different ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That people-pleasing, teacher&amp;rsquo;s-pet programming from our youth? Sure, it&amp;rsquo;s part of why we&amp;rsquo;re successful. But at what cost? How much are we missing out on because we won&amp;rsquo;t put ourselves in situations where we might not be the best in the room?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has to be a way to keep our drive while establishing healthier boundaries. It requires checking in with ourselves when we&amp;rsquo;re obsessing over the perfect wording of an email or avoiding an opportunity because we&amp;rsquo;re not guaranteed to excel. We need to allow ourselves to be in uncomfortable spaces, to potentially fail, and to see what happens when we stop limiting ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-communication-style-trap"&gt;The Communication Style Trap
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The third insight that really landed for me was about how we compare ourselves to colleagues who use more direct, assertive, sometimes aggressive communication styles. Many of us bring more empathetic, open-minded approaches to getting things done, yet we watch the more abrupt style get rewarded more often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes sense when you consider that corporate America was designed by and for a specific demographic. The system cyclically supports certain communication styles and ways of working. (If you haven&amp;rsquo;t read the Harvard Business Review article &lt;a class="link" href="https://hbr.org/2021/02/stop-telling-women-they-have-imposter-syndrome" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;&amp;ldquo;Stop Telling Women They Have Imposter Syndrome,&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; I highly recommend it—it articulates this dynamic perfectly.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s what I realized: someone who can learn from direct, assertive approaches &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; embrace empathetic, holistic communication? That person has access to a genuine superpower. Knowing when to be direct and when to be empathetic, understanding when to focus on goals and when to engage with someone as a whole person—this isn&amp;rsquo;t a weakness. It&amp;rsquo;s flexibility and range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The corporate value system is shifting, slowly but surely. I hope my generation of leaders—those of us who tend to be more thoughtful about the whole person and the whole situation—can help accelerate that change. We don&amp;rsquo;t need to place arbitrary value on one approach over another just because of historical precedent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-comes-next"&gt;What Comes Next
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This conversation was a turning point. I&amp;rsquo;m walking away with a reworked belief system, one that actually supports who I am and where I want to go instead of holding me back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to be clear: while these conversations often center on gender, this isn&amp;rsquo;t about attacking anyone. It&amp;rsquo;s about acknowledging that certain dynamics exist in workplace cultures—dynamics that don&amp;rsquo;t always support different approaches or perspectives equally. For those navigating multiple intersections of identity, these dynamics can be even more complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to seeing how things evolve. I&amp;rsquo;m excited to keep having these conversations with colleagues. And honestly? I&amp;rsquo;m excited to see where this rebrand takes me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here we go. New narrative, same person—just finally willing to own all of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And hey, to the women who were in my breakout session—if you&amp;rsquo;re reading this, thank you. You&amp;rsquo;re both incredible, you absolutely have this, and I&amp;rsquo;m lucky to work alongside you. I can&amp;rsquo;t wait to see your own rebrands in action.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A 12-Year Lookback: From Speech-Language Pathologist to Engineering Leader</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/12-year-lookback/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/12-year-lookback/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/12-year-lookback/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post A 12-Year Lookback: From Speech-Language Pathologist to Engineering Leader" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Twelve years ago, I graduated with my Master’s Degree from East Carolina University. And it wasn’t in Computer Science or anything remotely related to technology. I’m the proud owner of a Master of Science in Communication Sciences and Disorders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who don’t know, I spent the first six years of my grown-up-career life as a Speech-Language Pathologist, working with adult patients in acute care settings. I loved the patient care, even though it could be emotionally difficult. I had the privilege of working with some of the most resilient people I’ve ever met—witnessing their strength as they overcame incredible obstacles. I had the opportunity to apply clinical problem-solving to create diagnoses, prognoses, and treatment plans, always keeping my patients’ individual goals and quality of life at the center of everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I didn’t love working &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; the healthcare system. After several years, I realized I couldn’t make a sustainable long-term career out of it. Still, my passion for healthcare—and a desire to make it better—led me to a coding bootcamp. Six and a half years later, I’m still lucky enough to be at Relias, where I help connect healthcare professionals with top-tier educational resources and tools that make a real difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things that almost held me back from making the leap to tech was my Master’s degree. I had invested years of time and a lot of money into earning it. I worried it would be a sunk cost—a credential that was now irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or… was it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, the intricacies of laryngeal nerves and tracheostomy care don’t show up in my day-to-day work anymore. But a graduate degree is about much more than memorizing clinical protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here’s what else that degree gave me:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research literacy:&lt;/strong&gt; I learned how to evaluate sources, synthesize information, and apply evidence-based methods—skills I now use in technical investigations and strategic planning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Critical thinking under pressure:&lt;/strong&gt; Whether it was managing a stroke patient’s cognitive recovery or debugging a legacy integration system, the ability to assess, analyze, and act is foundational.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Communication with empathy:&lt;/strong&gt; Working with patients taught me to deliver difficult news with compassion, adjust my style based on the audience, and truly listen—something I rely on heavily in management today.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goal-oriented planning:&lt;/strong&gt; Building measurable therapy goals for patients is surprisingly similar to setting OKRs or team goals in engineering. You need to start with the end in mind and work backward to create a practical path forward.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience working in healthcare also directly informs what I love most about being a manager. I thrive on building relationships rooted in trust and empathy. I’m deeply motivated by aligning people’s individual aspirations with broader team and business goals. I understand the emotional component of work and how much it matters to feel heard, supported, and challenged at the right times. Just like in clinical settings, I strive to create environments where people feel safe to grow—but I also know when to step in, ask the hard questions, and help someone level up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twelve years ago, Ashley had no clue she’d end up here. And that’s kind of incredible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here’s a reminder—don’t box yourself in because of the sunk cost fallacy. Your past experience isn’t wasted. It’s raw material. You can shape it into something new. Even if the path forward isn’t crystal clear yet, every step builds on the last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You just have to start walking.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Power of Immediate Action: How I Tamed My Endless To-Do List</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/immediate-action/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/immediate-action/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/immediate-action/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The Power of Immediate Action: How I Tamed My Endless To-Do List" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have a secret. Don’t worry, it’s a good one—and I’m happy to share it with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first became an Engineering Manager, I felt like I was drowning. My “To Do” column in Trello, my notebook, and my brain kept expanding like a balloon, no matter how many tasks I knocked out. And those are the tasks that I didn&amp;rsquo;t forget to keep record of&amp;hellip;there were many that just fell through the cracks. I was attending back-to-back meetings, responding to Slack messages, trying to think strategically, and still expected to deliver tangible results. Everything felt equally urgent, and the pressure to perform without dropping the ball was intense. I considered working late every night just to keep up, but let’s be real—that’s a shortcut to burnout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what changed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One small shift made a big difference: &lt;strong&gt;Immediate action&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not a magic bullet for every task, but it’s been incredibly effective for the small, high-context action items that are easy to forget. You know the ones—send a follow-up message, file a ticket for access, start a shared doc, ask someone for a clarification. Things that don’t require deep focus but can easily slip through the cracks if left for later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, when I’m in a meeting and someone mentions needing IT access, I file the ticket right then. If we need input from someone who isn’t present, I send them a quick Slack or email immediately. If we need a document to capture notes or decisions, I open it and share it before the meeting ends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach has two major benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Momentum&lt;/strong&gt;: Even if the task isn’t fully complete, it’s already moving. There’s energy and attention on it. In many cases, that’s enough to keep it progressing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust&lt;/strong&gt;: My team and cross-functional partners now know that when they ask for something, it won’t vanish into the void. I’ve built a reputation for being responsive, and that builds confidence and credibility over time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me be clear—this doesn’t mean I multitask my way through every meeting. I prioritize quick, low-effort actions that I can complete in 30-90 seconds. For deeper asks, I jot them down and return to them later with full focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of caveats, though. Acting immediately can sometimes mean I’m not 100% focused on the current conversation. I’ve missed a few small details here and there—but in my experience, the trade-off is worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, this strategy works for me because I don’t struggle with attention redirection. I understand this isn’t the case for everyone. If you have attention-related challenges, this method might feel overwhelming or counterproductive. That’s okay—there are other ways to harness the same principle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some alternatives to try:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leave 5–10 minutes at the end of each meeting&lt;/strong&gt; to knock out those quick tasks before jumping to the next one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a running “Immediate Action” list&lt;/strong&gt; during meetings and batch-process them during your next break.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use keyboard shortcuts, templates, and automation tools&lt;/strong&gt; to reduce friction for repeatable tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heart of the idea is this: the faster you give a task momentum, the more likely it is to get done—and the more others will see you as reliable, effective, and “on it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="what-works-for-you"&gt;What Works for You?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;If immediate action isn’t your style, what &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;? How do you stay on top of your fast-moving task list without burning out? I’d love to hear your strategies and hacks. Let’s share notes—after all, we’re all just figuring it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to leave a comment or reach out directly. I’m always looking to expand my toolkit—and yours too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let’s connect.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
If this resonated with you, consider subscribing to the blog or sharing it with someone who might benefit. We&amp;rsquo;re all learning how to lead and live better, one tiny change at a time.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Can Leadership Ever Truly Log Off?</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/can-leadership-truly-logoff/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/can-leadership-truly-logoff/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/can-leadership-truly-logoff/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Can Leadership Ever Truly Log Off?" /&gt;&lt;h2 id="can-leadership-ever-truly-log-off"&gt;Can Leadership Ever Truly Log Off?
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Balancing Work Responsibilities with the Need for True Time Off&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week was a tough one. In the early hours of Monday morning, my daughter woke up with a &lt;strong&gt;103-degree fever&lt;/strong&gt;, and I knew the flu had finally hit our household. Six hours later, I started feeling off myself, and thus began a week of so-called “rest” and recovery.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I officially took Monday and Tuesday off to care for my daughter and attempt to recover. I’m incredibly fortunate that my husband’s job is flexible—he was able to be home for support. Later in the week, when we felt less contagious, my mom even came up to help. Despite all that support, I probably could have used the full five days to rest. But work had other plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-reality-of-leadership-work-never-pauses"&gt;The Reality of Leadership: Work Never Pauses
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Even though I was out sick, pressing issues kept piling up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;site was experiencing issues.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;My &lt;strong&gt;Principal Engineer was also out&lt;/strong&gt; sick all week.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unexpected compensation and promotion discussions&lt;/strong&gt; were happening at the manager level.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I needed to &lt;strong&gt;meet with HR&lt;/strong&gt; to plan a hiring strategy for a new team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Annual reviews were due.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The usual &lt;strong&gt;weekly administrative to-dos&lt;/strong&gt; still needed to be completed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Had this been planned PTO, I would have worked ahead to finish tasks, delegated responsibilities, and set expectations for my time away. But when unexpected time off happens, there’s no time to prepare—you just do your best.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-frustration-of-being-pulled-back-in"&gt;The Frustration of Being Pulled Back In
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I found myself feeling &lt;strong&gt;frustrated&lt;/strong&gt;. I needed to step away and completely log off to care for my daughter and recover, but I didn’t feel like I truly could. There was &lt;strong&gt;too much happening&lt;/strong&gt;, too many unknowns, and I felt a responsibility to show up for my team—especially in the &lt;strong&gt;compensation and promotion discussions&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(That said, my &lt;strong&gt;peer in my department had my back&lt;/strong&gt; in my absence—thank you so much!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it made me question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How can I expect my team to feel confident that they can fully log off when I don’t set the same example?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Is it even possible for leadership to fully step away?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="if-leaders-cant-log-off-can-anyone"&gt;If Leaders Can’t Log Off, Can Anyone?
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;My boss, an &lt;strong&gt;SVP&lt;/strong&gt;, has been on extended PTO. Before he left, I promised him I wouldn’t bother him while he was away visiting family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yet… I &lt;strong&gt;reached out at least five times&lt;/strong&gt; (probably more). Sometimes I messaged him directly. Other times, I tagged him in notes or documents.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sorry, Boss.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="no-easy-answersjust-questions"&gt;No Easy Answers—Just Questions
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I don’t have a perfect solution here. I’m simply &lt;strong&gt;asking the question&lt;/strong&gt; and wondering what others experience or expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As leaders, &lt;strong&gt;can we ever truly go offline&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While planning ahead helps, &lt;strong&gt;what about unexpected time away&lt;/strong&gt;?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do we ensure our teams know that they &lt;strong&gt;can and should&lt;/strong&gt; fully disengage during PTO—if we don’t set that example ourselves?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’d love to hear from others: &lt;strong&gt;Have you successfully &amp;ldquo;fully logged off&amp;rdquo; as a leader? If so, how?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Your Cheese Just Missing? Learning to Embrace Change in Process Overhaul</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/missing-cheese/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/missing-cheese/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/missing-cheese/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Is Your Cheese Just Missing? Learning to Embrace Change in Process Overhaul" /&gt;&lt;h2 id="update-2325"&gt;Update 2/3/25
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since publishing this article, it has been brought to my attention that the &amp;ldquo;missing cheese&amp;rdquo; metaphor my colleague used, and I assumed an off-the-cuff-original, is actually likely referencing &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/0091876044?ref=cm_sw_r_ffobk_cso_cp_apin_dp_X47H5QMN1BPD16XBKCC9&amp;amp;ref_=cm_sw_r_ffobk_cso_cp_apin_dp_X47H5QMN1BPD16XBKCC9&amp;amp;social_share=cm_sw_r_ffobk_cso_cp_apin_dp_X47H5QMN1BPD16XBKCC9&amp;amp;starsLeft=1&amp;amp;skipTwisterOG=1&amp;amp;bestFormat=true&amp;amp;titleSource=avft-a&amp;amp;newOGT=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;&lt;em&gt;Who Moved My Cheese&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Dr. Spencer Johnston. I shall be adding this to my TBR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I received an incredible compliment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m really looking for your steady presence in this to really drive &amp;lsquo;Is this actually broken? Or is your cheese just missing?&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This simple remark made my day and sparked some deep reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, we overhauled our Jira project management workflows, starting fresh with a simpler, more streamlined strategy. The goal? Cut down on complexity to make our sprints more effective and reduce administrative overhead. We removed redundant workflow statuses—like tracking deployment and verification—and simplified the movement of tasks on the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite detailed pre-communication, training, and preparation, the change wasn’t universally welcomed. Which is fine. Pleasing everyone is impossible and change is tough. Within a week, the change management Teams channel lit up with frustrations, particularly around the removal of the &amp;ldquo;Ready for Testing&amp;rdquo; status—a step where tickets lingered until a test engineer was available to pick them up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some, the absence of this status felt like a loss of control. To them, their &amp;ldquo;cheese was missing,&amp;rdquo; but it felt like something was actually broken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When discussions in the channel veered toward resistance rather than solutions, I sent a message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m hearing &amp;rsquo;this thing doesn&amp;rsquo;t work like it did before&amp;rsquo;—and that&amp;rsquo;s kind of the point. The first couple of sprints may have growing pains, but we owe it to the people who spent time designing this to see if it works as intended. We want to hear feedback, but let’s give it a little time before making big changes.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, I felt anxious after hitting send. Pushing back publicly wasn’t in my comfort zone. But the response—a trio of heart emojis from process designers and positive feedback from project leads in a private DM—was reaffirming. They appreciated that I stood firm, giving the new workflow the time and space to succeed before yielding to reactionary changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I later offered office hours to help teams adapt to the new process. While there weren’t many takers, it signaled to me that teams were finding ways to work through the adjustment. Now, as we enter Sprint 2, I’m eager to evaluate pain points after completing Sprint 3 and ensure the process is genuinely serving its purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What stood out most to me was how this moment taught me something about myself. By holding boundaries and embracing discomfort, I discovered a steadying presence I hadn’t fully recognized until I received that comment in passing today. It’s a trait I’ll nurture, as it not only supports me but also adds value to my teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day change can feel unsettling—but sometimes missing cheese just means it’s time to find a new snack. 😉&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have you ever experienced “missing cheese” in your workflows or team processes? Share your thoughts in the comments! How do you balance patience with addressing feedback during times of change?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Bringing Developers into the Bigger Picture</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/bigger-context/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/bigger-context/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/bigger-context/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Bringing Developers into the Bigger Picture" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;When it comes to company All Hands meetings—especially those focused on larger business goals or strategies—developers often react with indifference. Comments like, “Just give me tickets and let me code,” or “It’s just exec speak; I’m not interested,” are all too common.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a new developer, I remember feeling the same way. The business side of things felt distant and disconnected from my day-to-day tasks. It was hard to see how these grand initiatives translated to my keyboard or my assigned Jira tasks. But looking back, I wonder—what do we lose when we dismiss that broader context? And are business leaders missing an opportunity to engage their entire workforce by failing to connect these ideas to everyone?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, my company held its 2025 Kickoff event. For the second year, the event was open to the entire organization, not just senior leadership, client-facing teams, or Product. Last year, I missed it because I was seven months pregnant and reluctant to be in a crowded space. This year, I finally got to sit in the audience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll admit—I really liked what I heard. The speakers shared important context, background, and insights. Having previously worked in healthcare, staying connected to the impact our products have on providers and patients is deeply meaningful to me. The executive and Product teams’ discussions helped me stay grounded in our mission to make a positive impact in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also gained a clearer understanding of how my team’s work aligns with the company’s larger vision. Seeing that connection reinvigorated my sense of purpose. As an engineering manager, I hope my team took away similar insights, and I plan to follow up in one-on-one meetings to reinforce our mission, vision, and goals. We’ll also revisit these ideas at our next department All Hands meeting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://www.svpg.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;The Silicon Valley Product Group&lt;/a&gt; introduced me to the concept of &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.svpg.com/missionaries-vs-mercenaries/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;“Missionaries, not Mercenaries”&lt;/a&gt;, and it comes to mind thinking about the importance of that broader business context. The essence of this idea is captured perfectly in the article:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Teams of missionaries are engaged, motivated, have a deep understanding of the business context, and tangible empathy for the customer. Teams of mercenaries feel no real sense of empowerment or accountability, no passion for the problem to be solved, and little real connection with the actual users and customers.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When senior leadership clearly defines the organization’s mission, and employees are open to listening, the result is a highly engaged, motivated team ready to deliver exceptional value to users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m fortunate to lead a team that genuinely understands our mission and user base. Sure, there are sprints when we just need to power through the backlog. That’s part of the job. But the moments that leave me energized are when my team asks questions like, “What about our users who don’t have internet access at work?” or, “How can we make this process simpler for a particular group of users?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Developers are natural problem solvers. Leaders, let’s not underestimate the value of involving them in the bigger conversations. When they understand the broader business context, their creativity can lead to extraordinary ideas. And developers, let’s take the time to listen to our leaders—it might just open doors to new ways of thinking and problem-solving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What’s your experience with connecting your work to the broader company mission? Whether you’re a leader or an individual contributor, share your thoughts or strategies in the comments—I’d love to hear them!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>