<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Career Development on Figuring it Out</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/categories/career-development/</link><description>Recent content in Career Development on Figuring it Out</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ashleyedds.dev/categories/career-development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Incoming: Personal Rebrand</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/incoming-personal-rebrand/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/incoming-personal-rebrand/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/incoming-personal-rebrand/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Incoming: Personal Rebrand" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fair warning: this post is about to get introspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I participated in a Quantum Bloom Women&amp;rsquo;s Leadership Session provided by Relias, and let&amp;rsquo;s just say it&amp;rsquo;s one of those experiences that leaves you questioning some fundamental things about yourself. The good kind of questioning, though—the kind that makes you realize you&amp;rsquo;ve been carrying around beliefs that stopped serving you a long time ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session focused on examining the stories we tell ourselves—the beliefs and values that shape our professional identities but don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily help us grow. While the conversation touched on gender dynamics in the workplace, what I&amp;rsquo;m taking away goes deeper. It&amp;rsquo;s about the narratives we create, the shields we carry, and what happens when you finally decide to put them down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="when-your-heroes-have-the-same-doubts-you-do"&gt;When Your Heroes Have the Same Doubts You Do
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was in a breakout session with two colleagues I genuinely admire. These are women I consider experts in their fields—talented, productive, excellent communicators who build strong communities and possess deep knowledge in their areas of ownership. They&amp;rsquo;re the kind of professionals I look up to and think, &amp;ldquo;Yeah, that&amp;rsquo;s who I want to be like.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So imagine my surprise when both of them started talking about their insecurities. About not feeling good enough for their roles. About questioning whether they belong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These incredible, accomplished women were expressing the exact same doubts I carry around every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve been reading my posts for any length of time, you know my particular flavor of self-doubt. I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;m technical enough. I moved into management as a mid-level engineer without a computer science degree, having come to tech through a bootcamp as a second career. This insecurity was cemented early on when a leader told me that if I went into management before becoming a senior engineer, I&amp;rsquo;d never earn the respect of strong technical talent. They said senior developers wouldn&amp;rsquo;t respect me as a leader because of my lack of technical depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That comment? It stuck. Hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-shield-i-didnt-know-i-was-carrying"&gt;The Shield I Didn&amp;rsquo;t Know I Was Carrying
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the complicated part: this belief has actually served me in some ways. I&amp;rsquo;ve used this narrative to brand myself as a different kind of engineering leader—one who brings skills beyond the purely technical, who can fill gaps in a strongly technical leadership team. And honestly? That story has worked. It&amp;rsquo;s proven valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;rsquo;s also been a cage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve avoided situations where I&amp;rsquo;d be technically challenged. I&amp;rsquo;ve controlled the narrative by preemptively telling people—especially those I perceive as highly technical—that I&amp;rsquo;m &amp;ldquo;not a technical leader.&amp;rdquo; By saying it first, I manage their expectations and protect myself from judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that while there&amp;rsquo;s power in controlling how others see you, this approach has been unnecessarily reducing my value. It undermines how good I actually am at my job. And I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; good at my job. I&amp;rsquo;m very good at what I do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I shared this belief in our breakout session, the women I admire pushed back immediately. They told me I am technical. That they&amp;rsquo;ve always seen me as technical. That this story I tell myself doesn&amp;rsquo;t match the reality they see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we went around sharing our limiting beliefs, we were all genuinely shocked to discover we felt similarly diminished in different ways. Watching these talented women undersell their own skill sets was both disheartening and revealing—revealing of how we&amp;rsquo;ve internalized expectations and lost trust in ourselves over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-moment-everything-shifted"&gt;The Moment Everything Shifted
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the end of the exercise, we were asked to rewrite our limiting beliefs. My first attempt was predictably safe: &amp;ldquo;My lack of technical skills does not diminish my value in my role.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the women in my group stopped me cold. &amp;ldquo;You need to stop saying you&amp;rsquo;re not technical. Period. That&amp;rsquo;s not serving you and it never will.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I tried again. This time, I wrote something simple and terrifying: &lt;strong&gt;I am a technical leader.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There it is. That&amp;rsquo;s the rebrand. No more hedging, no more caveating, no more controlling the narrative by diminishing myself first. This blog will no longer be a space for ruminating on why I&amp;rsquo;m not enough. I&amp;rsquo;m going to own what I bring, challenge myself, and actually grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-perfection-problem"&gt;The Perfection Problem
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another theme that emerged in our session was the pressure to be perfect. Many of us talked about growing up with expectations to excel at everything—to be the A+ student, the top of the class, the one who never makes mistakes. While this isn&amp;rsquo;t exclusively a gendered experience, I do think we internalize these expectations in different ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That people-pleasing, teacher&amp;rsquo;s-pet programming from our youth? Sure, it&amp;rsquo;s part of why we&amp;rsquo;re successful. But at what cost? How much are we missing out on because we won&amp;rsquo;t put ourselves in situations where we might not be the best in the room?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has to be a way to keep our drive while establishing healthier boundaries. It requires checking in with ourselves when we&amp;rsquo;re obsessing over the perfect wording of an email or avoiding an opportunity because we&amp;rsquo;re not guaranteed to excel. We need to allow ourselves to be in uncomfortable spaces, to potentially fail, and to see what happens when we stop limiting ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-communication-style-trap"&gt;The Communication Style Trap
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The third insight that really landed for me was about how we compare ourselves to colleagues who use more direct, assertive, sometimes aggressive communication styles. Many of us bring more empathetic, open-minded approaches to getting things done, yet we watch the more abrupt style get rewarded more often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes sense when you consider that corporate America was designed by and for a specific demographic. The system cyclically supports certain communication styles and ways of working. (If you haven&amp;rsquo;t read the Harvard Business Review article &lt;a class="link" href="https://hbr.org/2021/02/stop-telling-women-they-have-imposter-syndrome" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;&amp;ldquo;Stop Telling Women They Have Imposter Syndrome,&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; I highly recommend it—it articulates this dynamic perfectly.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s what I realized: someone who can learn from direct, assertive approaches &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; embrace empathetic, holistic communication? That person has access to a genuine superpower. Knowing when to be direct and when to be empathetic, understanding when to focus on goals and when to engage with someone as a whole person—this isn&amp;rsquo;t a weakness. It&amp;rsquo;s flexibility and range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The corporate value system is shifting, slowly but surely. I hope my generation of leaders—those of us who tend to be more thoughtful about the whole person and the whole situation—can help accelerate that change. We don&amp;rsquo;t need to place arbitrary value on one approach over another just because of historical precedent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-comes-next"&gt;What Comes Next
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This conversation was a turning point. I&amp;rsquo;m walking away with a reworked belief system, one that actually supports who I am and where I want to go instead of holding me back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to be clear: while these conversations often center on gender, this isn&amp;rsquo;t about attacking anyone. It&amp;rsquo;s about acknowledging that certain dynamics exist in workplace cultures—dynamics that don&amp;rsquo;t always support different approaches or perspectives equally. For those navigating multiple intersections of identity, these dynamics can be even more complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to seeing how things evolve. I&amp;rsquo;m excited to keep having these conversations with colleagues. And honestly? I&amp;rsquo;m excited to see where this rebrand takes me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here we go. New narrative, same person—just finally willing to own all of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And hey, to the women who were in my breakout session—if you&amp;rsquo;re reading this, thank you. You&amp;rsquo;re both incredible, you absolutely have this, and I&amp;rsquo;m lucky to work alongside you. I can&amp;rsquo;t wait to see your own rebrands in action.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Seven Years at Relias: Three Lessons That Transformed My Career Journey</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/seven-years-relias-career-lessons-learned/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/seven-years-relias-career-lessons-learned/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/seven-years-relias-career-lessons-learned/cover.png" alt="Featured image of post Seven Years at Relias: Three Lessons That Transformed My Career Journey" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today marks my seventh anniversary at Relias, a milestone that feels both surreal and significant. This is officially the longest I&amp;rsquo;ve stayed with any employer, and the longest I&amp;rsquo;ve committed to any single career path. Before joining Relias, I spent six years as a speech-language pathologist before taking the leap into software engineering through a coding bootcamp. Looking back at the person I was seven years ago, I&amp;rsquo;m not sure she would recognize the professional she&amp;rsquo;s become—though perhaps some core elements would feel familiar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-journey-of-growth-and-gratitude"&gt;The Journey of Growth and Gratitude
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;These seven years have been filled with tremendous growth, and distilling that evolution into just three key takeaways proved challenging. My learning has been rapid, consistent, and wonderfully varied. I&amp;rsquo;ve been fortunate to have incredible mentors throughout this journey—from the developers on my first team who taught me what it truly means to be a software engineer and how to navigate our codebase, to the leadership mentors who helped me identify my strengths and step confidently into my role as a leader, to my colleagues who taught me the nuances of engineering management, how to develop team members effectively, and the principles of servant leadership. Thank you to each and every person who has invested in my growth and shaped the professional I am today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="lesson-one-embracing-your-technical-identity"&gt;Lesson One: Embracing Your Technical Identity
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I AM a technical person.&lt;/strong&gt; For those who&amp;rsquo;ve followed my writing, you might be tired of hearing about my confidence struggles. But this realization is foundational, and it&amp;rsquo;s something I still navigate daily. The questions persist: Am I strong enough as a player-coach? Am I &amp;ldquo;technical enough&amp;rdquo; to continue advancing in this field?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The answer, definitively, is yes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seven years ago, I joined Relias with just enough React and SQL knowledge to be dangerous. Today, I&amp;rsquo;m partnering with my team to modernize our integrations solution. I&amp;rsquo;m coaching team members on leveraging GitHub Copilot to troubleshoot configuration issues and get new services running. I&amp;rsquo;m mentoring emerging leaders across the company about what engineering means at Relias and how our technical systems work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The evidence is clear. It&amp;rsquo;s time to own this identity and stop questioning it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="lesson-two-the-power-of-doing-hard-things"&gt;Lesson Two: The Power of Doing Hard Things
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I can do hard things.&lt;/strong&gt; (Thank you, Ms. Rachel, for this mantra!)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like many millennials, I grew up being labeled &amp;ldquo;gifted&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;smart.&amp;rdquo; The unintended consequence? Whenever I encountered something challenging—something that threatened that identity—I ran. If I failed, did that mean I wasn&amp;rsquo;t gifted anymore? I avoided the discomfort of not immediately excelling or achieving perfection, whether it was learning to rock climb or tackling complex projects.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I entered software engineering, where everything was hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coding doesn&amp;rsquo;t come naturally to me the way it might for others. I&amp;rsquo;ve had to work exceptionally hard to achieve even middle-of-the-road results. Initially, this reinforced my feelings of being &amp;ldquo;not technical enough&amp;rdquo; and prevented me from pursuing opportunities that could have accelerated my growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned: &lt;strong&gt;the space of discomfort is where growth happens&lt;/strong&gt;. I will see the other side. It might not be perfect. I might not get it right the first time. And that&amp;rsquo;s completely okay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="lesson-three-know-thyself-trust-thyself"&gt;Lesson Three: Know Thyself, Trust Thyself
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Know thyself.&lt;/strong&gt; I understand my value now. I recognize my strengths. I&amp;rsquo;ve learned not to let doubts—whether internal or external—prevent me from pursuing what I know I can excel at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The times I&amp;rsquo;ve questioned my value or doubted my capabilities have stalled my growth and potentially led to missed opportunities. Staying grounded in self-knowledge keeps me on the path I&amp;rsquo;m meant to follow. This self-awareness isn&amp;rsquo;t about arrogance; it&amp;rsquo;s about having the confidence to advocate for yourself and make career decisions aligned with your authentic strengths.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="moving-forward-with-confidence"&gt;Moving Forward with Confidence
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;These seven years at Relias have taught me that career growth isn&amp;rsquo;t linear, and transformation often happens in the spaces that feel most uncomfortable. Whether you&amp;rsquo;re considering a career transition, struggling with imposter syndrome, or questioning your technical capabilities, remember: you are more capable than you think, hard things become possible with persistence, and knowing yourself is your greatest professional asset.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s your career transformation story? Have you experienced similar challenges with technical confidence or imposter syndrome? I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear about your journey in the comments below. Let&amp;rsquo;s continue learning and growing together.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Are you navigating a career transition in tech or struggling with similar confidence challenges? Connect with me on LinkedIn to continue the conversation and share insights from your own professional journey.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Five Managerial Archetypes That Shaped My Leadership Style (And What I Learned From Each)</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/five-managerial-archetypes/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/five-managerial-archetypes/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/five-managerial-archetypes/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Five Managerial Archetypes That Shaped My Leadership Style (And What I Learned From Each)" /&gt;&lt;h2 id="five-managerial-archetypes-that-shaped-my-leadership-style-and-what-i-learned-from-each"&gt;Five Managerial Archetypes That Shaped My Leadership Style (And What I Learned From Each)
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: If you recognize yourself in any of these vignettes, know that these are distilled stories meant to illustrate broader patterns. I&amp;rsquo;ve learned tremendously from each leader I&amp;rsquo;ve worked with, and I&amp;rsquo;m genuinely grateful for everything they&amp;rsquo;ve taught me that has shaped who I am today.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-charismatic-delegator-aka-the-ferris-bueller"&gt;The Charismatic Delegator (aka &amp;ldquo;The Ferris Bueller&amp;rdquo;)
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;You know this manager. They glide through the office with an almost supernatural ability to avoid looking busy while somehow keeping everything running. They&amp;rsquo;re rarely in meetings, masterfully delegate most tasks to their reports, and yet&amp;hellip; people genuinely like them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leader had an uncanny knack for interpersonal relationships and could read the political undercurrents of any situation. They&amp;rsquo;d show up fashionably late to meetings (always), drop a perfectly timed joke or wildly insightful observation, then disappear again. People either adored them for their hands-off approach or liked them while quietly wondering what exactly they did all day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt; This manager was the first person to tell me something revolutionary as a new leader: &amp;ldquo;You have agency to do what you need to do with your team to make things happen.&amp;rdquo; That permission to trust my instincts was invaluable. They taught me that sometimes the best leadership is knowing when to get out of people&amp;rsquo;s way or when to pull rank and do what needs to be done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What was missing:&lt;/strong&gt; While the autonomy was empowering, I craved more concrete mentoring. Their laissez-faire approach meant I had to figure out a lot of leadership challenges on my own when some direct guidance would have accelerated my growth significantly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-aloof-guru"&gt;The Aloof Guru
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Picture this: You spend hours preparing for your 1:1, armed with thoughtful questions, industry insights, team updates, and burning issues that need guidance. You&amp;rsquo;re ready for a rich 45-minute conversation. Instead, you get a distracted leader who seems to be mentally somewhere else entirely, wrapping up after 15-20 minutes with vague, inspirational platitudes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This leader had a frustrating pattern of responding to concrete problems with abstract wisdom. When I needed specific coaching on handling a difficult team dynamic, I&amp;rsquo;d get something like &amp;ldquo;trust the process&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;lean into the discomfort.&amp;rdquo; Meanwhile, initiatives they&amp;rsquo;d championed were quietly falling apart, and the team was left to navigate the chaos without clear direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt; Sometimes inspiration is exactly what people need, but sometimes they need you to roll up your sleeves and get tactical. The best leaders know when to be the visionary guru and when to be the hands-on problem-solver. Being only one or the other leaves gaps that your team will feel.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-fierce-advocate-aka-the-anti-change-agent"&gt;The Fierce Advocate (aka &amp;ldquo;The Anti-Change Agent&amp;rdquo;)
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This leader taught me everything about servant leadership and empathetic management. When I reported to them, I felt genuinely heard and supported. They&amp;rsquo;d fight tooth and nail for their team members, running concerns up the flagpole and using every ounce of their influence to make our work lives better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But when I became their colleague, I saw the other side of this coin. Their reflexive pushback against any change from senior leadership—even necessary business changes—started to feel counterproductive. While advocating for your team is crucial, sometimes changes need to happen for the organization to survive and thrive, even if they&amp;rsquo;re initially unpopular or challenging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt; There&amp;rsquo;s an art to strategic pushback. I now try to save my &amp;ldquo;squeaky wheel quota&amp;rdquo; for things I feel passionately about rather than reflexively opposing every change. The key is helping your team understand why changes are happening while still being their advocate within reasonable bounds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-emotional-volcano"&gt;The Emotional Volcano
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This manager wore every feeling on their sleeve—the good, the bad, and everything in between. We always knew exactly how they felt about any situation, person, or decision. While transparency can be valuable, this leader let emotions build and build until they&amp;rsquo;d explode in disruptive ways that affected the entire team&amp;rsquo;s dynamic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Their emotional volatility meant we often knew more than we should have about office politics, interpersonal conflicts, and leadership decisions that were still in flux. What started as refreshing honesty became exhausting unpredictability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt; Emotional transparency has its place in leadership, but it needs boundaries. Yes, your team should sometimes see when you&amp;rsquo;re upset about something important—it shows you care and have their backs. But sharing every emotional reaction creates unnecessary stress and can undermine your credibility as a steady presence your team can rely on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-puppet-master"&gt;The Puppet Master
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;This leader turned management into a psychological chess game. They&amp;rsquo;d weaponize silence in meetings, waiting until the discomfort forced you to say something you might not have otherwise shared. Trust was a foreign concept—they were never warm, never vulnerable, never genuine in their interactions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They played favorites openly, and for a while, I was on the good side of that equation. Conference attendance, paid training, regular 1:1 attention—I got it all. But when their focus shifted to someone else, I received the lowest performance review of my career during what I considered my hardest-working year.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most insidiously, they&amp;rsquo;d bring up gossip in individual conversations, designed to make people suspicious of their colleagues. And despite being in a player-coach role, whenever they needed to contribute as a &amp;ldquo;player,&amp;rdquo; their work barely met minimum standards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What I learned:&lt;/strong&gt; Trust is the foundation of effective leadership, and manipulation erodes it faster than almost anything else. Favorites might feel good in the moment, but they create toxic team dynamics. Consistency in how you treat people and genuine investment in everyone&amp;rsquo;s success builds the kind of culture where people actually want to do their best work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-leadership-cocktail"&gt;The Leadership Cocktail
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s what&amp;rsquo;s fascinating about these experiences: each archetype had elements worth emulating and others worth avoiding. The Charismatic Delegator&amp;rsquo;s trust in people&amp;rsquo;s agency, the Aloof Guru&amp;rsquo;s occasional inspirational moments, the Fierce Advocate&amp;rsquo;s genuine care, the Emotional Volcano&amp;rsquo;s transparency (in smaller doses), and even the Puppet Master&amp;rsquo;s strategic thinking (applied ethically)—there&amp;rsquo;s something to learn from every approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leaders who&amp;rsquo;ve had the most positive impact on my growth have been able to flex between these styles as situations demanded. They knew when to delegate and when to dive deep, when to inspire and when to get tactical, when to advocate and when to embrace change, when to be transparent and when to maintain professional boundaries, when to be strategic and when to be genuine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What managerial archetypes have shaped your leadership journey? Which ones do you find yourself gravitating toward, and which ones do you actively try to avoid?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Want more thoughts on leadership and management? Follow along for more real talk about the messy, complicated, and occasionally brilliant world of leading people.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Leadership Paradox: Why Showing Your Unhappiness Makes You a Better Leader</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/leadership-paradox/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/leadership-paradox/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/leadership-paradox/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The Leadership Paradox: Why Showing Your Unhappiness Makes You a Better Leader" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;As leaders, we&amp;rsquo;re often taught that emotional control is paramount. We learn to stay calm under pressure, think before we speak, and approach every situation with level-headed rationality. But what if this approach—while valuable—is missing a crucial component of effective leadership?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-feedback-that-changed-everything"&gt;The Feedback That Changed Everything
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;During my participation in a leadership accelerator program at Relias, I received feedback that fundamentally challenged how I viewed effective leadership. The comprehensive assessment revealed something I hadn&amp;rsquo;t considered: my pride in remaining emotionally detached might actually be limiting my effectiveness as a leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The conversation involved a leader I deeply respect—someone whose approach differs completely from mine yet achieves remarkable results. Through our discussion with a facilitator from our parent company, an uncomfortable truth emerged about my leadership style.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-default-leadership-response"&gt;My Default Leadership Response
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;For years, I&amp;rsquo;ve operated under a specific framework when facing challenging situations or feeling upset:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Remove myself from the immediate situation&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Process emotions privately until I feel calm and level-headed&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Return to address the issue without emotional involvement&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on constructive, forward-moving solutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach felt rational, professional, and respectful. It aligned with my personal values and seemed to avoid the pitfalls of reactive, emotion-driven communication that I&amp;rsquo;d witnessed create problems in other contexts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-surprising-truth-about-leadership-communication"&gt;The Surprising Truth About Leadership Communication
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The feedback I received was both simple and profound: &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s important as a leader that you sometimes let people know that you are unhappy with them.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This statement struck me like lightning because it ran completely counter to my self-image as a leader. I had spent considerable effort developing systems to avoid communicating emotionally, believing this made me more effective and professional.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-emotional-detachment-can-backfire"&gt;Why Emotional Detachment Can Backfire
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;What I learned through this experience is that my well-intentioned approach was creating an unintended consequence. By removing all emotion from my communication, I was inadvertently:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Downplaying the severity of situations&lt;/strong&gt; that warranted concern&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Depriving team members of important contextual information&lt;/strong&gt; about the impact of their actions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Missing opportunities for immediate course correction&lt;/strong&gt; through emotional feedback&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reducing the motivational impact&lt;/strong&gt; of my leadership communication&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-strategic-value-of-showing-unhappiness"&gt;The Strategic Value of Showing Unhappiness
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The revelation helped me understand that a leader&amp;rsquo;s unhappiness with a situation serves multiple strategic purposes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="immediate-signal-strength"&gt;Immediate Signal Strength
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;When team members see that their leader is genuinely upset about an outcome, it immediately communicates the gravity of the situation in ways that calm, rational feedback cannot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="creating-coachable-moments"&gt;Creating Coachable Moments
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;That moment when someone thinks, &amp;ldquo;Oh no, my boss is upset with me because of this&amp;rdquo; becomes a powerful catalyst for self-reflection and behavioral change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="authentic-relationship-building"&gt;Authentic Relationship Building
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Showing genuine emotion (when appropriate) demonstrates that you&amp;rsquo;re invested in outcomes and care deeply about the team&amp;rsquo;s success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="clear-expectation-setting"&gt;Clear Expectation Setting
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Your emotional response helps team members calibrate their understanding of what matters most and what standards they&amp;rsquo;re expected to meet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-two-phase-leadership-approach"&gt;The Two-Phase Leadership Approach
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The key insight wasn&amp;rsquo;t to abandon my thoughtful, rational approach entirely, but rather to implement a two-phase strategy:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="phase-1-immediate-emotional-feedback"&gt;Phase 1: Immediate Emotional Feedback
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Allow team members to witness and understand your genuine reaction to situations when they occur. This provides immediate context and impact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="phase-2-reflective-problem-solving"&gt;Phase 2: Reflective Problem-Solving
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Later, when emotions have settled, engage in the deeper, analytical conversation about what happened and how to improve moving forward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="balancing-emotional-intelligence-with-authentic-leadership"&gt;Balancing Emotional Intelligence with Authentic Leadership
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This experience taught me that effective leadership isn&amp;rsquo;t about eliminating emotion—it&amp;rsquo;s about using emotion strategically. The goal isn&amp;rsquo;t to become reactive or lose professional composure, but rather to ensure that the full picture of your leadership perspective is communicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your frustration, disappointment, or concern about a situation is itself valuable information for your team. It helps them understand not just what went wrong, but how significantly it impacted the broader goals and relationships they care about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="implementing-constructive-emotional-leadership"&gt;Implementing Constructive Emotional Leadership
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re like me and tend toward emotional restraint in leadership situations, consider these strategies:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow Initial Reactions:&lt;/strong&gt; Give yourself permission to show genuine concern or disappointment when it first occurs, rather than immediately suppressing it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use Emotion as Data:&lt;/strong&gt; Treat your emotional responses as valuable information to share with your team about priorities and expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Follow Up Thoughtfully:&lt;/strong&gt; Maintain your commitment to reflective, solution-oriented conversations, but don&amp;rsquo;t let them replace the immediate emotional feedback.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Model Emotional Intelligence:&lt;/strong&gt; Show your team that emotions can be acknowledged and expressed professionally without derailing productive communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-leadership-growth-mindset"&gt;The Leadership Growth Mindset
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Perhaps the most valuable aspect of this feedback was how it challenged my assumptions about what makes a &amp;ldquo;good&amp;rdquo; leader. Growth in leadership often requires us to examine our comfortable patterns and consider whether they&amp;rsquo;re serving our teams as effectively as we believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leader who gave me this feedback approaches leadership completely differently than I do, yet achieves incredible results. This experience reminded me that there&amp;rsquo;s no single template for effective leadership—but there are always opportunities to expand our toolkit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="moving-forward-emotion-as-leadership-tool"&gt;Moving Forward: Emotion as Leadership Tool
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Today, I&amp;rsquo;m still the same person who values thoughtful, rational problem-solving. But I&amp;rsquo;ve added a new dimension to my leadership approach: the strategic use of authentic emotional communication.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When something goes wrong now, I don&amp;rsquo;t hide my disappointment. I let my team see that I&amp;rsquo;m genuinely upset about the outcome, because that unhappiness is part of the feedback they need to fully understand the situation and grow from it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal isn&amp;rsquo;t to become more emotional as a leader—it&amp;rsquo;s to become more complete in how we communicate the full spectrum of our leadership perspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What surprising feedback have you received that changed your approach to leadership? How do you balance emotional authenticity with professional communication in your role?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>When Your Former Manager Apologizes: Lessons from My Early Management Transition</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/apology/</link><pubDate>Fri, 27 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/apology/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/apology/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post When Your Former Manager Apologizes: Lessons from My Early Management Transition" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Sometimes the most powerful career moments happen years after the fact. Recently, I received an unexpected LinkedIn message that made me reflect on one of the most pivotal conversations of my early career—and the lessons it taught me about trusting your instincts when transitioning into management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-backstory-when-coding-wasnt-my-calling"&gt;The Backstory: When Coding Wasn&amp;rsquo;t My Calling
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Back in my developer days, I had a realization that many engineers face but don&amp;rsquo;t always voice: coding wasn&amp;rsquo;t my passion. Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong—I liked it well enough, but I was honestly struggling to produce what I considered quality work. There&amp;rsquo;s a certain mental block that kicks in when you&amp;rsquo;re working outside your zone of genius, and for me, that happened once problems reached a certain complexity level.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was working in a tech stack I hadn&amp;rsquo;t trained for in bootcamp. While I&amp;rsquo;d become competent in Angular, I had zero interest in learning C# to support our backend and truly fulfill my &amp;ldquo;fullstack&amp;rdquo; job title. My heart just wasn&amp;rsquo;t in the technical depth required.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s what I &lt;em&gt;was&lt;/em&gt; passionate about: I&amp;rsquo;d worked incredibly hard on a project converting our legacy, manual deployment process into Azure DevOps pipelines. I was making connections outside the direct software engineering groups, thinking deeply about DevOps culture, operational considerations, and overall process improvement. I wanted to focus on how we got the job done, not just what we built.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming from my background as a Speech-Language Pathologist, I knew I was good with people. I missed having that human element as a focus of my day—working with varied professionals toward common goals, identifying objectives, and strategizing paths to reach them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I was ready for management. I craved it.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-conversation-that-stuck"&gt;The Conversation That Stuck
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d just received a promotion to mid-level and was getting direct coaching around transitioning into leadership. In my mind, I didn&amp;rsquo;t need to become a senior developer before becoming a manager (a topic that probably deserves its own blog series).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During a 1:1, my manager and I were building an upskilling plan. He was focused on getting me to a senior role, which meant extensive C# training—work I genuinely didn&amp;rsquo;t want to do. When I made my case for a different path, in a moment of frustration, he told me I was being &lt;strong&gt;impatient&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That word hit me hard for several reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I felt like I was finally doing what everyone said I should do&lt;/strong&gt;: advocating for myself. As someone who&amp;rsquo;s naturally conflict-avoidant, this was growth for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I&amp;rsquo;d never seen this manager frustrated with me before&lt;/strong&gt;. It felt like I&amp;rsquo;d hit a nerve, and I couldn&amp;rsquo;t understand why.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Creating shared understanding of goals and paths forward was supposed to be my strength&lt;/strong&gt;. But now that I was on the receiving end of career guidance, was I missing something?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not long after, this manager left for another opportunity. Within a few years, I successfully transitioned into management without becoming a senior developer first. But that moment—that word &amp;ldquo;impatient&amp;rdquo;—lingered like a gray cloud over my career journey.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-apology-that-changed-everything"&gt;The Apology That Changed Everything
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Recently, that same manager reached out on LinkedIn with an unexpected message: an apology. He acknowledged that our interaction had made an impact on him too. He said he was proud of me and felt he&amp;rsquo;d made a mistake not recognizing I was ready for management.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;re reading this, Manager-of-Before, thank you. I can&amp;rsquo;t express how much it means to know you&amp;rsquo;re proud of me and see in me what I was striving for back then.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This apology came at a time when I&amp;rsquo;d been questioning whether I truly made the right choice moving into management as early as I did. The answer, honestly, depends on the day. But knowing that he—on the other side of our previous interaction—sees me thriving in this role means everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="three-lessons-im-taking-forward"&gt;Three Lessons I&amp;rsquo;m Taking Forward
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reflecting on this experience, here are the insights swirling in my head:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="1-trust-your-gut-when-you-know-youre-ready"&gt;1. Trust Your Gut When You Know You&amp;rsquo;re Ready
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;If you feel ready for something in your bones, don&amp;rsquo;t automatically let others convince you otherwise. There&amp;rsquo;s wisdom in your intuition about your own readiness, especially when it comes to leveraging existing strengths in new ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="2-your-leaders-know-youlisten-thoughtfully-to-pushback"&gt;2. Your Leaders Know You—Listen Thoughtfully to Pushback
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;When managers push back on your career aspirations, try not to take it personally immediately. Consider their perspective thoughtfully. They may see development areas you haven&amp;rsquo;t acknowledged, or they may be operating from their own constraints and experiences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="3-intense-responses-often-have-context-you-cant-see"&gt;3. Intense Responses Often Have Context You Can&amp;rsquo;t See
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;If your manager has a strong reaction to something, it&amp;rsquo;s not necessarily about what&amp;rsquo;s happening in that moment. Other pressures, constraints, or experiences may be narrowing their perspective and making it harder for them to show up as their best selves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-bigger-picture-on-early-management-transitions"&gt;The Bigger Picture on Early Management Transitions
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This experience reinforced something I&amp;rsquo;m passionate about: the path into management doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be linear. While technical expertise matters, management is fundamentally about people, process, and vision. Sometimes the skills that make you ready for leadership—emotional intelligence, systems thinking, collaborative problem-solving—don&amp;rsquo;t perfectly align with traditional technical progression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The key is honest self-assessment: Are you avoiding management because you&amp;rsquo;re not ready, or are you avoiding technical depth because management is where your strengths and interests truly lie?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="your-turn-trusting-your-career-instincts"&gt;Your Turn: Trusting Your Career Instincts
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have you ever had a career conversation that stuck with you? A moment when you advocated for yourself and faced unexpected resistance? I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear about your experiences with non-traditional career transitions and how you navigated the tension between others&amp;rsquo; expectations and your own intuition.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>My Self-Rebrand: Owning the Room in My Own Way</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/self-rebrand/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/self-rebrand/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/self-rebrand/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post My Self-Rebrand: Owning the Room in My Own Way" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Have you ever had to go through a personal rebrand?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For our entire lives, we tell ourselves stories about ourselves. Others tell us stories about ourselves. And around and around it goes. Before long, all the neural pathways in our brains are deeply rooted in specific ideas, and it can be incredibly difficult to get them to move, bend, and change to fit new perspectives about our self-images.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My entire life, I&amp;rsquo;ve been told I&amp;rsquo;m quiet and shy. Soft-spoken. And I am — most days it can be difficult to get my voice to carry across a dinner table, much less command a presentation space. So by extension, I never thought of myself as much of a public speaker. I assumed I was too shy, too soft-spoken, not bold or confident enough to deliver a presentation that left people walking away thinking, &lt;em&gt;“Wow, that was a great session.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, though, my role has required me to step up — presenting to large internal audiences, engaging leadership in smaller strategy sessions, and showing up with clarity and purpose. And while I’ve always felt confident in my knowledge of my team and product, I hadn’t internalized the idea that &lt;em&gt;I’m good at public speaking&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the larger forums I regularly speak at is a quarterly stakeholder review, where I summarize key accomplishments and upcoming goals. The audience spans hundreds of people, so I’ve developed a rhythm: keep it casual, keep it high-level, throw in a little humor. I know it’s not a space for deep technical dives — it’s about connection and clarity. This is where I’ve found my stride.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feedback from my most recent presentation floored me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The new VP of Product said it reflected deep product knowledge and praised the strength of my partnership with my Director of Product.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A fellow engineering manager joked that I must secretly be in Sales or Marketing — and meant it as a compliment.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;An engineer who’s usually disengaged during company-wide meetings said mine actually woke him up.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And most meaningfully, an engineer I’ve admired since I was an Associate — someone I’ve always been intimidated by — reached out privately with kind words I’ll treasure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s the thing: this isn’t the first time I’ve received positive feedback on my presentations. But for some reason, this time it clicked. &lt;em&gt;Maybe I am good at this.&lt;/em&gt; Maybe public speaking isn’t something I have to muscle through — maybe it’s something I’ve grown into.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can still be soft-spoken, quiet, and reserved. But that doesn’t mean I can’t also own a room when the time calls for it. It’s not either/or.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This experience taught me something valuable: we don’t have to stay locked into the stories we were told — or the ones we told ourselves. We can allow room for expansion. Growth. New neural pathways. Rebranding doesn’t mean we lose ourselves — it means we make room for who we’re becoming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve ever felt boxed in by an identity that no longer fits, ask yourself: &lt;em&gt;What if I’m more than that?&lt;/em&gt; Give yourself permission to evolve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="ready-to-rebrand-yourself"&gt;Ready to rebrand yourself?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;If this post resonated with you, I’d love to hear your story. Have you ever surprised yourself with growth in an area you thought was closed off? Drop a comment, send a message, or share this with someone who might need the nudge today.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>