<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Book Club on Figuring it Out</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/categories/book-club/</link><description>Recent content in Book Club on Figuring it Out</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ashleyedds.dev/categories/book-club/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Atomic Habits: The Fundamentals</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/atomic-habits-part1/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/atomic-habits-part1/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/atomic-habits-part1/cover.jpeg" alt="Featured image of post Atomic Habits: The Fundamentals" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;After finally shaking off the holiday slump, I dove into the introduction section of James Clear&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/em&gt;. Titled &lt;em&gt;The Fundamentals: Why Tiny Changes Make a Big Difference&lt;/em&gt;, this section lays the groundwork for Clear&amp;rsquo;s approach to behavior change. He introduces key concepts, such as how small habits can lead to big outcomes and the role of identity in building lasting change. He also outlines his &amp;ldquo;Four Laws of Behavior Change,&amp;rdquo; which I’ll explore more as I progress through the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="identity-and-behavior-change"&gt;Identity and Behavior Change
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve already reflected on the role of identity in behavior change in my &lt;a class="link" href="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/hello-world/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;first blog post&lt;/a&gt;. As part of my daily routine, I remind myself of my targeted identity: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I am healthy. I am present. I am OK with failure.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; This practice has helped me stay focused on the person I want to become.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, on those evenings when I’d rather skip a workout and veg out on the couch with a bag of chips, I pause and ask myself: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;What would a healthy person do right now?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; More often than not, this mindset gets me moving—maybe it’s just a short workout, but it’s still progress. And yes, I still veg out afterward—but without the chips!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="goals-vs-systems"&gt;Goals vs. Systems
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clear makes a compelling case for focusing on systems rather than goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Goals are about the results you want to achieve. Systems are about the processes that lead to those results.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This distinction resonated with me. Many successful people unknowingly excel at creating systems that enable their success. Clear simply sheds light on what’s happening behind the scenes. To make lasting change, you need systems that support your habits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take writing, for example. If I want to improve as a writer, I need systems that enable consistency. That means having a blog to publish my work, a running list of ideas, and time set aside for planning, writing, and editing. Without those systems in place, my goal to “write more” wouldn’t get very far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-power-of-tiny-changes"&gt;The Power of Tiny Changes
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clear challenges the myth that big changes come from dramatic, life-altering moments. Instead, he argues that small, consistent improvements lead to significant results over time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s so easy to overestimate the importance of one defining moment and underestimate the value of making small improvements on a daily basis.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea hit home for me. I often struggle with being a beginner and lack patience when I don’t see immediate results. This mindset has led me to fall into two traps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting overly ambitious goals or routines, then giving up when I fail to stick to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dismissing small opportunities to make progress—if I only have 5 or 10 minutes, it feels “not worth it,” so I do nothing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clear’s emphasis on tiny changes encourages me to flip those reactions on their heads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on themes and identity shifts rather than rigid, black-and-white goals. This approach aligns with my &lt;a class="link" href="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/hello-world/#theme-ing-in-the-new-year-" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;yearly themes&lt;/a&gt;, where I aim to channel effort into broader systems of growth rather than specific, binary outcomes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Embrace all progress, no matter how small. Even 10 minutes in the car listening to an audiobook is valuable—it’s time I wouldn’t have spent otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-do-you-think"&gt;What Do You Think?
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clear’s insights on systems over goals and the impact of small, consistent changes are already shifting how I approach habit-building. What about you? Do you focus more on changing systems or setting goals? How do you view the value of tiny changes? Let me know in the comments—I’d love to hear your thoughts!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to continue exploring &lt;em&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/em&gt; and see what practical strategies Clear shares. Next up is &lt;em&gt;The First Law: Make It Obvious.&lt;/em&gt; I hope you’ll join me for the next post in this Book Club series!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>