<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Growth Mindset on Figuring it Out</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/tags/growth-mindset/</link><description>Recent content in Growth Mindset on Figuring it Out</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ashleyedds.dev/tags/growth-mindset/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Incoming: Personal Rebrand</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/incoming-personal-rebrand/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/incoming-personal-rebrand/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/incoming-personal-rebrand/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Incoming: Personal Rebrand" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Fair warning: this post is about to get introspective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week, I participated in a Quantum Bloom Women&amp;rsquo;s Leadership Session provided by Relias, and let&amp;rsquo;s just say it&amp;rsquo;s one of those experiences that leaves you questioning some fundamental things about yourself. The good kind of questioning, though—the kind that makes you realize you&amp;rsquo;ve been carrying around beliefs that stopped serving you a long time ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The session focused on examining the stories we tell ourselves—the beliefs and values that shape our professional identities but don&amp;rsquo;t necessarily help us grow. While the conversation touched on gender dynamics in the workplace, what I&amp;rsquo;m taking away goes deeper. It&amp;rsquo;s about the narratives we create, the shields we carry, and what happens when you finally decide to put them down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="when-your-heroes-have-the-same-doubts-you-do"&gt;When Your Heroes Have the Same Doubts You Do
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I was in a breakout session with two colleagues I genuinely admire. These are women I consider experts in their fields—talented, productive, excellent communicators who build strong communities and possess deep knowledge in their areas of ownership. They&amp;rsquo;re the kind of professionals I look up to and think, &amp;ldquo;Yeah, that&amp;rsquo;s who I want to be like.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So imagine my surprise when both of them started talking about their insecurities. About not feeling good enough for their roles. About questioning whether they belong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These incredible, accomplished women were expressing the exact same doubts I carry around every day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;rsquo;ve been reading my posts for any length of time, you know my particular flavor of self-doubt. I don&amp;rsquo;t think I&amp;rsquo;m technical enough. I moved into management as a mid-level engineer without a computer science degree, having come to tech through a bootcamp as a second career. This insecurity was cemented early on when a leader told me that if I went into management before becoming a senior engineer, I&amp;rsquo;d never earn the respect of strong technical talent. They said senior developers wouldn&amp;rsquo;t respect me as a leader because of my lack of technical depth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That comment? It stuck. Hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-shield-i-didnt-know-i-was-carrying"&gt;The Shield I Didn&amp;rsquo;t Know I Was Carrying
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s the complicated part: this belief has actually served me in some ways. I&amp;rsquo;ve used this narrative to brand myself as a different kind of engineering leader—one who brings skills beyond the purely technical, who can fill gaps in a strongly technical leadership team. And honestly? That story has worked. It&amp;rsquo;s proven valuable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But it&amp;rsquo;s also been a cage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve avoided situations where I&amp;rsquo;d be technically challenged. I&amp;rsquo;ve controlled the narrative by preemptively telling people—especially those I perceive as highly technical—that I&amp;rsquo;m &amp;ldquo;not a technical leader.&amp;rdquo; By saying it first, I manage their expectations and protect myself from judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem is that while there&amp;rsquo;s power in controlling how others see you, this approach has been unnecessarily reducing my value. It undermines how good I actually am at my job. And I &lt;em&gt;am&lt;/em&gt; good at my job. I&amp;rsquo;m very good at what I do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I shared this belief in our breakout session, the women I admire pushed back immediately. They told me I am technical. That they&amp;rsquo;ve always seen me as technical. That this story I tell myself doesn&amp;rsquo;t match the reality they see.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we went around sharing our limiting beliefs, we were all genuinely shocked to discover we felt similarly diminished in different ways. Watching these talented women undersell their own skill sets was both disheartening and revealing—revealing of how we&amp;rsquo;ve internalized expectations and lost trust in ourselves over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-moment-everything-shifted"&gt;The Moment Everything Shifted
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;At the end of the exercise, we were asked to rewrite our limiting beliefs. My first attempt was predictably safe: &amp;ldquo;My lack of technical skills does not diminish my value in my role.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the women in my group stopped me cold. &amp;ldquo;You need to stop saying you&amp;rsquo;re not technical. Period. That&amp;rsquo;s not serving you and it never will.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I tried again. This time, I wrote something simple and terrifying: &lt;strong&gt;I am a technical leader.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There it is. That&amp;rsquo;s the rebrand. No more hedging, no more caveating, no more controlling the narrative by diminishing myself first. This blog will no longer be a space for ruminating on why I&amp;rsquo;m not enough. I&amp;rsquo;m going to own what I bring, challenge myself, and actually grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-perfection-problem"&gt;The Perfection Problem
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Another theme that emerged in our session was the pressure to be perfect. Many of us talked about growing up with expectations to excel at everything—to be the A+ student, the top of the class, the one who never makes mistakes. While this isn&amp;rsquo;t exclusively a gendered experience, I do think we internalize these expectations in different ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That people-pleasing, teacher&amp;rsquo;s-pet programming from our youth? Sure, it&amp;rsquo;s part of why we&amp;rsquo;re successful. But at what cost? How much are we missing out on because we won&amp;rsquo;t put ourselves in situations where we might not be the best in the room?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There has to be a way to keep our drive while establishing healthier boundaries. It requires checking in with ourselves when we&amp;rsquo;re obsessing over the perfect wording of an email or avoiding an opportunity because we&amp;rsquo;re not guaranteed to excel. We need to allow ourselves to be in uncomfortable spaces, to potentially fail, and to see what happens when we stop limiting ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-communication-style-trap"&gt;The Communication Style Trap
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The third insight that really landed for me was about how we compare ourselves to colleagues who use more direct, assertive, sometimes aggressive communication styles. Many of us bring more empathetic, open-minded approaches to getting things done, yet we watch the more abrupt style get rewarded more often.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This makes sense when you consider that corporate America was designed by and for a specific demographic. The system cyclically supports certain communication styles and ways of working. (If you haven&amp;rsquo;t read the Harvard Business Review article &lt;a class="link" href="https://hbr.org/2021/02/stop-telling-women-they-have-imposter-syndrome" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;&amp;ldquo;Stop Telling Women They Have Imposter Syndrome,&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; I highly recommend it—it articulates this dynamic perfectly.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s what I realized: someone who can learn from direct, assertive approaches &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; embrace empathetic, holistic communication? That person has access to a genuine superpower. Knowing when to be direct and when to be empathetic, understanding when to focus on goals and when to engage with someone as a whole person—this isn&amp;rsquo;t a weakness. It&amp;rsquo;s flexibility and range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The corporate value system is shifting, slowly but surely. I hope my generation of leaders—those of us who tend to be more thoughtful about the whole person and the whole situation—can help accelerate that change. We don&amp;rsquo;t need to place arbitrary value on one approach over another just because of historical precedent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-comes-next"&gt;What Comes Next
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This conversation was a turning point. I&amp;rsquo;m walking away with a reworked belief system, one that actually supports who I am and where I want to go instead of holding me back.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to be clear: while these conversations often center on gender, this isn&amp;rsquo;t about attacking anyone. It&amp;rsquo;s about acknowledging that certain dynamics exist in workplace cultures—dynamics that don&amp;rsquo;t always support different approaches or perspectives equally. For those navigating multiple intersections of identity, these dynamics can be even more complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to seeing how things evolve. I&amp;rsquo;m excited to keep having these conversations with colleagues. And honestly? I&amp;rsquo;m excited to see where this rebrand takes me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here we go. New narrative, same person—just finally willing to own all of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And hey, to the women who were in my breakout session—if you&amp;rsquo;re reading this, thank you. You&amp;rsquo;re both incredible, you absolutely have this, and I&amp;rsquo;m lucky to work alongside you. I can&amp;rsquo;t wait to see your own rebrands in action.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>When Your Nervous System Says "Run": The Courage to Give People Who Scare You a Chance</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/growth-through-uncomfortable-encounters/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/growth-through-uncomfortable-encounters/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/growth-through-uncomfortable-encounters/cover.png" alt="Featured image of post When Your Nervous System Says "Run": The Courage to Give People Who Scare You a Chance" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;My nervous system went into overdrive the moment I met her. Everything about this person screamed &amp;ldquo;threat&amp;rdquo; to my conflict-averse brain—the confident way she spoke about her accomplishments, the casual mention of impressive experiences, the ease with which she navigated conversations I found intimidating. Coming from what I perceived as a humble background, I felt instantly small and easily dismissed. &lt;em&gt;Who am I to this person with all these accolades?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every instinct told me to politely excuse myself and avoid future interactions. Instead, I made one of the most transformative decisions of my professional life: I chose to stay and engage with the discomfort.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="when-fear-masks-opportunity"&gt;When Fear Masks Opportunity
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;As leaders, we&amp;rsquo;re constantly pushing ourselves out of our comfort zones—whether it&amp;rsquo;s having difficult conversations, asking challenging questions, or simply letting people know when we&amp;rsquo;re upset rather than sugarcoating our feelings. Yet when that alarm bell triggers during first encounters, it feels easiest to retreat and minimize future contact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But here&amp;rsquo;s what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned from intentionally engaging with people who initially scared me: that nervous system response isn&amp;rsquo;t always signaling danger. Sometimes, it&amp;rsquo;s responding to something unfamiliar—and unfamiliar is often where our greatest growth lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I&amp;rsquo;ve consciously chosen discomfort over avoidance, several encounters stand out as particularly meaningful. Some of those people are now among my closest friends and most trusted advisors. The person I mentioned earlier? She&amp;rsquo;s someone I confide in regularly, someone who serves as both mirror and lighthouse when I need honest feedback. It turns out her apparent bragging was armor against her own self-consciousness—the same way my withdrawal was mine. We shared similar values but applied them differently, which is exactly why she could offer perspectives I couldn&amp;rsquo;t reach alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-learning-lives-in-both-outcomes"&gt;The Learning Lives in Both Outcomes
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;There are other meaningful encounters,however, that didn&amp;rsquo;t blossom into lasting friendships, but they taught me invaluable lessons about myself and others. In both cases, my initial discomfort was partially warranted—there were genuine misalignments in values or communication styles that made deep connection difficult. But engaging authentically allowed me to understand &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; I felt triggered, what those reactions revealed about my own growth edges, and how to trust my judgment more effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beauty lies in this: whether the relationship flourishes or fades, you&amp;rsquo;ve gained crucial data about yourself. You&amp;rsquo;ve practiced assuming positive intent, stretched your emotional intelligence, and hopefully offered something meaningful to the other person in return. Most importantly, you&amp;rsquo;ve learned to distinguish between your nervous system responding to genuine incompatibility versus simply responding to difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="practical-steps-for-engaging-with-discomfort"&gt;Practical Steps for Engaging with Discomfort
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Start with perspective-shifting.&lt;/strong&gt; Before your next networking event or team meeting, remind yourself that your initial discomfort might be pointing toward growth, not danger. When you meet someone who triggers that alarm, pause and ask: &amp;ldquo;What if I don&amp;rsquo;t know them well enough to judge? What might their perspective be?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Assume positive intent deliberately.&lt;/strong&gt; This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean ignoring red flags—it means giving people the benefit of the doubt when your nervous system reacts to unfamiliarity rather than actual threat. Ask yourself: &amp;ldquo;What if their confidence comes from a place of sharing rather than showing off? What if their directness is clarity, not aggression?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Engage with curiosity.&lt;/strong&gt; Instead of defensive questioning, try genuine inquiry. &amp;ldquo;Tell me more about that project&amp;rdquo; instead of internal skepticism. &amp;ldquo;How did you develop that approach?&amp;rdquo; rather than immediate judgment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust the learning process.&lt;/strong&gt; Whether the relationship deepens or remains surface-level, you&amp;rsquo;re building emotional agility and expanding your leadership capacity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-courage-to-stay-present"&gt;The Courage to Stay Present
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;In our hyperconnected yet increasingly polarized world, the ability to sit with discomfort and engage authentically across differences isn&amp;rsquo;t just a nice-to-have—it&amp;rsquo;s essential leadership currency. The people who challenge us, who make us squirm a little in their presence, often hold the keys to our next level of growth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of my most valuable professional relationships started with that stomach-dropping feeling of &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t belong here&amp;rdquo; or &amp;ldquo;This person is too much for me.&amp;rdquo; Learning to distinguish between productive discomfort and genuine warning signals has become one of my most valuable leadership skills.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your nervous system will always have opinions. But you get to choose whether to let those opinions make your decisions—or use them as data points in a much richer conversation about growth, connection, and possibility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about you?&lt;/strong&gt; Have you ever been surprised by a relationship that started with discomfort? I&amp;rsquo;d love to hear your stories in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*The image for this post was generated by AI&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A 12-Year Lookback: From Speech-Language Pathologist to Engineering Leader</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/12-year-lookback/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/12-year-lookback/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/12-year-lookback/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post A 12-Year Lookback: From Speech-Language Pathologist to Engineering Leader" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Twelve years ago, I graduated with my Master’s Degree from East Carolina University. And it wasn’t in Computer Science or anything remotely related to technology. I’m the proud owner of a Master of Science in Communication Sciences and Disorders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who don’t know, I spent the first six years of my grown-up-career life as a Speech-Language Pathologist, working with adult patients in acute care settings. I loved the patient care, even though it could be emotionally difficult. I had the privilege of working with some of the most resilient people I’ve ever met—witnessing their strength as they overcame incredible obstacles. I had the opportunity to apply clinical problem-solving to create diagnoses, prognoses, and treatment plans, always keeping my patients’ individual goals and quality of life at the center of everything.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, I didn’t love working &lt;em&gt;within&lt;/em&gt; the healthcare system. After several years, I realized I couldn’t make a sustainable long-term career out of it. Still, my passion for healthcare—and a desire to make it better—led me to a coding bootcamp. Six and a half years later, I’m still lucky enough to be at Relias, where I help connect healthcare professionals with top-tier educational resources and tools that make a real difference.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things that almost held me back from making the leap to tech was my Master’s degree. I had invested years of time and a lot of money into earning it. I worried it would be a sunk cost—a credential that was now irrelevant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or… was it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, the intricacies of laryngeal nerves and tracheostomy care don’t show up in my day-to-day work anymore. But a graduate degree is about much more than memorizing clinical protocols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Here’s what else that degree gave me:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research literacy:&lt;/strong&gt; I learned how to evaluate sources, synthesize information, and apply evidence-based methods—skills I now use in technical investigations and strategic planning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Critical thinking under pressure:&lt;/strong&gt; Whether it was managing a stroke patient’s cognitive recovery or debugging a legacy integration system, the ability to assess, analyze, and act is foundational.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Communication with empathy:&lt;/strong&gt; Working with patients taught me to deliver difficult news with compassion, adjust my style based on the audience, and truly listen—something I rely on heavily in management today.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Goal-oriented planning:&lt;/strong&gt; Building measurable therapy goals for patients is surprisingly similar to setting OKRs or team goals in engineering. You need to start with the end in mind and work backward to create a practical path forward.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My experience working in healthcare also directly informs what I love most about being a manager. I thrive on building relationships rooted in trust and empathy. I’m deeply motivated by aligning people’s individual aspirations with broader team and business goals. I understand the emotional component of work and how much it matters to feel heard, supported, and challenged at the right times. Just like in clinical settings, I strive to create environments where people feel safe to grow—but I also know when to step in, ask the hard questions, and help someone level up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Twelve years ago, Ashley had no clue she’d end up here. And that’s kind of incredible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here’s a reminder—don’t box yourself in because of the sunk cost fallacy. Your past experience isn’t wasted. It’s raw material. You can shape it into something new. Even if the path forward isn’t crystal clear yet, every step builds on the last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You just have to start walking.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Learning GA4 and Rediscovering the Joy of Growth</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/ga4-new-learning/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/ga4-new-learning/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/ga4-new-learning/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Learning GA4 and Rediscovering the Joy of Growth" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week, I earned my first new certification in years: &lt;a class="link" href="https://skillshop.exceedlms.com/student/catalog/list?category_ids=53-google-analytics" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Google Analytics&lt;/a&gt;, offered through Google Skillshop. And let me tell you—it felt &lt;strong&gt;SO GOOD&lt;/strong&gt;. From watching the videos and taking notes, to studying for the final exam, to finally passing and posting that shiny little badge on LinkedIn, I felt a sense of pride that I hadn’t experienced in a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally got to be the one to say: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m happy to share that I&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But beyond the badge, I’m proud of something deeper: the small, intentional choices I made that allowed me to chip away at the coursework despite a jam-packed schedule. Choosing to log in instead of doomscroll. Prioritizing my own growth alongside my responsibilities as a manager. Investing in myself again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not that I haven’t been learning—stepping into management, navigating a new tech stack, and entering the world of e-commerce was like jumping off a cliff into deep water. But this was different. This was structured, focused learning that I chose. And it reminded me how much I &lt;em&gt;missed&lt;/em&gt; that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding Google Analytics 4 was a key step for me as a leader. I’d never worked with SEO before—didn’t even realize how closely it ties into software development and data collection. I used to sit silently in meetings while our product managers and engineers discussed upcoming tagging work or issues with a poorly performing page. I’d listen, absorb, and nod&amp;hellip; but rarely contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now? After just one certification, I’ve already seen the impact. We just wrapped up our Q2 Big Room Planning, and for the first time, I was able to ask intelligent questions about data collection strategies for a new set of pages we’re rolling out. I even caught a user flow issue that hadn’t been considered yet—&lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; suggested a tagging approach to help track it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It felt empowering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combination of new knowledge and immediate application was an absolute rush. I remembered how curiosity, when nurtured, turns into confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now I’m hooked. I’m ready to keep going. But what next?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should I dive into &lt;strong&gt;Google Cloud Platform&lt;/strong&gt; (GCP) training to get more comfortable with the infrastructure side of things? Are there deeper SEO-related topics—like structured data, schema markup, or Lighthouse audits—that I should explore? What would help me show up even stronger for my team and our cross-functional partners?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve recently learned something new that shifted how you work, I’d love to hear about it. Let’s trade notes. Or if you’ve taken GCP or SEO courses you really liked, send them my way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s to the next learning curve. I’m ready.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;✨ Got suggestions for what I should learn next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Drop them in the comments, message me on LinkedIn, or send a carrier pigeon. I’m serious—I want to hear what’s helped you grow. Let’s build a little learning community together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you’ve been putting off that course, certification, or passion project? This is your nudge. Start today. A little at a time adds up, I promise.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mindful Curiosity</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/mindful-curiosity/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/mindful-curiosity/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/mindful-curiosity/cover.jpeg" alt="Featured image of post Mindful Curiosity" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my most recent coaching session, I sought guidance on an upcoming meeting with my management colleagues, directors, and SVP. I was nervous because I had received information about a change I didn’t agree with—one that I believed would significantly impact my team. &lt;em&gt;(It turned out my concerns were based on a misunderstanding, and my anxiety was unnecessary.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I explained my concerns, the questions I had, and my apprehension about how &amp;ldquo;pushing back&amp;rdquo; might be perceived, my coach interrupted with a thought-provoking question:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why do you think you&amp;rsquo;re pushing back? What I hear is your curiosity about the change and a desire to understand where it’s coming from.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That question completely reframed my perspective. Why did I instinctively view my desire to understand leadership decisions as resistance? Shouldn’t gathering context and reasoning be part of my role as an effective change agent for my team? Isn’t deeper understanding essential for:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Ensuring I have the right information before expressing concerns?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Framing concerns in a productive and constructive way?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This internalized fear of questioning leadership likely stems from deep-seated patterns in my psychology—an exploration for another time. But recognizing this mindset allows me to be more mindful in leadership interactions. Moving forward, when I feel anxiety creeping in, I’ll pause and ask myself:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Am I feeling anxious because I’m mislabeling my curiosity as pushback?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h2 id="strengthening-my-curiosity-muscle"&gt;Strengthening My Curiosity Muscle
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since this realization, I’ve also noticed other ways my curiosity (or lack thereof) manifests. Sometimes, I accept information or suggestions at face value without deeper exploration. If I want to continue growing as a technical leader, I need to challenge myself to dig deeper and ensure I have a well-rounded understanding before making decisions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-commitment-to-mindful-curiosity"&gt;My Commitment to Mindful Curiosity
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;To foster this growth, I’m setting the following personal challenges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reframing curiosity&lt;/strong&gt; – Asking leadership questions to understand a decision isn’t an act of defiance; it’s a tool for learning, effective communication, and advocacy for my team.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Seeking deeper understanding&lt;/strong&gt; – Instead of passively accepting information, I’ll actively engage, research, and explore different perspectives to develop a more informed viewpoint.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curiosity isn’t resistance—it’s a leadership strength. If I can embrace this mindset, I’ll not only become a stronger advocate for my team but also continue evolving as a leader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What about you?&lt;/strong&gt; Have you ever mistaken curiosity for pushback? How do you challenge yourself to ask better questions and seek deeper understanding? Let’s discuss in the comments!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Your Cheese Just Missing? Learning to Embrace Change in Process Overhaul</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/missing-cheese/</link><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/missing-cheese/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/missing-cheese/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Is Your Cheese Just Missing? Learning to Embrace Change in Process Overhaul" /&gt;&lt;h2 id="update-2325"&gt;Update 2/3/25
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Since publishing this article, it has been brought to my attention that the &amp;ldquo;missing cheese&amp;rdquo; metaphor my colleague used, and I assumed an off-the-cuff-original, is actually likely referencing &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.amazon.com/dp/0091876044?ref=cm_sw_r_ffobk_cso_cp_apin_dp_X47H5QMN1BPD16XBKCC9&amp;amp;ref_=cm_sw_r_ffobk_cso_cp_apin_dp_X47H5QMN1BPD16XBKCC9&amp;amp;social_share=cm_sw_r_ffobk_cso_cp_apin_dp_X47H5QMN1BPD16XBKCC9&amp;amp;starsLeft=1&amp;amp;skipTwisterOG=1&amp;amp;bestFormat=true&amp;amp;titleSource=avft-a&amp;amp;newOGT=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;&lt;em&gt;Who Moved My Cheese&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Dr. Spencer Johnston. I shall be adding this to my TBR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I received an incredible compliment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m really looking for your steady presence in this to really drive &amp;lsquo;Is this actually broken? Or is your cheese just missing?&amp;rsquo;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This simple remark made my day and sparked some deep reflection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, we overhauled our Jira project management workflows, starting fresh with a simpler, more streamlined strategy. The goal? Cut down on complexity to make our sprints more effective and reduce administrative overhead. We removed redundant workflow statuses—like tracking deployment and verification—and simplified the movement of tasks on the board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite detailed pre-communication, training, and preparation, the change wasn’t universally welcomed. Which is fine. Pleasing everyone is impossible and change is tough. Within a week, the change management Teams channel lit up with frustrations, particularly around the removal of the &amp;ldquo;Ready for Testing&amp;rdquo; status—a step where tickets lingered until a test engineer was available to pick them up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some, the absence of this status felt like a loss of control. To them, their &amp;ldquo;cheese was missing,&amp;rdquo; but it felt like something was actually broken.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When discussions in the channel veered toward resistance rather than solutions, I sent a message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m hearing &amp;rsquo;this thing doesn&amp;rsquo;t work like it did before&amp;rsquo;—and that&amp;rsquo;s kind of the point. The first couple of sprints may have growing pains, but we owe it to the people who spent time designing this to see if it works as intended. We want to hear feedback, but let’s give it a little time before making big changes.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Admittedly, I felt anxious after hitting send. Pushing back publicly wasn’t in my comfort zone. But the response—a trio of heart emojis from process designers and positive feedback from project leads in a private DM—was reaffirming. They appreciated that I stood firm, giving the new workflow the time and space to succeed before yielding to reactionary changes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I later offered office hours to help teams adapt to the new process. While there weren’t many takers, it signaled to me that teams were finding ways to work through the adjustment. Now, as we enter Sprint 2, I’m eager to evaluate pain points after completing Sprint 3 and ensure the process is genuinely serving its purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What stood out most to me was how this moment taught me something about myself. By holding boundaries and embracing discomfort, I discovered a steadying presence I hadn’t fully recognized until I received that comment in passing today. It’s a trait I’ll nurture, as it not only supports me but also adds value to my teams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day change can feel unsettling—but sometimes missing cheese just means it’s time to find a new snack. 😉&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Have you ever experienced “missing cheese” in your workflows or team processes? Share your thoughts in the comments! How do you balance patience with addressing feedback during times of change?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Atomic Habits: The Fundamentals</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/atomic-habits-part1/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/atomic-habits-part1/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/atomic-habits-part1/cover.jpeg" alt="Featured image of post Atomic Habits: The Fundamentals" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;After finally shaking off the holiday slump, I dove into the introduction section of James Clear&amp;rsquo;s &lt;em&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/em&gt;. Titled &lt;em&gt;The Fundamentals: Why Tiny Changes Make a Big Difference&lt;/em&gt;, this section lays the groundwork for Clear&amp;rsquo;s approach to behavior change. He introduces key concepts, such as how small habits can lead to big outcomes and the role of identity in building lasting change. He also outlines his &amp;ldquo;Four Laws of Behavior Change,&amp;rdquo; which I’ll explore more as I progress through the book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="identity-and-behavior-change"&gt;Identity and Behavior Change
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;I’ve already reflected on the role of identity in behavior change in my &lt;a class="link" href="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/hello-world/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;first blog post&lt;/a&gt;. As part of my daily routine, I remind myself of my targeted identity: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I am healthy. I am present. I am OK with failure.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; This practice has helped me stay focused on the person I want to become.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, on those evenings when I’d rather skip a workout and veg out on the couch with a bag of chips, I pause and ask myself: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;What would a healthy person do right now?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt; More often than not, this mindset gets me moving—maybe it’s just a short workout, but it’s still progress. And yes, I still veg out afterward—but without the chips!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="goals-vs-systems"&gt;Goals vs. Systems
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clear makes a compelling case for focusing on systems rather than goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Goals are about the results you want to achieve. Systems are about the processes that lead to those results.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This distinction resonated with me. Many successful people unknowingly excel at creating systems that enable their success. Clear simply sheds light on what’s happening behind the scenes. To make lasting change, you need systems that support your habits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Take writing, for example. If I want to improve as a writer, I need systems that enable consistency. That means having a blog to publish my work, a running list of ideas, and time set aside for planning, writing, and editing. Without those systems in place, my goal to “write more” wouldn’t get very far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-power-of-tiny-changes"&gt;The Power of Tiny Changes
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clear challenges the myth that big changes come from dramatic, life-altering moments. Instead, he argues that small, consistent improvements lead to significant results over time:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s so easy to overestimate the importance of one defining moment and underestimate the value of making small improvements on a daily basis.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This idea hit home for me. I often struggle with being a beginner and lack patience when I don’t see immediate results. This mindset has led me to fall into two traps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting overly ambitious goals or routines, then giving up when I fail to stick to them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dismissing small opportunities to make progress—if I only have 5 or 10 minutes, it feels “not worth it,” so I do nothing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clear’s emphasis on tiny changes encourages me to flip those reactions on their heads:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Focus on themes and identity shifts rather than rigid, black-and-white goals. This approach aligns with my &lt;a class="link" href="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/hello-world/#theme-ing-in-the-new-year-" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;yearly themes&lt;/a&gt;, where I aim to channel effort into broader systems of growth rather than specific, binary outcomes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Embrace all progress, no matter how small. Even 10 minutes in the car listening to an audiobook is valuable—it’s time I wouldn’t have spent otherwise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-do-you-think"&gt;What Do You Think?
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Clear’s insights on systems over goals and the impact of small, consistent changes are already shifting how I approach habit-building. What about you? Do you focus more on changing systems or setting goals? How do you view the value of tiny changes? Let me know in the comments—I’d love to hear your thoughts!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m excited to continue exploring &lt;em&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/em&gt; and see what practical strategies Clear shares. Next up is &lt;em&gt;The First Law: Make It Obvious.&lt;/em&gt; I hope you’ll join me for the next post in this Book Club series!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Building the Foundation: Lessons and Wins from Blog Iteration One</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/blog-part-1/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/blog-part-1/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/blog-part-1/cover.jpeg" alt="Featured image of post Building the Foundation: Lessons and Wins from Blog Iteration One" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;One purpose of this blog is to make sure I’m keeping my hands on the keyboard so I don’t drift too far from coding, even though I’ve transitioned into a management role. Truthfully, it’s been nearly three years since I’ve coded with any real focus, and, well, I’ve forgotten &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Writing this post also pushes me out of my comfort zone by doing something I find challenging: documenting my technical skillset and confronting where I fall short. I’ve never been great at not being great at something, and software development often feels like “going against the grain” for me. It doesn’t help that I work with some incredibly talented developers—comparing my skills to theirs feels like dropping a stone in my stomach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That said, this blog is about growth. And I know I’ll never expand my boundaries if I don’t push against them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="blog-10"&gt;Blog 1.0
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;The blog you’re reading now is actually my second full build and deploy. When I first spun up a Hugo project, I struggled to get my theme-of-choice to work. Instead of dwelling in that discomfort (noticing a trend?), I decided to build and style everything myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The result? Functional but awful. I had a homepage, an About page, post pages, and an article list, but it all looked a little bit like my MySpace circa 2004. Once I deployed it, I immediately knew it wasn’t my best work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A UX designer, I am not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I scrapped it all, read up on Hugo themes, and voilà—here we are. This version feels much more polished and streamlined, and I’m excited to keep iterating on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="friction-points-and-takeaways"&gt;Friction points and Takeaways
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;There were definitely some bumps along the way. Here are the biggest challenges and lessons learned:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Remembering CSS.&lt;/strong&gt;
I don’t miss fiddling with selectors and flexbox, but nothing beats the rush of seeing something finally look like the idea in your head after 20 minutes of tinkering in the browser inspector.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reading technical documentation.&lt;/strong&gt;
I struggle with reading through dense technical docs—it sometimes feels like decoding another language. Hugo’s structure took me longer to understand than I’d care to admit, but persistence paid off. Now, I know where to put things to make them work as intended.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deployment.&lt;/strong&gt;
This blog is currently deployed via GitHub Pages, which I’m familiar with. However, I wanted to use GCP to align with the tooling my team works with. My first attempt failed (likely a DNS configuration issue), so I pivoted to get the blog up and running. I’ll circle back to GCP deployment soon.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ChatGPT&lt;/strong&gt;
Wow. If this had existed when I was learning to code, I wonder how it would have shaped my career. It helped me clear several hurdles, but I’m also grappling with whether it’s becoming a crutch. Generative AI is just another tool—like a calculator—but I can’t help but wonder what I might miss by relying on it too much.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="status-update"&gt;Status Update
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;rsquo;s where things stand after this iteration:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;
&lt;thead&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;th&gt;To Do 📋&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Completed ✅&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;th&gt;Revisit ♻️&lt;/th&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/thead&gt;
&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add GA 4 tracking&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Deploy Blog&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;GCP deployment&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Make SEO improvements&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;First post&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Hugo documentation&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Investigate metadata and update&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add newsletter sign up&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Add Disqus for comments&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;Promote on LinkedIn&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;td&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
&lt;/tr&gt;
&lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This journey has already been a learning experience, and I’m looking forward to iterating further.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you tackled a similar project? Struggled with CSS selectors or documentation that felt like another language? I’d love to hear about your experiences! Drop your thoughts, tips, or questions in the comments below—I’m excited to learn from you, too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stay tuned as I keep figuring it out!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Hello World</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/hello-world/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/hello-world/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/hello-world/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Hello World" /&gt;&lt;h1 id="welcome-to-my-little-space-on-the-internet"&gt;Welcome to my little space on the internet
&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Hi there, I’m Ashley.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here, you’ll find a collection of ramblings and thoughts—some half-baked, others a bit more polished—about the everyday adventure of learning, growing, and trying to make life a bit more meaningful. I’ll write about all sorts of things: what I’m discovering about being a better leader, mother, wife, friend, and how to juggle it all. But it’s not just about the roles we play—it’s about the little moments, the lessons, and the quirks that shape our journeys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And yes, I’ll be using generative AI to help me shape some of these words, because sometimes even the best ideas need a little digital nudge. Consider this space an experiment, a place to reflect, and—hopefully—a space where you’ll find something that resonates with your own story. Glad you’re here to join me in the process!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="so-anyway-happy-new-year-"&gt;So Anyway, Happy New Year! 🎉
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;This year, I’m not doing resolutions. There’s plenty of online discourse about how resolutions never stick, so I won’t dwell on that. But I will say that I’ve never been able to see a resolution through. So, I’ve decided to try a different approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This shift comes from two key inspirations: &lt;em&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/em&gt; by James Clear and my coaching sessions through Torch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="the-influence-of-atomic-habits"&gt;The Influence of &lt;em&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a class="link" href="https://jamesclear.com/atomic-habits" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Atomic Habits&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; was (admittedly) a recommendation from my coach—thanks, &lt;a class="link" href="https://worth.am" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Tanner&lt;/a&gt;! A few points made in the opening chapters solidified my new approach: I need to make the changes I desire a part of my identity. According to Clear, “true behavior change is identity change” because our behaviors ultimately reflect our identity. If we behave in a way that conflicts with who we are, those behaviors won’t stick.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="themes-vs-goals"&gt;Themes vs. Goals
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In my work with Tanner, we’re focusing on themes to create habits that foster change and growth rather than rigid goals. Goals are great for identifying where you want to end up, but they often overlook the processes that get you there. As Clear notes, achieving a goal “only changes your life for a moment.” Without changing the underlying systems or identity that led to setting the goal in the first place, the change won’t last.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By using themes, I’m supporting the identity I’ve defined for myself while building the systems needed for lasting change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="new-year-new-me-"&gt;New Year, New Me 💁🏻‍♀️
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;Here are the aspects of my identity I want to foster and focus on this year:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am healthy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am present.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am coping in a healthy way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am OK with failure.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am clean, neat, and tidy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am a good friend, wife, mother, daughter, boss, and coworker.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These traits align with past goals and resolutions that have fallen off the rails, as well as parts of myself I like and want to reinforce.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that I’m on the other side of growing and birthing two little humans, I want to return to caring for my body and mind. That means working out, eating healthy, and choosing to be more active. It also means putting my phone down more often and finding healthier ways to cope with hard days.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to be more vulnerable and brave, allowing myself to fail. Growth and learning often happen in those moments of failure, and I don’t want to miss out. These identity traits support the direction I want to take myself in this year and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="theme-ing-in-the-new-year-"&gt;Theme-ing in the New Year 🎊
&lt;/h2&gt;&lt;p&gt;My 2025 themes are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Nourishment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Routine&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mindfulness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="nourishment"&gt;Nourishment
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Nourishment is about more than feeding my body healthy foods. It’s about:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Completing the skincare routine I’ve been planning for months.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Taking a walk to get fresh air in the middle of the day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reading a book that makes me think—or helps me escape.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reconnecting with my husband on a night out.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Traveling to explore new places.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Getting back into baking and experimenting in the kitchen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are all things that support a healthy mind and body, help me find work-life balance, and keep me present in my day-to-day life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="routine"&gt;Routine
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Routines will help support my journey of nourishment. I want to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Go to bed at the same time every night with a consistent pre-bed routine (hello, skincare!).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do a “closing shift” each night to ensure the living space is tidy for the next day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stick to personal growth habits like journaling, setting daily goals, and dedicating time each week to learning about leadership or technology topics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id="mindfulness"&gt;Mindfulness
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;Man, I am always distracted—thinking about the next meeting, answering Slack messages in that meeting, or scrolling Instagram at dinner.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to pull myself out of those moments and check in with where I am and what I should be doing. Whether at work, with my family, or with friends, I want to be fully present. Life moves fast, and I don’t want to miss it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading and letting me share a little bit of my journey. I’m excited about what this project might become, and I hope that in a year, I can look back at this blog and see how far I’ve come. I hope you’ll come back and see what I’ve been up to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Happy New Year! 🎉&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enjoyed this post?&lt;/strong&gt;
Sign up for my newsletter to get updates on new posts, tips, and behind-the-scenes insights!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;header class="article-category"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://ashleyedds-figuringitout.kit.com/signup" style="background-color:#8ea885;"&gt;Subscribe Now&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/header&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>