<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Time Management on Figuring it Out</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/tags/time-management/</link><description>Recent content in Time Management on Figuring it Out</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ashleyedds.dev/tags/time-management/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Power of Immediate Action: How I Tamed My Endless To-Do List</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/immediate-action/</link><pubDate>Thu, 10 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/immediate-action/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/immediate-action/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post The Power of Immediate Action: How I Tamed My Endless To-Do List" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;I have a secret. Don’t worry, it’s a good one—and I’m happy to share it with you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first became an Engineering Manager, I felt like I was drowning. My “To Do” column in Trello, my notebook, and my brain kept expanding like a balloon, no matter how many tasks I knocked out. And those are the tasks that I didn&amp;rsquo;t forget to keep record of&amp;hellip;there were many that just fell through the cracks. I was attending back-to-back meetings, responding to Slack messages, trying to think strategically, and still expected to deliver tangible results. Everything felt equally urgent, and the pressure to perform without dropping the ball was intense. I considered working late every night just to keep up, but let’s be real—that’s a shortcut to burnout.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what changed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One small shift made a big difference: &lt;strong&gt;Immediate action&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not a magic bullet for every task, but it’s been incredibly effective for the small, high-context action items that are easy to forget. You know the ones—send a follow-up message, file a ticket for access, start a shared doc, ask someone for a clarification. Things that don’t require deep focus but can easily slip through the cracks if left for later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, when I’m in a meeting and someone mentions needing IT access, I file the ticket right then. If we need input from someone who isn’t present, I send them a quick Slack or email immediately. If we need a document to capture notes or decisions, I open it and share it before the meeting ends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This approach has two major benefits:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Momentum&lt;/strong&gt;: Even if the task isn’t fully complete, it’s already moving. There’s energy and attention on it. In many cases, that’s enough to keep it progressing.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Trust&lt;/strong&gt;: My team and cross-functional partners now know that when they ask for something, it won’t vanish into the void. I’ve built a reputation for being responsive, and that builds confidence and credibility over time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me be clear—this doesn’t mean I multitask my way through every meeting. I prioritize quick, low-effort actions that I can complete in 30-90 seconds. For deeper asks, I jot them down and return to them later with full focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a couple of caveats, though. Acting immediately can sometimes mean I’m not 100% focused on the current conversation. I’ve missed a few small details here and there—but in my experience, the trade-off is worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also, this strategy works for me because I don’t struggle with attention redirection. I understand this isn’t the case for everyone. If you have attention-related challenges, this method might feel overwhelming or counterproductive. That’s okay—there are other ways to harness the same principle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some alternatives to try:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Leave 5–10 minutes at the end of each meeting&lt;/strong&gt; to knock out those quick tasks before jumping to the next one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create a running “Immediate Action” list&lt;/strong&gt; during meetings and batch-process them during your next break.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Use keyboard shortcuts, templates, and automation tools&lt;/strong&gt; to reduce friction for repeatable tasks.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The heart of the idea is this: the faster you give a task momentum, the more likely it is to get done—and the more others will see you as reliable, effective, and “on it.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="what-works-for-you"&gt;What Works for You?
&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;If immediate action isn’t your style, what &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt;? How do you stay on top of your fast-moving task list without burning out? I’d love to hear your strategies and hacks. Let’s share notes—after all, we’re all just figuring it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Feel free to leave a comment or reach out directly. I’m always looking to expand my toolkit—and yours too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let’s connect.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
If this resonated with you, consider subscribing to the blog or sharing it with someone who might benefit. We&amp;rsquo;re all learning how to lead and live better, one tiny change at a time.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>