<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>SEO on Figuring it Out</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/tags/seo/</link><description>Recent content in SEO on Figuring it Out</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ashleyedds.dev/tags/seo/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Learning GA4 and Rediscovering the Joy of Growth</title><link>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/ga4-new-learning/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://ashleyedds.dev/p/ga4-new-learning/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://ashleyedds.dev/p/ga4-new-learning/cover.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Learning GA4 and Rediscovering the Joy of Growth" /&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last week, I earned my first new certification in years: &lt;a class="link" href="https://skillshop.exceedlms.com/student/catalog/list?category_ids=53-google-analytics" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
&gt;Google Analytics&lt;/a&gt;, offered through Google Skillshop. And let me tell you—it felt &lt;strong&gt;SO GOOD&lt;/strong&gt;. From watching the videos and taking notes, to studying for the final exam, to finally passing and posting that shiny little badge on LinkedIn, I felt a sense of pride that I hadn’t experienced in a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally got to be the one to say: &lt;em&gt;&amp;ldquo;I&amp;rsquo;m happy to share that I&amp;hellip;&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But beyond the badge, I’m proud of something deeper: the small, intentional choices I made that allowed me to chip away at the coursework despite a jam-packed schedule. Choosing to log in instead of doomscroll. Prioritizing my own growth alongside my responsibilities as a manager. Investing in myself again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not that I haven’t been learning—stepping into management, navigating a new tech stack, and entering the world of e-commerce was like jumping off a cliff into deep water. But this was different. This was structured, focused learning that I chose. And it reminded me how much I &lt;em&gt;missed&lt;/em&gt; that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Understanding Google Analytics 4 was a key step for me as a leader. I’d never worked with SEO before—didn’t even realize how closely it ties into software development and data collection. I used to sit silently in meetings while our product managers and engineers discussed upcoming tagging work or issues with a poorly performing page. I’d listen, absorb, and nod&amp;hellip; but rarely contribute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now? After just one certification, I’ve already seen the impact. We just wrapped up our Q2 Big Room Planning, and for the first time, I was able to ask intelligent questions about data collection strategies for a new set of pages we’re rolling out. I even caught a user flow issue that hadn’t been considered yet—&lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; suggested a tagging approach to help track it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It felt empowering.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The combination of new knowledge and immediate application was an absolute rush. I remembered how curiosity, when nurtured, turns into confidence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now I’m hooked. I’m ready to keep going. But what next?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should I dive into &lt;strong&gt;Google Cloud Platform&lt;/strong&gt; (GCP) training to get more comfortable with the infrastructure side of things? Are there deeper SEO-related topics—like structured data, schema markup, or Lighthouse audits—that I should explore? What would help me show up even stronger for my team and our cross-functional partners?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve recently learned something new that shifted how you work, I’d love to hear about it. Let’s trade notes. Or if you’ve taken GCP or SEO courses you really liked, send them my way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s to the next learning curve. I’m ready.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;✨ Got suggestions for what I should learn next?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Drop them in the comments, message me on LinkedIn, or send a carrier pigeon. I’m serious—I want to hear what’s helped you grow. Let’s build a little learning community together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And if you’ve been putting off that course, certification, or passion project? This is your nudge. Start today. A little at a time adds up, I promise.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>